<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Statute PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Statute v2.0.0//EN" "Dtd/Version_2.0.0/Statute/Statute.dtd"><Statute bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes"><Identification><BillNumber>C-3</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>62-63</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2013-2014</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the indemnity of certain aviation industry participants for certain events</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Aviation Industry Indemnity Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Aviation Industry Indemnity</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>06</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2014</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>9</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber official="no">A-18.5</ConsolidatedNumber><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>29, s. 2</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2014</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><ReaderNote><Note status="editorial">[Enacted by section 2 of chapter 29 of the Statutes of Canada, 2014, in force on assent December 9, 2014.]</Note></ReaderNote></Identification><Introduction><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text /></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aviation Industry Indemnity Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>airport</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>aéroport</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>aviation industry participant</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>participant de l’industrie aérienne</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>aviation industry participant</DefinedTermEn> means </Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an air carrier, as defined in subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>, that is a Canadian, as defined in subsection 55(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Transportation Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>NAV CANADA, a corporation incorporated on May 26, 1995 under Part II of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Corporations Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an owner or operator of an airport;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a supplier of goods or services that directly support the operation of aircraft from an airport, including with respect to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the preparation of an aircraft for departure or on its arrival, including maintenance and cleaning of the aircraft and the loading and unloading of passengers, baggage and cargo,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>freight forwarding,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>air navigation, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>airport security services; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>an entity that is prescribed by regulation or a member of a class of entity that is prescribed by regulation.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>event</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>événement</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>event</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an act of unlawful interference with an aircraft, airport or air navigation facility, including an act of terrorism; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an act or omission in the course of armed conflict, war, invasion, hostilities, civil war, revolution, rebellion, insurrection, an application of martial law, a usurpation or attempted usurpation of power, a civil commotion or a riot.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Transport.</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Undertaking</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Undertaking by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, in writing, undertake to indemnify one or more aviation industry participants  —  or one or more classes of aviation industry participant  —  against their loss or damage, or liability for loss or damage, that is caused by an event.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The undertaking to indemnify is limited to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>loss, damage or liability, or any portion of it, that is not insured or otherwise indemnified; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>loss, damage or liability that is not solely with respect to a loss of income.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Terms</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may attach terms to an undertaking, including terms that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>specify the event or class of event that is covered by the undertaking or that is excluded from coverage;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>specify the activity or class of activity in which an aviation industry participant engages that is covered by the undertaking or that is excluded from coverage;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>specify the class of loss, damage or liability that is covered by the undertaking or that is excluded from coverage;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>establish the maximum amount of indemnification, or the method to determine that amount, that may be paid out to an aviation industry participant per event;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>require that an aviation industry participant obtain a specified minimum amount of insurance coverage for events; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>require that an aviation industry participant enter, at the Minister’s request, into an agreement with the Minister respecting the conduct or settlement of any proceedings to which the participant is a party that are related to loss, damage or liability covered by the undertaking.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Different terms</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In attaching terms to an undertaking, the Minister may distinguish among aviation industry participants, including among aviation industry participants of the same class, and may distinguish among classes of aviation industry participants.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Incorporation by reference</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An undertaking may incorporate any material by reference, regardless of its source, as it exists on a particular date.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No delegation</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Minister must personally exercise the powers that are set out in this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to an undertaking.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause an undertaking, an amended undertaking or a notice of revocation of an undertaking to be published in Part I of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> within 23 days after the issuance, amendment or revocation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Request for information</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>At any time after the Minister issues an undertaking, he or she may request that aviation industry participants who are covered by the undertaking provide him or her with any information that he or she specifies, including with respect to their eligibility and their existing level of insurance coverage for events covered by the undertaking.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Claim for Indemnification</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of potential claim</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An aviation industry participant must provide the Minister with a written notice of a potential claim within two years after the day on which the event that could give rise to a claim occurred.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information to be provided</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The aviation industry participant must provide the Minister with any additional information that the Minister considers necessary in the circumstances.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Claim and indemnification</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>After an aviation industry participant submits a written claim for indemnification under an undertaking, the Minister must review the claim and  —  if a notice was provided in accordance with section <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal> and the Minister determines that the claim is eligible for indemnification under the undertaking as it read on the day on which the event that gave rise to the claim occurred  —  indemnify the participant accordingly.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Further information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The aviation industry participant must provide the Minister with any additional information that the Minister considers necessary to determine if the claim is eligible for indemnification.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deeming  — single event</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Minister considers that two or more events are directly connected by any factor or factors, including timing, cause or the parties involved, he or she may deem the events to be a single event.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reliance on court or tribunal</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister may, in determining if a claim is eligible for indemnification, rely on a final determination, not subject to any appeal, of a court or other tribunal, in or outside Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Fault of aviation industry participant</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), the Minister is not required to indemnify an aviation industry participant if the Minister is of the opinion that the loss, damage or liability claimed is principally the fault of the aviation industry participant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the Minister’s determination of whether the claim is eligible for indemnification includes a determination of the amount, if any, of the indemnification.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Consolidated Revenue Fund</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>Any amount payable under an undertaking is to be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Subrogation</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Her Majesty is subrogated, to the extent of a payment under an undertaking to an aviation industry participant, to all of the participant’s rights in respect of the loss, damage or liability for which the payment was made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Action</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Her Majesty may maintain an action, in the aviation industry participant’s name or in the name of Her Majesty, against any person to enforce those rights.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Assessment and Report</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Assessment</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>The Minister must, at least once every two years, assess whether it is feasible for aviation industry participants to obtain insurance coverage for events or other similar coverage.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must prepare a report on his or her activities under this Act within</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>90 days after the day on which he or she issued, amended or revoked an undertaking; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>two years after the day on which a report was last tabled, if he or she has not, within that period, issued, amended or revoked an undertaking.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling in Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause each report to be tabled in each House of Parliament within the first 15 days on which the House is sitting after the report is prepared.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Governor in Council</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the Minister’s recommendation, make regulations for the purpose of this Act, including regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prescribing an entity or class of entity for the purpose of the definition <DefinedTermEn>aviation industry participant</DefinedTermEn> in section <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>respecting the circumstances in which an undertaking may cover only one aviation industry participant.</Text></Paragraph></Section></Body></Statute>