<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE Statute PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Statute v2.0.0//EN" "Dtd/Version_2.0.0/Statute/Statute.dtd"><Statute bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes"><Identification><LongTitle>An Act respecting DNA identification and to make consequential amendments to the Criminal Code and other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">DNA Identification Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>DNA Identification</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>1998</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>10</DD></Date></Stages><Stages stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>06</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber official="no">D-3.8</ConsolidatedNumber><AnnualStatuteId revised-statute="no"><AnnualStatuteNumber>37</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>1998</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter></Identification><Introduction><Enacts><Provision language-align="no" format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">DNA Identification Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The definitions in this section apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>authorization</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>autorisation</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>authorization</DefinedTermEn> means an authorization made under section 487.055 or 487.091 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or section 196.24 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>commissaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> means the Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>infraction désignée</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> means a designated offence within the meaning of section 487.04 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or section 196.11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>DNA</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ADN</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>DNA</DefinedTermEn> means deoxyribonucleic acid.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>DNA profile</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>profil d’identification génétique</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>DNA profile</DefinedTermEn> means the results of forensic DNA analysis of a bodily substance.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>forensic DNA analysis</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>analyse génétique</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>forensic DNA analysis</DefinedTermEn>, in relation to a bodily substance, means forensic DNA analysis of the bodily substance.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>order</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ordonnance</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>order</DefinedTermEn> means an order made under section 487.051 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or section 196.14 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Young Offenders Act</XRefExternal></DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur les jeunes contrevenants</XRefExternal></DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Young Offenders Act</XRefExternal></DefinedTermEn> means chapter Y-1 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>young person</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>adolescent</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>young person</DefinedTermEn> has the meaning assigned by subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal> or subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Young Offenders Act</XRefExternal>, as the case may be.</Text></Definition><HistoricalNote>1998, c. 37, s. 2; 2000, c. 10, s. 4; 2002, c. 1, s. 187; 2005, c. 25, s. 14; 2007, c. 22, s. 27.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Purpose</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label><FootnoteRef idref="D-3.8_en_1">*</FootnoteRef>3</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to establish a national DNA data bank to help law enforcement agencies identify persons alleged to have committed designated offences, including those committed before the coming into force of this Act.</Text><Footnote id="D-3.8_en_1" placement="section" status="editorial" xml:space="default"><Label>*</Label><Text>[Note: Sections 2, 3 and 12 in force May 8, 2000, see SI/2000-37; sections 1, 4 to 11 and 13 to 25 in force June 30, 2000, <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/2000-60.]</Text></Footnote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Principles</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Principles</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>It is recognized and declared that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the protection of society and the administration of justice are well served by the early detection, arrest and conviction of offenders, which can be facilitated by the use of DNA profiles;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the DNA profiles, as well as samples of bodily substances from which the profiles are derived, may be used only for law enforcement purposes in accordance with this Act, and not for any unauthorized purpose; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>to protect the privacy of individuals with respect to personal information about themselves, safeguards must be placed on</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the use and communication of, and access to, DNA profiles and other information contained in the national DNA data bank, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the use of, and access to, bodily substances that are transmitted to the Commissioner for the purposes of this Act.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><HistoricalNote>1998, c. 37, s. 4; 2000, c. 10, s. 5.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National DNA Data Bank</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness shall, for criminal identification purposes, establish a national DNA data bank, consisting of a crime scene index and a convicted offenders index, to be maintained by the Commissioner.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Commissioner’s duties</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commissioner’s duties under this Act may be performed on behalf of the Commissioner by any person authorized by the Commissioner to perform those duties.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Crime scene index</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The crime scene index shall contain DNA profiles derived from bodily substances that are found</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>at any place where a designated offence was committed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on or within the body of the victim of a designated offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>on anything worn or carried by the victim at the time when a designated offence was committed; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>on or within the body of any person or thing or at any place associated with the commission of a designated offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Convicted offenders index</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The convicted offenders index shall contain DNA profiles derived from bodily substances that are taken under orders and authorizations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other information</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>In addition to the DNA profiles referred to in subsections (3) and (4), the DNA data bank shall contain, in relation to each of the profiles, information from which can be established</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of a profile in the crime scene index, the case number of the investigation associated with the bodily substance from which the profile was derived; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of a profile in the convicted offenders index, the identity of the person from whose bodily substance the profile was derived.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote>1998, c. 37, s. 5; 2000, c. 10, s. 6; 2005, c. 10, s. 34, c. 25, s. 15; 2007, c. 22, s. 28.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Review of information transmitted</MarginalNote><Label>5.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner shall review the information transmitted under section 487.071 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or section 196.22 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> to ensure that the offence referred to in the order or authorization is a designated offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Forensic DNA analysis</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commissioner shall conduct a forensic DNA analysis of the bodily substances transmitted if satisfied that the offence referred to in the order or authorization is a designated offence and enter the resulting DNA profile in the convicted offenders index.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Retention of order or authorization</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Commissioner shall retain the copy of the order or authorization transmitted under subsection 487.071(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or subsection 196.22(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 25, s. 16; 2007, c. 22, s. 29.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Defect in order or authorization</MarginalNote><Label>5.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Commissioner is of the opinion that the offence referred to in the order or authorization is not a designated offence, the Commissioner shall retain any bodily substances collected under it and any information transmitted with it, and give notice of the apparent defect to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Attorney General of the province in which the order or authorization was made, if it was transmitted under section 487.071 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Director of Military Prosecutions, if the order or authorization was transmitted under section 196.22 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confirmation or correction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Attorney General or Director of Military Prosecutions, as the case may be, confirms in writing that the order or authorization is valid or sends a copy of a corrected order or authorization to the Commissioner, the Commissioner shall conduct a forensic DNA analysis of any bodily substances collected under it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Substantive defect</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Attorney General or the Director of Military Prosecutions, as the case may be, informs the Commissioner that the offence referred to in the order or authorization is not a designated offence, the Commissioner shall, without delay, destroy the bodily substances collected under the order or authorization and the information transmitted with it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Destruction of bodily substances</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Commissioner shall destroy any bodily substances and information retained under subsection (1) on the expiry of 180 days after sending a notice under that subsection unless, before the expiry of that period, the Commissioner receives</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a confirmation that the order or authorization is valid;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a corrected order or authorization;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a notice that the Attorney General or Director of Military Prosecutions requires an additional period of not greater than 90 days to review the order or authorization; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a notice that the issue of whether or not the order or authorization is defective is under review by a judge or in proceedings before a court.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 25, s. 16; 2007, c. 22, s. 30.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Communication of information</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner shall compare any DNA profile that is entered in the convicted offenders index or the crime scene index with those DNA profiles that are already contained in the data bank and may then, for the purpose of the investigation of a criminal offence, communicate the following information to any Canadian law enforcement agency or laboratory that the Commissioner considers appropriate:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if the DNA profile is not already contained in the data bank, the fact that it is not;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the DNA profile is already contained in the data bank, the information contained in the data bank in relation to that DNA profile;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if the DNA profile is, in the opinion of the Commissioner, similar to one that is already contained in the data bank, the similar DNA profile; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>if a law enforcement agency or laboratory advises the Commissioner that their comparison of a DNA profile communicated under paragraph (c) with one that is connected to the commission of a criminal offence has not excluded the former as a possible match, the information contained in the data bank in relation to that profile.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authorized users</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Information as to whether a person’s DNA profile is contained in the convicted offenders index may be communicated to an authorized user of the automated criminal conviction records retrieval system maintained by the Royal Canadian Mounted Police.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Foreign law enforcement agencies</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On receipt of a DNA profile from the government of a foreign state, an international organization established by the governments of states or an institution of such a government or international organization, the Commissioner may compare the profile with those in the DNA data bank to determine whether it is already contained in the data bank and may then communicate to the government, organization or institution</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the information referred to in any of paragraphs (1)(a) to (c) in the circumstances referred to in that paragraph; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the information contained in the data bank in relation to a DNA profile communicated to the government, organization or institution in the circumstances set out in paragraph (1)(c) if the government, organization or institution advises the Commissioner that their comparison of that DNA profile with one that is connected to the commission of a criminal offence has not excluded the former as a possible match.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Communication of DNA profile</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may, on the request of a law enforcement agency in the course of the investigation of a designated offence, communicate a DNA profile contained in the crime scene index to the government of a foreign state, an international organization established by the governments of states or an institution of any such government or international organization.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Agreement or arrangement</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsections (3) and (4) apply only if the Government of Canada or one of its institutions has entered into an agreement or arrangement, in accordance with paragraph 8(2)(f) of the  <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal>, with that government, international organization or institution, as the case may be, authorizing the communication solely for the purposes of the investigation or prosecution of a criminal offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Use of results — order, authorization</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>No person shall use the results of forensic DNA analysis of bodily substances that are taken in execution of an order or authorization, except in accordance with this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsequent communication</MarginalNote><Label>(6.1)</Label><Text>Information that is communicated under subsection (1) may be communicated subsequently to a person to whom the communication is necessary for the purpose of the investigation or prosecution of a criminal offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Unauthorized communication</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Subject to this section, no person shall communicate any information that is contained in the DNA data bank or allow the information to be communicated.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>1998, c. 37, s. 6; 2000, c. 10, s. 7; 2005, c. 25, s. 17; 2007, c. 22, s. 31.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Access to information</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>Access to information contained in the DNA data bank may be granted to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any person or class of persons that the Commissioner considers appropriate for the purposes of the proper operation and maintenance of the DNA data bank; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the personnel of any laboratories that the Commissioner considers appropriate for training purposes.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Unauthorized use of information</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>No person to whom information is communicated under subsection 6(1) or (6.1) or who has access to information under paragraph 7(a) or (b) shall use that information other than for the purposes referred to in that subsection or paragraph.</Text><HistoricalNote>1998, c. 37, s. 8; 2005, c. 25, s. 17.1.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Crime scene index</MarginalNote><Label>8.1</Label><Text>Access to the information in the crime scene index shall be permanently removed, in accordance with any regulations that may be made under this Act, if the information relates to a DNA profile derived from a bodily substance of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a victim of a designated offence that was the object of the relevant investigation; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a person who has been eliminated as a suspect in the relevant investigation.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Information to be kept indefinitely</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), section 9.1 and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Records Act</XRefExternal>, information in the convicted offenders index shall be kept indefinitely.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information to be permanently removed</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Access to information in the convicted offenders index shall be permanently removed</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>without delay after every order or authorization for the collection of bodily substances from the person to whom the information relates is finally set aside;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>without delay after the person is finally acquitted of every designated offence in connection with which an order was made or an authorization was granted; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>one year after the day on which the person is discharged absolutely, or three years after the day on which they are discharged conditionally, of a designated offence under section 730 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> if they are not subject to an order or authorization that relates to another designated offence and are neither convicted of, nor found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, a designated offence during that period.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote>1998, c. 37, s. 9; 2000, c. 10, s. 8; 2005, c. 25, s. 18; 2007, c. 22, s. 32.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Young persons — access to information removed</MarginalNote><Label>9.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Access to information in the convicted offenders index in relation to a young person who has been found guilty under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Young Offenders Act</XRefExternal> or under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal> of a designated offence shall be permanently removed without delay when the record relating to the same offence is required to be destroyed, sealed or transmitted to the National Archivist of Canada under Part 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 9 nevertheless applies to information in the convicted offenders index in relation to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a serious violent offence as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a record to which subsection 120(6) of that Act applies.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 9; 2005, c. 25, s. 19; 2012, c. 1, s. 202.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Storage of bodily substances</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When bodily substances are transmitted to the Commissioner under section 487.071 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or section 196.22 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, the Commissioner shall, subject to this section and section 10.1, safely and securely store, for the purpose of forensic DNA analysis, the portions of the samples of the bodily substances that the Commissioner considers appropriate and without delay destroy any remaining portions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Change in technology</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Forensic DNA analysis of stored bodily substances may be performed if the Commissioner is of the opinion that the analysis is justified because significant technological advances have been made since the time when a DNA profile of the person who provided the bodily substances, or from whom they were taken, was last derived.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2005, c. 25, s. 20]</Repealed></Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Access</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Access to stored bodily substances may be granted to any person or class of persons that the Commissioner considers appropriate for the purpose of preserving the bodily substances.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Use of bodily substances</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>No person shall transmit stored bodily substances to any person or use stored bodily substances except for the purpose of forensic DNA analysis.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Later destruction</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may at any time destroy any or all of the stored bodily substances if the Commissioner considers that they are no longer required for the purpose of forensic DNA analysis.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Mandatory destruction in certain cases</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The Commissioner shall destroy the stored bodily substances of a person</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>without delay after every order or authorization for the collection of bodily substances from the person is finally set aside;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>without delay after the person is finally acquitted of every designated offence in connection with which an order was made or an authorization was granted; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>one year after the day on which the person is discharged absolutely, or three years after the day on which they are discharged conditionally, of a designated offence under section 730 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> if they are not subject to an order or authorization that relates to another designated offence and are neither convicted of, nor found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, a designated offence during that period.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When record suspension is in effect</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Despite anything in this section, stored bodily substances of a person in respect of whom a record suspension, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Records Act</XRefExternal>, is in effect shall be kept separate and apart from other stored bodily substances, and no such bodily substance shall be used for forensic DNA analysis, nor shall the existence of such a bodily substance be communicated to any person.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>1998, c. 37, s. 10; 2000, c. 10, s. 10; 2005, c. 25, s. 20; 2007, c. 22, s. 33; 2012, c. 1, s. 148.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Young persons — destruction of bodily substances</MarginalNote><Label>10.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner shall, without delay, destroy stored bodily substances of a young person who has been found guilty of a designated offence under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Young Offenders Act</XRefExternal> or under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal> when the record relating to the same offence is required to be destroyed, sealed or transmitted to the National Archivist of Canada under Part 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 10(6) and (7) nevertheless apply to the destruction of stored bodily substances of a young person that relate to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a serious violent offence as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a record to which subsection 120(6) of that Act applies.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 11; 2005, c. 25, s. 21; 2012, c. 1, s. 203.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection 6(6) or (7), section 8 or subsection 10(5)</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to a fine not exceeding $2,000 or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months, or to both.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote>1998, c. 37, s. 11; 2005, c. 25, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review of Act by Parliamentary committee</MarginalNote><Label><FootnoteRef idref="D-3.8_en_2">*</FootnoteRef>13</Label><Text>Within five years after this Act comes into force, a review of the provisions and operation of this Act shall be undertaken by any committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament that is designated or established for that purpose.</Text><Footnote id="D-3.8_en_2" placement="section" status="editorial" xml:space="default"><Label>*</Label><Text>[Note: Sections 2, 3 and 12 in force May 8, 2000, see SI/2000-37; sections 1, 4 to 11 and 13 to 25 in force June 30, 2000, <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/2000-60.]</Text></Footnote><HistoricalNote>1998, c. 37, s. 13; 2000, c. 10, s. 12.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Report to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>13.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner shall, within three months after the end of each fiscal year, submit to the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness a report on the operations of the national DNA data bank for the year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling in Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause the report of the Commissioner to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after he or she receives it.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 12; 2005, c. 10, s. 26.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>14 to 25</Label><Text>[Amendments]</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label><FootnoteRef idref="D-3.8_en_3">*</FootnoteRef>26</Label><Text>This Act or any of its provisions or any provision of an Act enacted by this Act comes into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text><Footnote id="D-3.8_en_3" placement="section" status="editorial" xml:space="default"><Label>*</Label><Text>[Note: Sections 2, 3 and 12 in force May 8, 2000, <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/2000-37; sections 1, 4 to 11 and 13 to 25 in force June 30, 2000, <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/2000-60.]</Text></Footnote></Section></Body><Schedule id="RelatedProvs"><ScheduleFormHeading type="amending"><TitleText>RELATED PROVISIONS</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><BillPiece><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2012, c. 1, par. 165(c)</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Pardons in effect — references in other legislation</MarginalNote><Label>165</Label><Text>A reference to a record suspension in the following provisions, as enacted by this Part, is deemed also to be a reference to a pardon that is granted or issued under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Records Act</XRefExternal>:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>subsection 10(8) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">DNA Identification Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></Section></BillPiece></Schedule><Schedule id="NifProvs"><ScheduleFormHeading type="amending"><TitleText>AMENDMENTS NOT IN FORCE</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><BillPiece><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 39, s. 232</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>232</Label><Text>Section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">DNA Identification Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>human remains</DefinedTermEn> includes any detached part of the body of a person who may still be alive. (<DefinedTermFr>restes humains</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>investigating authority</DefinedTermEn> means, as the case may be,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a Canadian law enforcement agency;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a coroner or medical examiner, or a person or organization with similar duties or functions, who is acting in the course of their duties under an Act of Parliament or of a provincial legislature; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a laboratory. (<DefinedTermFr>autorité chargée de l’enquête</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 39, s. 233</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>233</Label><Text>Section 3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to establish a national DNA data bank to help</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>law enforcement agencies identify persons alleged to have committed designated offences, including those committed before the coming into force of this Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>law enforcement agencies — as well as coroners, medical examiners or persons and organizations with similar duties or functions — find missing persons and identify human remains.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 39, s. 234</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 5</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>234</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 4(b) of the Act is replaced by the following :</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>society is well served by locating missing persons and identifying human remains, which can be facilitated by the use of DNA profiles;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the DNA profiles, as well as samples of bodily substances from which the profiles are derived, may be used only in accordance with this Act, and not for any unauthorized purpose; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 4(c)(i) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following :</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>l’utilisation et la communication des renseignements contenus dans la banque de données — notamment des profils —, de même que leur accessibilité,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 39, s. 235</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>235</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following before section 5:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Establishment and Contents</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 39, s. 236</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 10, par. 34(1)(h)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>236</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 5(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness shall establish a national DNA data bank, to be maintained by the Commissioner, consisting of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for criminal identification purposes, a crime scene index, a convicted offenders index and a victims index;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for the purposes of finding missing persons and identifying human remains, a missing persons index, a relatives of missing persons index and a human remains index; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>for the purposes set out in paragraphs (a) and (b), a voluntary donors index.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 5(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Victims index</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>The victims index shall contain DNA profiles derived from bodily substances of a victim of a designated offence that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>are voluntarily submitted by the victim for the purpose of having their DNA profile added to the index; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the victim is unidentified, deceased or unable to consent to submitting their bodily substances or their whereabouts are unknown, are obtained, as the case may be, from</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>their personal effects,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>any place associated with the commission of the designated offence, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>if the victim is deceased, their remains.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Missing persons index</MarginalNote><Label>(4.2)</Label><Text>The missing persons index shall contain DNA profiles derived from bodily substances of a missing person, including bodily substances obtained from their personal effects.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Relatives of missing persons index</MarginalNote><Label>(4.3)</Label><Text>The relatives of missing persons index shall contain DNA profiles derived from bodily substances of a person that are voluntarily submitted by them for the purpose of having their DNA profile added to the index, where their profile may assist in confirming the identity of a person whose DNA profile is contained in the missing persons index or human remains index.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Human remains index</MarginalNote><Label>(4.4)</Label><Text>The human remains index shall contain DNA profiles derived from human remains.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Voluntary donors index</MarginalNote><Label>(4.5)</Label><Text>The voluntary donors index shall contain DNA profiles derived from the bodily substances of a person, other than a victim of a designated offence, that are voluntarily submitted by them for the purpose of having their DNA profile added to the index, where their profile may be relevant to an investigation of a designated offence or of a missing person or human remains.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other information</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>In addition to the DNA profiles referred to in subsections (3) to (4.5), the DNA data bank shall contain, in relation to each of the profiles, information from which can be established</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of a profile referred to in subsection (3) or any of subsections (4.1) to (4.4), the case number of the investigation associated with the bodily substance from which the profile was derived;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of a profile referred to in any of subsections (4) to (4.5), the identity of the person from whose bodily substance the profile was derived, if that identity is known; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in the case of a profile referred to in subsection (4.3), the stated biological or other relationship of the person from whose bodily substance the profile was derived with the person whose identity is to be confirmed.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 39, s. 237</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 25, s. 16</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>237</Label><Text>Subsection 5.1(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Forensic DNA analysis</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commissioner shall conduct a forensic DNA analysis of the bodily substances transmitted if satisfied that the offence referred to in the order or authorization is a designated offence and add the resulting DNA profile in the convicted offenders index.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 39, s. 238</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 25, ss. 17(1) and (3); 2007, c. 22, ss. 31(1), (2)(E) and (3) to (5)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>238</Label><Text>Section 6 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Precondition — victims</MarginalNote><Label>5.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A DNA profile and related information shall be added to the victims index only if the Commissioner has reasonable grounds to suspect that the comparison of the profile conducted under subsection 5.5(1) will assist in the investigation of a designated offence with respect to which the profile was obtained.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Preconditions — missing persons and relatives</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A DNA profile and related information shall be added to the missing persons index or the relatives of missing persons index only if the Commissioner</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>has reasonable grounds to suspect that the comparison of the profile conducted under section 5.5 will assist in the investigation of a missing person or human remains; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is satisfied that other investigative procedures have been tried and have failed or are unlikely to succeed, or that the urgency of the situation requires the comparison of the profile to others.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Written consent</MarginalNote><Label>5.4</Label><Text>A DNA profile and related information shall be added to the relatives of missing persons index or the voluntary donors index, or to the victims index in the circumstances described in paragraph 5(4.1)(a), only if the Commissioner has received the written consent to that addition, provided in accordance with any regulations, of the person who voluntarily provided the bodily substances from which the profile was derived.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Comparison of Profiles and Communication and Use of Information</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Comparison of DNA profiles</MarginalNote><Label>5.5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner shall compare each DNA profile that is added to the crime scene index, the convicted offenders index, the victims index, the missing person index, the voluntary donors index or the human remains index with the DNA profiles that are already contained in those indices.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Relatives of missing persons index</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commissioner shall compare each DNA profile that is added to the relatives of missing persons index with the DNA profiles that are already contained in the missing persons index and the human remains index.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Communication — match</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a comparison conducted under subsection 5.5(1) produces a match between DNA profiles, and none of the profiles that match is contained in the missing persons index or the human remains index, the Commissioner may communicate any information in relation to the profiles, to any laboratory or Canadian law enforcement agency that the Commissioner considers appropriate, for the purpose of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if at least one of the profiles is contained in the victims index, the investigation of a designated offence with respect to which that profile was obtained; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in any other case, the investigation of any designated offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Missing persons and human remains indices</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a comparison conducted under subsection 5.5(1) produces a match between DNA profiles, and at least one of the profiles that match is contained in the missing persons index or the human remains index, the Commissioner may communicate any information in relation to the profiles, to any investigating authority that the Commissioner considers appropriate, for the purpose of the investigation of a missing person or human remains.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Communication — similar profile</MarginalNote><Label>6.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a comparison conducted under subsection 5.5(1) indicates that, in the Commissioner’s opinion, two or more DNA profiles are similar, the Commissioner may communicate the similar DNA profiles, to any investigating authority that the Commissioner considers appropriate, for the purpose of determining whether the possibility of a match between the profiles can be excluded.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deemed match</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the investigating authority advises the Commissioner that the profiles are similar and that the possibility of a match between the DNA profiles has not been excluded, the Commissioner may communicate any information in relation to the profiles in accordance with subsection 6(1) or (2), as the case may be, as if there were a match between them.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Relatives of missing persons index</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a comparison conducted under subsection 5.5(2) indicates that a DNA profile that is already contained in the missing persons index or human remains index could be the profile of a biological relative of someone whose DNA profile is added to the relatives of missing persons index, the Commissioner may communicate any information in relation to both DNA profiles, to any investigating authority that the Commissioner considers appropriate, for the purpose of the investigation of a missing person or human remains.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Communication — no match</MarginalNote><Label>6.2</Label><Text>If a comparison conducted under section 5.5 produces neither a match between DNA profiles nor a result referred to in subsection 6.1(1) or (3), the Commissioner may communicate that fact to any investigating authority that the Commissioner considers appropriate.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Subsequent communication — paragraph 6(1)(a)</MarginalNote><Label>6.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Information that is communicated under paragraph 6(1)(a) may be communicated subsequently to a person to whom it is necessary to communicate the information for the purpose of the investigation or prosecution of a designated offence with respect to which the DNA profile referred to in that paragraph was obtained.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsequent communication — different purpose</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Information that is communicated under paragraph 6(1)(a) to a law enforcement agency may be communicated subsequently by a member of the agency to a person to whom it is necessary to communicate the information for the purpose of the investigation or prosecution of any designated offence, if the member has reasonable grounds to suspect that the information will assist in the investigation or prosecution.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Further communication — different purpose</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Information that is communicated to a person under subsection (2) may be communicated subsequently to another person to whom it is necessary to communicate the information for the purpose of the investigation or prosecution referred to in that subsection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsequent communication — paragraph 6(1)(b)</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Information that is communicated under paragraph 6(1)(b) may be communicated subsequently to a person to whom it is necessary to communicate the information for the purpose of the investigation or prosecution of any designated offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsequent communication — missing person or human remains</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Information that is communicated under subsection 6(2) or 6.1(3) may be communicated subsequently to a person to whom it is necessary to communicate the information for the purpose of the investigation of a missing person or human remains.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsequent communication — different purpose</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Information that is communicated under subsection 6(2) or 6.1(3) to a law enforcement agency may be communicated subsequently by a member of the agency to a person to whom it is necessary to communicate the information for the purpose of the investigation or prosecution of a designated offence, if the member has reasonable grounds to suspect that the information will assist in the investigation or prosecution.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Further communication — different purpose</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Information that is communicated to a person under subsection (6) may be communicated subsequently to another person to whom it is necessary to communicate the information for the purpose of the investigation or prosecution referred to in that subsection.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Communication — foreign law enforcement agencies</MarginalNote><Label>6.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On receipt of a DNA profile from the government of a foreign state, an international organization established by the governments of states or an institution of such a government or international organization, the Commissioner may compare the profile with those already contained in the crime scene index, the convicted offenders index, the missing persons index and the human remains index to determine whether there is a match between profiles and may then communicate any of the following to the government, organization or institution, as the case may be:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if there is no match, that fact;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if there is a match, any information in relation to a matching DNA profile that is already contained in any of those indices;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if there is, in the Commissioner’s opinion, a similar DNA profile already contained in an index, the similar DNA profile;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>if, after receiving the similar DNA profile referred to in paragraph (c), the government, organization or institution advises the Commissioner that the possibility of a match between the similar profile with the DNA profile it provided has not been excluded, any information in relation to the similar DNA profile.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Crime scene index</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may, on the request of a law enforcement agency in the course of the investigation of a designated offence, communicate a DNA profile contained in the crime scene index to the government of a foreign state, an international organization established by the governments of states or an institution of any such government or international organization.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Missing persons or human remains index</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may, on the request of an investigating authority in the course of the investigation of a missing person or human remains, communicate a DNA profile contained in the missing persons index or the human remains index to the government of a foreign state, an international organization established by the governments of states or an institution of any such government or international organization.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Agreement or arrangement</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) to (3) apply only if the Government of Canada or one of its institutions has entered into an agreement or arrangement, in accordance with any regulations, with that government, international organization or institution, authorizing the communication solely for the purposes of, as the case may be, the investigation or prosecution of a criminal offence or the investigation of a missing person or human remains.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Authorized users</MarginalNote><Label>6.5</Label><Text>Information as to whether a person’s DNA profile is contained in the convicted offenders index may be communicated to an authorized user of the automated criminal conviction records retrieval system maintained by the Royal Canadian Mounted Police.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Unauthorized communication</MarginalNote><Label>6.6</Label><Text>Subject to sections 6 to 6.5, no person shall communicate any information that is contained in the DNA data bank or allow the information to be communicated.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 39, s. 239</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>239</Label><Text>Section 7 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following :</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Accès aux renseignements contenus dans la banque</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>Le personnel de tout laboratoire et toute personne — ou catégorie de personnes — que le commissaire estime compétents peuvent avoir accès aux renseignements contenus dans la banque de données respectivement à des fins de formation et pour assurer le bon fonctionnement et l’entretien de la banque.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 39, s. 240</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 25, s. 17.1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>240</Label><Text>Sections 8 and 8.1 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Unauthorized use of information</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), no person to whom information is communicated under any of sections 6, 6.1 and 6.3 or who has access to information under paragraph 7(a) or (b) shall use that information other than for the purposes set out in the applicable provision of those sections.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Use for different purpose</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>After a law enforcement agency has received information in relation to a DNA profile that was communicated to them under paragraph 6(1)(a) or subsection 6(2) or 6.1(3), a member of the agency may use that information for the purpose of the investigation or prosecution of a designated offence if they have reasonable grounds to suspect that the information will assist in the investigation or prosecution.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Use of results of DNA analysis — order or authorization</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No person shall use the results of forensic DNA analysis of bodily substances that are taken in execution of an order or authorization, except in accordance with this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Removal of Access to Information</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Removal of access to information — crime scene index</MarginalNote><Label>8.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Access to information in the crime scene index shall be removed from that index without delay if the information relates to a DNA profile derived from a bodily substance of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a victim of a designated offence that was the object of the relevant investigation; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a person who has been eliminated as a suspect in the relevant investigation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other indices</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Access to information in relation to a DNA profile in the victims index, the missing persons index, the relatives of missing persons index, the human remains index or the voluntary donors index shall be removed from that index without delay if the Commissioner is advised that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the person from whose bodily substances the profile was derived wishes to have access to the information removed; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the comparison under this Act of the profile with other profiles will not assist in the investigation with respect to which the profile was obtained.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Periodic removal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>After each period prescribed by regulation, access to information in relation to a DNA profile in the victims index, the missing persons index, the relatives of missing persons index or the voluntary donors index shall be removed from that index without delay unless the Commissioner is advised before the end of the period, by any investigating authority that the Commissioner considers appropriate, that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the investigating authority has not been advised by the person from whose bodily substances the profile was derived that they wish to have access to the information removed; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the comparison under this Act of the profile with other profiles may assist in the investigation with respect to which the profile was obtained.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsequent DNA profile</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Removal of access to information in relation to a DNA profile of a person from an index under this section does not prevent a DNA profile derived from the bodily substances of the same person, and any information in relation to that profile, from subsequently being added to any index in accordance with this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations — requirements</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The removal of access to information under any of subsections (1) to (3) shall be done in accordance with the requirements set out in any regulations that apply with respect to that subsection.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Transfer to another index</MarginalNote><Label>8.2</Label><Text>The Commissioner may transfer a DNA profile and information in relation to it from one index — other than the convicted offenders index or the relatives of missing persons index — to another, as long as the addition of the profile to the other index is in accordance with the applicable provisions of this Act.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 39, s. 241</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2007, c. 22, s. 32</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>241</Label><Text>Subsection 9(2) of the Act is amended by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (a), by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (b) and by repealing paragraph (c).</Text></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 39, s. 242</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>242</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following before section 10:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Storage and Destruction of Bodily Substances</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 39, s. 243</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2007, c. 22, s. 33</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>243</Label><Text>Subsection 10(7) of the Act is amended by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (a), by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (b) and by repealing paragraph (c).</Text></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 39, s. 244</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>244</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following before section 11:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Offence</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 39, s. 245</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 25, s. 22</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>245</Label><Text>The portion of section 11 of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Contravention of sections</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes section 6.6 or 8 or subsection 10(5)</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 39, s. 246</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>246</Label><Text>Section 12 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Act, including regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>respecting the establishment and operation of the national DNA data bank;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>respecting the collection and transmission of any information or other thing that is to be received by the Commissioner;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>respecting agreements or arrangements referred to in subsection 6.4(4);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>respecting access to information that is contained in the national DNA data bank, including removal of access to information and destruction of information;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>respecting the establishment of advisory committees to advise on any matter related to the national DNA data bank; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>prescribing anything that by this Act is to be prescribed by regulation.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section></BillPiece></Schedule></Statute>