<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Statute PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Statute v2.0.0//EN" "Dtd/Version_2.0.0/Statute/Statute.dtd"><Statute bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes"><Identification><BillNumber>C-10</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>40</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>57-58</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2009</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to restrain the Government of Canada’s expenditures in relation to employment</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Expenditure Restraint Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Expenditure Restraint</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>06</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2009</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>12</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber official="no">E-15.5</ConsolidatedNumber><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>2, s. 393</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2009</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><ReaderNote><Note status="editorial" xml:space="default">[Enacted by section 393 of chapter 2 of the Statutes of Canada, 2009, in force on assent March 12, 2009.]</Note></ReaderNote></Identification><Introduction><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text /></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Expenditure Restraint Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>additional remuneration</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>rémunération additionnelle</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>additional remuneration</DefinedTermEn> means any allowance, bonus, differential or premium or any payment to employees that is similar to any of those payments.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>arbitral award</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>décision arbitrale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>arbitral award</DefinedTermEn> means an arbitral award governing employees to whom this Act applies.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>bargaining agent</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>agent négociateur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>bargaining agent</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>as in subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>, in relation to employees to whom Part I of that Act applies;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>as in section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliamentary Employment and Staff Relations Act</XRefExternal>, in relation to employees to whom that Act applies; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>as in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Labour Relations Act</XRefExternal>, in relation to employees to whom that Act applies.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>collective agreement</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>convention collective</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>collective agreement</DefinedTermEn> means a collective agreement governing employees to whom this Act applies.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Her Majesty</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Sa Majesté</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Her Majesty</DefinedTermEn> means Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>National Joint Council</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Conseil national mixte</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>National Joint Council</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Labour Relations Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>rate of pay</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>taux de salaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>rate of pay</DefinedTermEn> means a base rate of pay, whether expressed as a single rate of pay or a range of rates of pay — or, if no such rate or range exists, any fixed or ascertainable amount of base pay — but does not include any additional remuneration.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>restraint period</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>période de contrôle</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>restraint period</DefinedTermEn> means the period that begins on April 1, 2006 and ends on March 31, 2011.</Text></Definition></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Deemed bonus</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>For the purpose of this Act, any lump sum that an employer is required by an arbitral award to pay to employees is deemed to be a bonus.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>National Joint Council recommendations</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>Any reference in this Act to additional remuneration does not include any additional remuneration that is provided for by a directive, policy, regulation, agreement or other instrument issued or made</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on the recommendation of the National Joint Council and with the employer’s approval; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>unilaterally by an employer in respect of a subject matter that, in the opinion of the Treasury Board, is the same as or is related to the subject matter of any instrument made in accordance with paragraph (a).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>When certain collective agreements are deemed to have been entered into</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purpose of this Act, a collective agreement is deemed to have been entered into before December 8, 2008 if it was actually entered into on or after that date but its parties had, before that date, agreed in writing to enter into it with effect on the expiry of a previous collective agreement and they entered into it without alteration.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When provisions of certain terms and conditions of employment are deemed to have been established</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If subsection (1) applies in respect of a collective agreement and terms and conditions of employment were established on or after December 8, 2008, the provisions of those terms and conditions of employment that are identical in all material respects to those of the collective agreement and that are applicable to non-represented and excluded employees that normally have terms and conditions of employment that are similar to those of the employees governed by the collective agreement are, for the purposes of this Act, deemed to have been made before December 8, 2008.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Effects of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Right to bargain collectively</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, the right to bargain collectively under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliamentary Employment and Staff Relations Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Labour Relations Act</XRefExternal> is continued.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right to strike</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act affects the right to strike under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Labour Relations Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Amendments permitted</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act precludes the bargaining agent for employees governed by a collective agreement or arbitral award and the employer of those employees from amending, by agreement in writing, any provision of the collective agreement or arbitral award, other than a provision relating to its term, so long as the amendment is not contrary to any provision of this Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Workplace improvements</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act precludes the co-development of workplace improvements by bargaining agents and employers under the auspices of the National Joint Council or any other body that they may agree on.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Incremental and merit increases</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act is to be construed as precluding the entitlement of any employee to incremental increases — including any based on the attainment of further qualifications or the acquisition of further skills — or to merit or performance increases, in-range increases, performance bonuses or similar forms of compensation.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Conflicts with other Acts</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>In the event of a conflict between a provision of this Act and a provision of any other Act of Parliament, including a provision in Part X of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, the provision of this Act prevails to the extent of the conflict, unless the other Act expressly declares that it or any of its provisions apply despite this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Members of Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>This Act applies to members of the Senate and the House of Commons.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Employees</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>This Act applies to employees who are employed in or by</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the departments and other portions of the federal public administration named in Schedules I and IV, respectively, to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> and the separate agencies named in Schedule V to that Act, other than the Financial Consumer Agency of Canada and the Staff of the Non-Public Funds, Canadian Forces;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Crown corporations and public bodies named in Schedule 1; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Senate, the House of Commons, the Library of Parliament, the office of the Senate Ethics Officer, the office of the Conflict of Interest and Ethics Commissioner and the Parliamentary Protective Service.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Members of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, members of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police are employees.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deemed employees</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>This Act applies to the following persons, who are deemed to be employees for the purposes of this Act:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the staff of members of the Senate and the House of Commons;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>directors of the Crown corporations and public bodies named in Schedule 1;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>officers and non-commissioned members of the Canadian Forces; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the Chief Electoral Officer.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Persons appointed by Governor in Council</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>This Act applies to persons who are appointed by the Governor in Council, and those persons are deemed to be employees for the purposes of this Act. Despite this subsection, this Act does not apply to lieutenant governors, judges who are paid a salary under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Judges Act</XRefExternal>, military judges appointed under section 165.21 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> and prothonotaries appointed under section 12 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 2, s. 393 "13"; 2015, c. 36, s. 152.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Persons designated by Governor in Council</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, designate any person or class of persons as persons to whom this Act applies, and those persons are deemed to be employees for the purposes of this Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Locally engaged persons and independent contractors</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Text>This Act does not apply to a person who is locally engaged outside Canada or, for greater certainty, to a person who is engaged as an independent contractor.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Restraint Measures</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Increases to Rates of Pay</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Increases to rates of pay</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Text>Despite any collective agreement, arbitral award or terms and conditions of employment to the contrary, but subject to the other provisions of this Act, the rates of pay for employees are to be increased, or are deemed to have been increased, as the case may be, by the following percentages for any 12-month period that begins during any of the following fiscal years:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the 2006–2007 fiscal year, 2.5%;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the 2007–2008 fiscal year, 2.3%;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the 2008–2009 fiscal year, 1.5%;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the 2009–2010 fiscal year, 1.5%; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the 2010–2011 fiscal year, 1.5%.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Employees Represented by a Bargaining Agent</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Increases to rates of pay — collective agreements or arbitral awards after coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The provisions of any collective agreement that is entered into, or arbitral award that is made, after the day on which this Act comes into force may not provide for increases to rates of pay that are greater than those set out in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal>, but they may provide for increases that are lower.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>12-month periods</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, any collective agreement that is entered into, or any arbitral award that is made, after the day on which this Act comes into force and that provides for increases to rates of pay for any period that begins during the restraint period must do so on the basis of a 12-month period.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Increases to rates of pay — collective agreements and arbitral awards — December 8, 2008 until coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Text>The provisions of any collective agreement that is entered into, or any arbitral award that is made, during the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on the day on which this Act comes into force that provide, for any particular period, for increases to rates of pay that are greater than those referred to in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> for that particular period are of no effect or are deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be, and are deemed to be provisions that provide for the increases referred to in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Increases to rates of pay — collective agreements and arbitral awards — before December 8, 2008</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Text>With respect to a collective agreement that is entered into, or an arbitral award that is made, before December 8, 2008,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> does not apply in respect of any period that began during the 2006–2007 or 2007–2008 fiscal year; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for any 12-month period that begins during any of the 2008–2009, 2009–2010 and 2010–2011 fiscal years, section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> applies only in respect of periods that begin on or after December 8, 2008 and any provisions of those agreements or awards that provide, for any particular period, for increases to rates of pay that are greater than those referred to in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> for that particular period are of no effect or are deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be, and are deemed to be provisions that provide for the increases referred to in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Other than 12-month periods — section <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal></MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Text>If a collective agreement or arbitral award to which section <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal> applies provides for an increase to rates of pay for a period of other than 12 months that begins during any particular fiscal year in the restraint period, that increase is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be, and is deemed to be an increase for that period of other than 12 months, determined on an annualized basis to the nearest 1/100%, that provides for the increase referred to in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> for a period that begins during that particular fiscal year.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Other than 12-month periods — section <XRefInternal>19</XRefInternal></MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Text>If a collective agreement or arbitral award to which section <XRefInternal>19</XRefInternal> applies provides for an increase to rates of pay for a period of other than 12 months that begins during any particular fiscal year that begins during the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on March 31, 2011, that increase is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be, and is deemed to be an increase for that period of other than 12 months, determined on an annualized basis to the nearest 1/100%, that provides for the increase referred to in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> for a period that begins during that particular fiscal year.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Lower percentages not affected</MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Text>If a collective agreement or arbitral award to which section <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal> or <XRefInternal>19</XRefInternal> applies provides for an increase to the rates of pay for any particular period that is lower than the increase referred to in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> for that period, section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> does not apply in respect of that increase.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Restructuring prohibited</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Text>Subject to sections <XRefInternal>31</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal>,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>no provision of a collective agreement that is entered into, or of an arbitral award that is made, after the day on which this Act comes into force may provide for the restructuring of rates of pay during any period that begins during the restraint period;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any provision of a collective agreement that is entered into, or of an arbitral award that is made, during the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on the day on which this Act comes into force that provides for the restructuring of rates of pay during any period that begins during the restraint period is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any provision of a collective agreement that is entered into, or of an arbitral award that is made, before December 8, 2008 that provides for the restructuring of rates of pay during any period that begins during the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on March 31, 2011 is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No increases to additional remuneration — after coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Text>No collective agreement that is entered into, or arbitral award that is made, after the day on which this Act comes into force may provide, for any period that begins during the restraint period, for any increase to the amount or rate of any additional remuneration that applied to the employees governed by the collective agreement or the arbitral award immediately before the collective agreement, or the arbitral award, as the case may be, becomes effective.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No increases to additional remuneration — December 8, 2008 until coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>25</Label><Text>If a collective agreement that is entered into, or arbitral award that is made, at any time during the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on the day on which this Act comes into force contains provisions that provide, for any period that begins during the restraint period, for an increase to the amount or rate of any additional remuneration that applied to the employees governed by the collective agreement or the arbitral award immediately before the collective agreement, or the arbitral award, as the case may be, became effective, those provisions are of no effect or are deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No increases to additional remuneration — before December 8, 2008</MarginalNote><Label>26</Label><Text>If a collective agreement that is entered into, or an arbitral award that is made, before December 8, 2008 contains provisions that, for any period that begins in the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on March 31, 2011, provide for an increase to the amount or rate of any additional remuneration that applied to the employees governed by the collective agreement or the arbitral award immediately before the first period that began on or after December 8, 2008, those provisions are of no effect or are deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No new additional remuneration — after coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>27</Label><Text>No collective agreement that is entered into, or arbitral award that is made, after the day on which this Act comes into force may provide, for any period that begins during the restraint period, for any additional remuneration that is new in relation to the additional remuneration that applied to the employees governed by the collective agreement or the arbitral award immediately before the collective agreement or the arbitral award, as the case may be, becomes effective.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No new additional remuneration — December 8, 2008 to coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>28</Label><Text>If a collective agreement that is entered into, or an arbitral award that is made, at any time during the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on the day on which this Act comes into force contains a provision that provides, for any period that begins during the restraint period, for any additional remuneration to the employees governed by the collective agreement or the arbitral award that is new in relation to the additional remuneration that applied to the employees governed by the collective agreement or the arbitral award, as the case may be, immediately before it became effective, that provision is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No new additional remuneration — before December 8, 2008</MarginalNote><Label>29</Label><Text>If a collective agreement that is entered into, or an arbitral award that is made, before December 8, 2008 contains a provision that provides, for any period that begins in the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on March 31, 2011, for any additional remuneration to the employees governed by the collective agreement or the arbitral award that is new in relation to the additional remuneration that applied to the employees governed by the collective agreement or arbitral award, as the case may be, immediately before the first period that began on or after December 8, 2008, that provision is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Canada Border Services Agency</MarginalNote><Label>30</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>24</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>26</XRefInternal> do not apply in respect of pay notes applicable only to employees in the Canada Border Services Agency who were transferred to the Agency on its creation, but the rates of those pay notes may not be increased during any period that begins in any of the fiscal years referred to in section 16 by a percentage that is higher than the percentage set out in that section for that fiscal year.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Border Services Group</MarginalNote><Label>31</Label><Text>The following rules apply in respect of collective agreements that govern employees in the Border Services Group whose employer is Her Majesty as represented by the Treasury Board:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>paragraph <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>(a) does not prevent any collective agreement that is entered into after the day on which this Act comes into force from restructuring, as a result of a classification conversion, the rates of pay during the 2007–2008 or 2009–2010 fiscal year, and the increases set out in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> apply in respect of the restructured rates of pay;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if a collective agreement is entered into during the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on the day on which this Act comes into force and, as a result of a classification conversion, it contains provisions for the restructuring of rates of pay during the 2007–2008 or 2009–2010 fiscal year, paragraph <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>(b) does not apply in respect of those provisions, and the increases set out in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> apply in respect of the restructured rates of pay; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if a collective agreement is entered into before December 8, 2008 and, as a result of a classification conversion, it contains provisions for the restructuring of rates of pay during the 2009–2010 fiscal year, paragraph <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>(c) does not apply in respect of those provisions, and the increase set out in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> applies in respect of the restructured rates of pay.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Groups subject to national rates of pay</MarginalNote><Label>32</Label><Text>The following rules apply in respect of collective agreements that govern employees in the Operational Services Group whose employer is Her Majesty as represented by the Treasury Board and employees in the General Labour and Trades Group and the General Services Group whose employer is Her Majesty as represented by the Parks Canada Agency or Her Majesty as represented by the Canadian Food Inspection Agency:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>paragraph <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>(a) does not prevent any collective agreement that is entered into after the day on which this Act comes into force from restructuring the rates of pay during the 2009–2010 fiscal year in order to create national rates of pay, and the increase set out in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> applies in respect of the restructured rates of pay;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if a collective agreement is entered into during the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on the day on which this Act comes into force and, in order to create national rates of pay, it contains provisions for the restructuring of rates of pay during the 2009–2010 fiscal year, paragraph <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>(b) does not apply in respect of those provisions, and the increase set out in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> applies in respect of the restructured rates of pay; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if a collective agreement is entered into before December 8, 2008 and, in order to create national rates of pay, it contains provisions for the restructuring of rates of pay during the 2009–2010 fiscal year, paragraph <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>(c) does not apply in respect of those provisions, and the increase set out in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> applies in respect of the restructured rates of pay.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Ships’ Officers Group</MarginalNote><Label>33</Label><Text>The following rules apply in respect of any arbitral award that is made before December 8, 2008 and that governs employees in the Ships’ Officers Group whose employer is Her Majesty as represented by the Treasury Board:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>paragraph <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>(c) does not apply in respect of the provisions of any arbitral award that provide for the restructuring of rates of pay during the 2010–2011 fiscal year, and the increase set out in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> applies in respect of the restructured rates of pay; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>section <XRefInternal>29</XRefInternal> does not apply in respect of the provisions of any arbitral award that provide for the payment, during the 2010–2011 fiscal year, of a sum in lieu of vacation leave factors.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Law Group</MarginalNote><Label>34</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following rules apply in respect of any collective agreement or arbitral award that governs employees in the Law Group whose employer is Her Majesty as represented by the Treasury Board, and in respect of any period that begins during the restraint period:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of a collective agreement entered into — or an arbitral award made — after the day on which this Act comes into force,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>it may not have retroactive effect in respect of a day that is earlier than May 10, 2006,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>any increase to rates of pay that it provides for in respect of any period that begins during the 2006–2007 fiscal year must be based on the rates of pay set out in Schedule 2,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>it must provide, for all employees in the Law Group, for the same performance pay plans that were in effect on May 9, 2006 for any employees in the Law Group and, in relation to any particular position level, those plans must be at the same amounts or rates that were in effect for that position level on that date, but those plans may not have retroactive effect,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>it may provide for any additional remuneration — other than a performance bonus — that applied to any position level in the Law Group on May 9, 2006, but the amount or rate of that additional remuneration for a particular position level may not be greater than the highest amount or rate that applied to employees of that position level on that date, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>it may not provide for additional remuneration if that additional remuneration applied to no employee in the Law Group on May 9, 2006; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of a collective agreement entered into — or an arbitral award made — on or before the day on which this Act comes into force,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>if any of its provisions has retroactive effect in respect of a day that is earlier than May 10, 2006, that retroactive effect is deemed never to have had effect, the provision is deemed to have had retroactive effect as of May 10, 2006 and the first day of every other period that is related to that provision is deemed to be moved forward by the number of days that is equal to the number of days between the first day the provision was expressed to have retroactive effect and May 10, 2006,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>if the increase provided to rates of pay for any period that begins during the 2006–2007 fiscal year is based on rates of pay that are greater than those set out in Schedule 2, those greater rates of pay are of no effect or are deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be, and the increase is deemed to be based on the rates of pay set out in Schedule 2,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>if subparagraph (ii) applies, its provision that provides for the rates of pay for any other period that begins on or before March 31, 2011 is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be, and the rates of pay in that provision are deemed to be the rates of pay that applied immediately before the beginning of that period as a result of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>if it provides for performance pay plans and those plans are not the same as those that were in effect on May 9, 2006 for any employees in the Law Group or the amounts or rates provided for in those plans in relation to any particular position level are not the same as those of the performance pay plans that were in effect on that date — or the plans were expressed to be retroactive — the provisions that provide for those plans are of no effect or are deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be, and are deemed to be provisions that provide, for all employees in the Law Group, as of the day that the agreement was entered into or the award was made, for the same performance pay plans that were in effect on May 9, 2006 for any employees in the Law Group at the same amounts or rates, in relation to any particular position level, that were in effect on that date,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>if it does not provide for performance pay plans, it is deemed to provide, for all employees in the Law Group, as of the day that the agreement was entered into or the award was made, for the same performance pay plans that were in effect on May 9, 2006 for any employees in the Law Group at the same amounts or rates, in relation to any particular position level, that were in effect on that date,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>if it provides for any additional remuneration — other than a performance bonus — that applied to any position level in the Law Group on May 9, 2006, and the amount or rate of that additional remuneration for a particular position level is greater than the highest amount or rate that applied to any employees of that position level on that date, the provision that provides for that payment is deemed to be of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be, and is deemed to provide for the highest amount or rate, as the case may be, that applied in respect of any of those employees on that date, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>if it provides for any additional remuneration, and that additional remuneration applied to no employee in the Law Group on May 9, 2006, the provision that provides for that payment is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other provisions apply</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the provisions of this Act that are not inconsistent with subsection (1) apply to collective agreements and arbitral awards that govern employees in the Law Group.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Non-represented and Excluded Employees</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>35</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in sections <XRefInternal>36</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>54</XRefInternal>.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>employee</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>employé</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>employee</DefinedTermEn> means an employee who is not represented by a bargaining agent or who is excluded from a bargaining unit.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>terms and conditions of employment</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>condition d’emploi</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>terms and conditions of employment</DefinedTermEn> means terms and conditions of employment that apply to employees.</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When terms and conditions of employment are considered to be established</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of sections <XRefInternal>36</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>54</XRefInternal>, terms and conditions of employment are considered to be established if they are established by an employer acting alone or agreed to by an employer and employees.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Increases to rates of pay — terms and conditions established after coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>36</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Terms and conditions of employment established after the day on which this Act comes into force may not provide for increases to rates of pay that are greater than those set out in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal>, but they may provide for increases that are lower.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>12-month periods</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, terms and conditions of employment established after the day on which this Act comes into force that provide for increases to rates of pay for any period that begins during the restraint period must do so on the basis of a 12-month period.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Increases to rates of pay — terms and conditions of employment — December 8, 2008 until coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>37</Label><Text>The provisions of any terms and conditions of employment established during the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on the day on which this Act comes into force that provide, for any particular period, for an increase to rates of pay that are greater than those referred to in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> for that particular period are of no effect or are deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be, and are deemed to be provisions that provide for the increases referred to in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Increases to rates of pay — terms and conditions of employment — before December 8, 2008</MarginalNote><Label>38</Label><Text>With respect to any terms and conditions of employment established before December 8, 2008 that provide for increases to rates of pay</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> does not apply in respect of any period that began during the 2006–2007 or 2007–2008 fiscal year; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for any 12-month period that begins during any of the 2008–2009, 2009–2010 and 2010–2011 fiscal years, section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> applies only in respect of periods that begin on or after December 8, 2008 and any provisions of those terms and conditions of employment that provide, for any particular period, for increases to rates of pay that are greater than those referred to in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> for that particular period are of no effect or are deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be, and are deemed to be provisions that provide for the increases referred to in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Other than 12-month periods — section <XRefInternal>37</XRefInternal></MarginalNote><Label>39</Label><Text>If any terms and conditions of employment to which section <XRefInternal>37</XRefInternal> applies provide for an increase to rates of pay for a period of other than 12 months that begins during any particular fiscal year in the restraint period, that increase is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be, and the increase is deemed to be an increase for that period of other than 12 months, determined on an annualized basis to the nearest 1/100%, that provides for the increase referred to in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> for a period that begins during that particular fiscal year.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Other than 12-month periods — section <XRefInternal>38</XRefInternal></MarginalNote><Label>40</Label><Text>If any terms and conditions of employment to which section <XRefInternal>38</XRefInternal> applies provide for an increase to rates of pay for a period of other than 12 months that begins during any particular fiscal year that begins during the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on March 31, 2011, that increase is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be, and is deemed to be an increase for that period of other than 12 months, determined on an annualized basis to the nearest 1/100%, that provides for the increases referred to in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> in respect of a period that begins during that particular fiscal year.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Lower percentages not affected</MarginalNote><Label>41</Label><Text>If any terms and conditions of employment to which section <XRefInternal>37</XRefInternal> or <XRefInternal>38</XRefInternal> apply provide for an increase to the rates of pay for any particular period that is lower than the increase referred to in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> for that period, section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> does not apply in respect of that increase.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> does not create authority to increase</MarginalNote><Label>42</Label><Text>If any terms and conditions of employment established before, on or after the day on which this Act comes into force do not provide for an increase to the rates of pay for any particular period that begins during the restraint period, section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> is not to be construed as authorizing any increase to those rates of pay.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Restructuring prohibited</MarginalNote><Label>43</Label><Text>Subject to sections <XRefInternal>51</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>54</XRefInternal>,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>no provision of terms and conditions of employment established after the day on which this Act comes into force may provide for the restructuring of rates of pay during any period that begins during the restraint period;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any provision of terms and conditions of employment established during the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on the day on which this Act comes into force that provides for the restructuring of rates of pay during any period that begins during the restraint period is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any provision of terms and conditions of employment established before December 8, 2008 that provides for the restructuring of rates of pay during any period that begins during the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on March 31, 2011 is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No increases to additional remuneration — after coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>44</Label><Text>No terms and conditions of employment established after the day on which this Act comes into force may provide, for any period that begins during the restraint period, for any increase to the amount or rate of any additional remuneration that applied to the employees governed by those terms and conditions of employment immediately before those terms and conditions of employment become effective.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No increases to additional remuneration — December 8, 2008 until coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>45</Label><Text>If any terms and conditions of employment established at any time during the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on the day on which this Act comes into force contain provisions that provide, for any period that begins during the restraint period, for an increase to the amount or rate of any additional remuneration that applied to the employees governed by those terms and conditions of employment immediately before those provisions became effective, those provisions are of no effect or are deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No increases to additional remuneration — before December 8, 2008</MarginalNote><Label>46</Label><Text>If any terms and conditions of employment established before December 8, 2008 contain provisions that, for any period that begins in the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on March 31, 2011, provide for an increase to the amount or rate of any additional remuneration that applied to the employees governed by those terms and conditions of employment immediately before the first period that began on or after December, 8, 2008, those provisions are of no effect or are deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No new additional remuneration — after coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>47</Label><Text>No terms and conditions of employment established after the day on which this Act comes into force may provide, for any period that begins during the restraint period, for any additional remuneration that is new in relation to the additional remuneration that applied to the employees governed by those terms and conditions of employment immediately before the terms and conditions of employment become effective.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No new additional remuneration — December 8, 2008 until coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>48</Label><Text>If any terms and conditions of employment established at any time during the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on the day on which this Act comes into force contain, in relation to any employees, a provision that provides, for any period that begins during the restraint period, for any additional remuneration that is new in relation to the additional remuneration that applied to the employees governed by those terms and conditions of employment immediately before the effective date of the provisions, that provision is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No new additional remuneration — before December 8, 2008</MarginalNote><Label>49</Label><Text>If any terms and conditions of employment established before December 8, 2008 contain, in relation to any employees, a provision that provides, for any period that begins in the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on March 31, 2011, for any additional remuneration that is new in relation to the additional remuneration that applied to the employees governed by those terms and conditions of employment immediately before the first period that began on or after December 8, 2008, that provision is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Canada Border Services Agency</MarginalNote><Label>50</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>44</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>46</XRefInternal> do not apply in respect of pay notes applicable only to employees in the Canada Border Services Agency who were transferred to the Agency on its creation, but the rates of those pay notes may not be increased during any period that begins in any of the fiscal years referred to in section 16 by a percentage that is higher than the percentage set out in that section for that fiscal year.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Border Services Group</MarginalNote><Label>51</Label><Text>The following rules apply in respect of terms and conditions of employment governing employees in the Border Services Group whose employer is Her Majesty as represented by the Treasury Board:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if the restructuring permitted by paragraph <XRefInternal>31</XRefInternal>(a) occurs, paragraph <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal>(a) does not prevent terms and conditions of employment established after the day on which this Act comes into force from restructuring, as a result of a classification conversion, the rates of pay during the 2007–2008 or 2009–2010 fiscal year, and the increases set out in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> apply in respect of the restructured rates of pay;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if any terms and conditions of employment were established during the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on the day on which this Act comes into force and, as a result of a classification conversion, they contain provisions for the restructuring of rates of pay during the 2007–2008 or 2009–2010 fiscal year and the restructuring permitted by paragraph <XRefInternal>31</XRefInternal>(b) occurs, paragraph <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal>(b) does not apply in respect of those provisions, and the increases set out in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> apply in respect of the restructured rates of pay; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if any terms and conditions of employment were established before December 8, 2008 and, as a result of a classification conversion, they contain provisions for the restructuring of rates of pay during the 2009–2010 fiscal year and the restructuring permitted by paragraph <XRefInternal>31</XRefInternal>(c) occurs, paragraph <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal>(c) does not apply in respect of those provisions, and the increase set out in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> applies in respect of the restructured rates of pay.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Groups subject to national rates of pay</MarginalNote><Label>52</Label><Text>The following rules apply in respect of terms and conditions of employment governing employees in the Operational Services Group whose employer is Her Majesty as represented by the Treasury Board and employees in the General Labour and Trades Group and the General Services Group whose employer is Her Majesty as represented by the Parks Canada Agency or Her Majesty as represented by the Canadian Food Inspection Agency:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if the restructuring permitted by paragraph <XRefInternal>32</XRefInternal>(a) occurs, paragraph <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal>(a) does not prevent terms and conditions of employment established after the day on which this Act comes into force from restructuring rates of pay during the 2009–2010 fiscal year in order to create national rates of pay, and the increase set out in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> applies in respect of the restructured rates of pay;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if any terms and conditions of employment were established during the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on the day on which this Act comes into force and, in order to create national rates of pay, they contain provisions for the restructuring of rates of pay during the 2009–2010 fiscal year and the restructuring permitted by paragraph <XRefInternal>32</XRefInternal>(b) occurs, paragraph <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal>(b) does not apply in respect of those provisions, and the increase set out in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> applies in respect of the restructured rates of pay; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if any terms and conditions of employment were established before December 8, 2008 and, in order to create national rates of pay, they contains provisions for the restructuring of rates of pay during the 2009–2010 fiscal year and the restructuring permitted by paragraph <XRefInternal>32</XRefInternal>(c) occurs, paragraph <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal>(c) does not apply in respect of those provisions, and the increase set out in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> applies in respect of the restructured rates of pay.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Ships’ Officers Group</MarginalNote><Label>53</Label><Text>The following rules apply in respect of terms and conditions of employment established before December 8, 2008 that govern employees in the Ships’ Officers Group whose employer is Her Majesty as represented by the Treasury Board:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>paragraph <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal>(c) does not apply in respect of the provisions of those terms and conditions of employment that provide for the restructuring of rates of pay during the 2010–2011 fiscal year, and the increase set out in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> applies in respect of the restructured rates of pay; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>section <XRefInternal>49</XRefInternal> does not apply in respect of the provisions of those terms and conditions of employment that provide for the payment, during the 2010–2011 fiscal year, of a sum in lieu of vacation leave factors.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Law Group</MarginalNote><Label>54</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following rules apply in respect of terms and conditions of employment governing employees in the Law Group whose employer is Her Majesty as represented by the Treasury Board, and in respect of any period that begins during the restraint period:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case where the terms and conditions of employment are established after the day on which this Act comes into force,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the provisions of those terms and conditions of employment that provide for increases to rates of pay may not have retroactive effect in respect of a day that is earlier than May 10, 2006,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>any increase to rates of pay that the terms and conditions of employment provide for in respect of any period that begins during the 2006–2007 fiscal year must be based on the rates of pay set out in Schedule 2,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the provisions of those terms and conditions of employment must provide, for all employees of the Law Group, for the same performance pay plans that were in effect on May 9, 2006 for any employees in the Law Group and, in relation to any particular position level, those plans must be at the same amounts or rates that were in effect for that position level on that date but those plans may not have retroactive effect, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the provisions of those terms and conditions of employment may provide for any additional remuneration — other than a performance bonus — that applied to any position level in the Law Group on May 9, 2006, but the amount or rate of that additional remuneration for a particular position level may not be greater than the highest amount or rate that applied to employees of that position level on that date, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>those terms and conditions of employment may not provide for additional remuneration if that additional remuneration applied to no employee in the Law Group on May 9, 2006; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case where the terms and conditions of employment were established on or before the day on which this Act comes into force,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>if any of their provisions have retroactive effect in respect of a day that is earlier than May 10, 2006, that retroactive effect is deemed never to have had effect, the provision is deemed to have had retroactive effect as of May 10, 2006 and the first day of every other period referred to in that provision is deemed to be moved forward by the number of days that is equal to the number of days between the first day the provision was expressed to have retroactive effect and May 10, 2006,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>if the increase provided to rates of pay for any period that begins during the 2006–2007 fiscal year is based on rates of pay that are greater than those set out in Schedule 2, those greater rates of pay are of no effect or are deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be, and the increase is deemed to be based on the rates of pay set out in Schedule 2,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>if subparagraph (ii) applies, the provisions of the terms and conditions of employment that provide for rates of pay for every other period that begins on or before March 31, 2011 are of no effect or are deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be, and the rates of pay in those provisions are deemed to be the rates of pay that applied immediately before the beginning of that period as a result of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>if those terms and conditions of employment provide for performance pay plans and those plans are not the same as those that were in effect on May 9, 2006 for any employees in the Law Group or the amounts or rates provided for in those plans in relation to any particular position level are not the same as those of the performance pay plans that were in effect on that date — or the plans were expressed to be retroactive — the provisions that provide for those plans are of no effect or are deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be, and are deemed to be provisions that provide, for all employees in the Law Group, as of the day that the terms and conditions of employment were established, for the same performance pay plans that were in effect on May 9, 2006 for any employees in the Law Group at the same amounts or rates, in relation to any particular position level, that were in effect on that date,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>if those terms and conditions of employment do not provide for performance pay plans, they are deemed to provide, for all employees in the Law Group, as of the day that they were established, for the same performance pay plans that were in effect on May 9, 2006 for any employees in the Law Group at the same amounts or rates, in relation to any particular position level, that were in effect on that date,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>if those terms and conditions of employment provide for any additional remuneration — other than a performance bonus — that applied to any position level in the Law Group on May 9, 2006, and the amount or rate of that additional remuneration for a particular position level is greater than the highest amount or rate that applied to any employees of that position level on that date, the provisions that provide for that payment are deemed to be of no effect or are deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be, and are deemed to provide for the highest amount or rate, as the case may be, that applied in respect of any of those employees on that date, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>if those terms and conditions of employment provide for any additional remuneration, and that additional remuneration applied to no employee in the Law Group on May 9, 2006, the provision that provides for that payment is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other provisions apply</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the provisions of this Act that are not inconsistent with subsection (1) apply to terms and conditions of employment governing employees in the Law Group.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Members of Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Increase</MarginalNote><Label>55</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite subsections 55.1(2), 62.1(2), 62.2(2) and 62.3(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and subsections 4.1(2), (4) and (6) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, the increase in respect of allowances and salaries to be paid to members of the Senate and the House of Commons for the 2009–2010 fiscal year is to be 1.5%.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No increase</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite the provisions referred to in subsection (1), there are to be no increases in respect of allowances and salaries to be paid to members of the Senate and the House of Commons for the 2010–2011, 2011–2012 and 2012–2013 fiscal years.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Transition — 2013–2014 fiscal year</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In calculating the allowances and salaries to be paid to members of the Senate and the House of Commons for the 2013–2014 fiscal year, the indexing mentioned in the provisions referred to in subsection (1) is to be applied to the allowances and salaries payable to the members for the 2009–2010 fiscal year.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 2, s. 393 “55”; 2010, c. 12, s. 1649.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Inconsistent provisions</MarginalNote><Label>56</Label><Text>Any provision of any collective agreement that is entered into — or of any arbitral award that is made, or of any terms and conditions of employment that are established — after the day on which this Act comes into force that is inconsistent with this Act is of no effect.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Compensating for restraint measures prohibited</MarginalNote><Label>57</Label><Text>No provision of any collective agreement that is entered into — or of any arbitral award that is made, or of any terms and conditions of employment that are established — after the day on which this Act comes into force may provide for compensation for amounts that employees did not receive as a result of the restraint measures in this Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Provisions compensating for restraint measures of no effect</MarginalNote><Label>58</Label><Text>If a provision of a collective agreement that is entered into — or of an arbitral award that is made, or of terms and conditions of employment that are established — on or before the day on which this Act comes into force provides for compensation for amounts that employees did not receive as a result of the restraint measures in this Act, that provision is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No changes to performance pay plans — new collective agreements, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>59</Label><Text>No provision of any collective agreement that is entered into — or of any arbitral award that is made, or of any terms and conditions of employment that are established — after the day on which this Act comes into force may, for any period that begins during the restraint period, change the performance pay plans, including the amounts or rates, that apply to any employees governed by the agreement, award or terms and conditions of employment.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No changes to performance pay plans — existing collective agreements, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>60</Label><Text>If a provision of a collective agreement that is entered into — or of an arbitral award that is made, or of terms and conditions of employment that are established — during the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on the day on which this Act comes into force changes, for any period that begins during the restraint period, the performance pay plans, including the amounts or rates, that apply to any employees governed by the agreement, award or terms and conditions of employment, the change is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No changes to performance pay plans — existing collective agreements, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>61</Label><Text>If a provision of a collective agreement that is entered into — or of an arbitral award that is made, or of terms and conditions of employment that are established — before December 8, 2008 changes, for any period that begins in the period that begins on December 8, 2008 and ends on March 31, 2011, the performance pay plans, including the amounts or rates, that apply to any employees governed by the agreement, award or terms and conditions of employment, the change is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect, as the case may be.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Royal Canadian Mounted Police</MarginalNote><Label>62</Label><Text>Despite sections <XRefInternal>44</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>49</XRefInternal>, the Treasury Board may change the amount or rate of any allowance, or make any new allowance, applicable to members of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police if the Treasury Board is of the opinion that the change or the new allowance, as the case may be, is critical to support transformation initiatives relating to the Royal Canadian Mounted Police.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Administration</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Powers and duties of Treasury Board</MarginalNote><Label>63</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Treasury Board may exercise the powers and shall perform the duties in relation to this Act that are necessary to enable it to determine whether an employer of employees, other than employees referred to in paragraph <XRefInternal>13</XRefInternal>(1)(c) or (3)(a), is complying with this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information and documentation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Treasury Board may require from the employer any information and documentation that it considers necessary to enable it to determine whether the employer is complying with this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Treasury Board directive</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Treasury Board determines under this section that the employer is not complying with this Act, it may issue any directives that it considers appropriate to ensure the compliance.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Debt due to Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>64</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every amount paid — including amounts paid before the day on which this Act comes into force — to any person in excess of the amount that should have been paid as a result of this Act is a debt due to Her Majesty and may be recovered as such.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Overpayment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any amount that is a debt due to Her Majesty as a result of subsection (1) is deemed to be an overpayment to which subsection 155(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> applies.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, subsection (1) applies to, but is not limited to, the following amounts:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>amounts paid under a provision that by the operation of this Act is of no effect or is deemed never to have had effect; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>amounts paid as a result of the payment of any amount referred to in paragraph (a).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Orders</MarginalNote><Label>65</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Treasury Board, by order, amend Schedule 1 by adding to or deleting from it the name of any Crown corporation or public body.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 1</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 13 and 65)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Crown Corporations and Public Bodies</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canada Council for the Arts</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Conseil des Arts du Canada</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Broadcasting Corporation</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Société Radio-Canada</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Centre for Occupational Health and Safety</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Centre canadien d’hygiène et de sécurité au travail</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Commercial Corporation</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr> Corporation commerciale canadienne</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Museum of Civilization</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Musée canadien des civilisations</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Museum of Immigration at Pier 21</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Musée canadien de l’immigration du Quai 21</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Museum of Nature</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Musée canadien de la nature</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Tourism Commission</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission canadienne du tourisme</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>International Development Research Centre</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Centre de recherches pour le développement international</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>National Arts Centre Corporation</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Corporation du Centre national des Arts</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>National Battlefields Commission, The</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission des champs de bataille nationaux</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>National Gallery of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Musée des beaux-arts du Canada</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>National Museum of Science and Technology</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Musée national des sciences et de la technologie</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Office of the Communications Security Establishment Commissioner</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bureau du commissaire du Centre de la sécurité des télécommunications</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Telefilm Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Téléfilm Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 2, s. 393 "Sch. 1"; 2010, c. 7, s. 7.</HistoricalNote></Schedule><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 2</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 34 and 54)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Rates of Pay — Employees in the Law Group</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><TableGroup bilingual="no" pointsize="8" rowbreak="no" spanlanguages="no" spanmarginalnotecol="no"><table frame="topbot"><tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colsep="0" colwidth="10*" rowsep="0" /><colspec align="right" colname="2" colnum="2" colsep="0" colwidth="5*" rowsep="0" /><colspec align="right" colname="3" colnum="3" colsep="0" colwidth="2*" rowsep="0" /><colspec align="right" colname="4" colnum="4" colsep="0" colwidth="5*" rowsep="0" /><thead><row topdouble="yes" topmarginspacing="4"><entry rowsep="1" valign="top">All regions except Toronto</entry><entry align="right" rowsep="1" valign="top">Minimum</entry><entry rowsep="1" valign="top" /><entry align="right" rowsep="1" valign="top">Maximum</entry></row></thead><tbody><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry>LA-DEV</entry><entry align="right">$27,410</entry><entry /><entry align="right">$62,155</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry>LA-01</entry><entry align="right">$54,580</entry><entry /><entry align="right">$77,868</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry>LA-02(A) or LA-02(I)</entry><entry align="right">$75,622</entry><entry /><entry align="right">$108,525</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry>LA-02(B) or LA-02(II)</entry><entry align="right">$94,097</entry><entry /><entry align="right">$119,975</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry>LA-03(A)</entry><entry align="right">$107,300</entry><entry /><entry align="right">$136,300</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry>LA-03(B)</entry><entry align="right">$124,400</entry><entry /><entry align="right">$152,200</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry>LA-03(C)</entry><entry align="right">$141,700</entry><entry /><entry align="right">$172,800</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup><TableGroup bilingual="no" pointsize="8" rowbreak="no" spanlanguages="no" spanmarginalnotecol="no"><table frame="topbot"><tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colsep="0" colwidth="10*" rowsep="0" /><colspec align="right" colname="2" colnum="2" colsep="0" colwidth="5*" rowsep="0" /><colspec align="right" colname="3" colnum="3" colsep="0" colwidth="2*" rowsep="0" /><colspec align="right" colname="4" colnum="4" colsep="0" colwidth="5*" rowsep="0" /><tbody><row rowsep="1" topdouble="yes" topmarginspacing="8"><entry rowsep="1">Toronto region</entry><entry align="right" rowsep="1">Minimum</entry><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" rowsep="1">Maximum</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry>LA-DEV</entry><entry align="right">$27,410</entry><entry /><entry align="right">$62,155</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry>LA-01</entry><entry align="right">$54,585</entry><entry /><entry align="right">$77,868</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry>LA-02(A) or LA-02(I)</entry><entry align="right">$75,630</entry><entry /><entry align="right">$124,940</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry>LA-02(B) or LA-02(II)</entry><entry align="right">$98,840</entry><entry /><entry align="right">$138,075</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry>LA-03(A)</entry><entry align="right">$113,600</entry><entry /><entry align="right">$148,100</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry>LA-03(B)</entry><entry align="right">$124,400</entry><entry /><entry align="right">$152,200</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry>LA-03(C)</entry><entry align="right">$141,700</entry><entry /><entry align="right">$172,800</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Schedule><Schedule id="RelatedProvs"><ScheduleFormHeading type="amending"><TitleText>RELATED PROVISIONS</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><BillPiece><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2009, c. 2, s. 398</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>398</Label><Text>Sections 30 and 33 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Sector Equitable Compensation Act</XRefExternal> and sections <XRefInternal>396</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>397</XRefInternal> apply despite any provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Expenditure Restraint Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></BillPiece></Schedule></Statute>