<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE Statute PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Statute v2.0.0//EN" "Dtd/Version_2.0.0/Statute/Statute.dtd"><Statute bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes"><Identification><LongTitle>An Act to provide for the release of information that may assist in locating persons in default and other persons and to permit, for the enforcement of support orders and support provisions, the garnishment and attachment of certain moneys payable by Her Majesty in right of Canada</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Family Orders and Agreements Enforcement Assistance Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Family Orders and Agreements Enforcement Assistance</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>06</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber official="no">F-1.4</ConsolidatedNumber><AnnualStatuteId revised-statute="yes"><AnnualStatuteNumber>4 (2nd Supp.)</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>1985</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><ReaderNote><Note status="official" xml:space="default">[<Emphasis style="italic">1986, c. 5, assented to 13th February, 1986</Emphasis>]</Note></ReaderNote></Identification><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Family Orders and Agreements Enforcement Assistance Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>Release of Information</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>In this Part,</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>access right</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>droit d’accès</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>access right</DefinedTermEn> means a right, granted in an order or agreement, of access to or visitation of a child;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>court</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>tribunal</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>court</DefinedTermEn> means a court having jurisdiction with respect to the enforcement of family provisions;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>custody provision</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>disposition de garde</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>custody provision</DefinedTermEn> means a provision of an order or agreement awarding custody of a child;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>family provision</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>disposition familiale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>family provision</DefinedTermEn> means a support provision, a custody provision or an access right;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>information bank director</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>directeur de fichier</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>information bank director</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>with respect to any of the information banks controlled by the Department of Employment and Social Development that may be searched under this Part, the Minister of Employment and Social Development,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>with respect to any of the information banks controlled by the Canada Employment Insurance Commission that may be searched under this Part, the Chairman of the Canada Employment Insurance Commission, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>with respect to any of the information banks controlled by the Canada Revenue Agency that may be searched under this Part, the Minister of National Revenue;</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Justice;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>order</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ordonnance</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>order</DefinedTermEn> means any order or judgment, or interim order or judgment, relating to family support, custody or access that is enforceable in a province;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>provincial enforcement service</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>autorité provinciale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>provincial enforcement service</DefinedTermEn> means any service, agency or body designated in an agreement with a province under section 3 that is entitled under the laws of the province to enforce family provisions;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>provincial information bank</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>fichier provincial</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>provincial information bank</DefinedTermEn> means a source of information designated in an agreement made under section 3;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>support provision</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>disposition alimentaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>support provision</DefinedTermEn> means a provision of an order or agreement for maintenance, alimony or family financial support and includes any order for arrears of payments thereof.</Text></Definition><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 2; 1996, c. 11, ss. 95, 97(E), 99; 1997, c. 1, s. 16; 1999, c. 17, s. 158; 2005, c. 35, ss. 66, 67, c. 38, s. 138; 2012, c. 19, ss. 694, 695(E); 2013, c. 40, s. 229.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Federal-Provincial Agreements</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Agreements with provinces for application of Part</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>With the approval of the Governor in Council, the Minister may, on behalf of the Government of Canada, enter into agreements with each of the provinces concerning the searching for and the release of information under this Part.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Contents of agreements</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>Every agreement with a province under section 3 must provide for</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the establishment of safeguards in the province for the protection of information released under this Part; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the designation of the provincial information bank or banks that, subject to this Part, must be searched before information may be released under this Part.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Designation of provincial enforcement services</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>The Minister and a province may designate in an agreement made under section 3 one or more provincial enforcement services for the purposes of this Part.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Agreements regarding comprehensive pension plans</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>With the approval of the Governor in Council, the Minister of Employment and Social Development may, on behalf of the Government of Canada, enter into an agreement with each province providing a comprehensive pension plan, as defined under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, for the purpose of obtaining the approval of that province for</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the creation, for the purposes of this Act, of an information bank to be controlled by the Department of Employment and Social Development in respect of contributors to and beneficiaries under that comprehensive pension plan; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the release of information under this Part from the information bank referred to in paragraph (a) and from any other information bank controlled by the Department of Employment and Social Development that contains information in respect of contributors to and beneficiaries under that comprehensive pension plan.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 6; 1996, c. 11, ss. 95, 97; 2005, c. 35, s. 53; 2012, c. 19, ss. 694, 695; 2013, c. 40, s. 230.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Applications to Court</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Applications to court</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>Any person, service, agency or body entitled to have a family provision enforced may, by <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application, request that the court apply for the release to the court of information under this Part.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 7; 1993, c. 8, s. 6.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Applications in relation to family provisions</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An application under section 7 in relation to a family provision must be accompanied by</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a certified copy of the order, or a copy of the agreement, containing the support provision, custody provision or access right to which the application relates;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an affidavit in accordance with section 9; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>subject to subsection (2), proof, as supplied by the province where the court seized of the application has jurisdiction, that the provincial information banks designated with respect to that province have been searched for information helpful in locating, as the case may be, the person who is in arrears under the support provision or the child or children who is or are the object of the custody provision or access right.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Where proof not necessary</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The proof referred to in paragraph (1)(c) is not necessary where the affidavit in support of the application discloses that there are reasonable grounds to believe that the person, child or children referred to in that paragraph has or have left the province of the court seized of the application.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Contents of affidavit</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>An affidavit in support of an application under section 7 in relation to a family provision must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>allege a breach of the family provision;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>set out particulars of the breach and identify the person who</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>where the family provision is a support provision, is in arrears, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>where the family provision is a custody provision or access right, is believed to have possession of the child or children who is or are the object of the custody provision or access right;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>disclose that reasonable steps have been taken to locate the person who is in arrears or the child or children who is or are the object of the custody provision or access right and that the person, child or children have not been located;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>set out particulars of the reasonable steps referred to in paragraph (c); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>where the affidavit is not accompanied by the proof referred to in paragraph 8(1)(c), disclose that there are reasonable grounds to believe that the person, child or children referred to in paragraph (c) has or have left the province of the court seized of the application to which the affidavit relates and set out information in support of that belief.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><Label>10 and 11</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 1993, c. 8, s. 7]</Repealed></Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Court shall grant authorization</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>A court seized of a valid application under section 7 shall, if it is satisfied</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that reasonable steps have been taken to locate the person, child or children to whom the application relates, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>where it is alleged that the person, child or children to whom the application relates has or have left the province of the court, that the allegation is based on reasonable grounds,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>grant an authorization in writing authorizing any judge of that court or any officer thereof, as the case may be, to apply for the release of information under this Part.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 12; 1993, c. 8, s. 8.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Applications for the Release of Information</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Applications for the release of information</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>Subject to this Part, the following, namely,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a judge of a court or any officer thereof, if authorized to do so under section 12,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a provincial enforcement service, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a peace officer investigating a child abduction pursuant to section 282 or 283 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>may apply to the Minister, in the manner prescribed by the regulations, to have the information banks referred to in section 15 searched for the information referred to in section 16 and to have any such information found in those information banks released on a confidential basis.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 13; 1993, c. 8, s. 9; 1997, c. 1, s. 17.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Form of application</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An application under section 13 for the release of information must contain the information and be in the form prescribed by the regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Supporting documents</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where an application under section 13 is made by a person referred to in paragraph 13(a), the application must be accompanied by</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a copy of the family provision to which the application relates;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the applicant’s authorization under section 12;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a copy of the affidavit submitted in support of the application for the authorization; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>where the applicant’s affidavit does not contain the allegation referred to in paragraph 9(e), proof, as supplied by the province where the court that granted the authorization has jurisdiction, that the provincial information banks designated with respect to that province have been searched for information helpful in locating the person, child or children to whom the application relates.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Supporting documents for provincial enforcement service</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where an application under section 13 is made by a provincial enforcement service, the application must be accompanied by an affidavit submitted by an officer of the provincial enforcement service in accordance with subsection (4).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Supporting documents for peace officer</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>Where an application under section 13 is made by a peace officer investigating a child abduction pursuant to section 282 or 283 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, the application must be accompanied by</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a copy of the information to which the application relates; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an affidavit, submitted by the peace officer in accordance with subsection (5).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of affidavit</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An affidavit submitted by an officer of a provincial enforcement service must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>allege a breach of the family provision;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>set out particulars of the breach and identify the person who</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>where the family provision is a support provision, is in arrears, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>where the family provision is a custody provision or an access right, is believed to have possession of the child or children who is or are the object of the custody provision or access right;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>disclose that reasonable steps have been taken to locate the person who is in arrears or the child or children who is or are the object of the custody provision or access right and that the person, child or children has or have not been located;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>set out particulars of the reasonable steps referred to in paragraph (c); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>disclose</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>that the provincial information banks designated with respect to the province of the provincial enforcement service have been searched for information helpful in locating the person who is in arrears or the child or children who is or are the object of the custody provision or access right, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>that there are reasonable grounds to believe that the person, child or children referred to in subparagraph (i) has or have left the province of the provincial enforcement service, and set out information in support of that belief.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Idem</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An affidavit submitted by a peace officer must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>disclose that reasonable steps have been taken to locate the person against whom the information was laid and the child or children alleged to have been abducted and that the person, child or children has or have not been located;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>set out particulars of the reasonable steps referred to in paragraph (a); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>disclose</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>that the provincial information banks designated with respect to the province where the information was laid have been searched for information helpful in locating the person, child or children referred to in paragraph (a), or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>that there are reasonable grounds to believe that the person, child or children referred to in paragraph (a) has or have left the province where the information was laid, and set out information in support of that belief.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 14; 1993, c. 8, s. 10; 1997, c. 1, s. 18.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Information banks that may be searched</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Text>The information banks that may be searched under this Part are the information banks designated by the regulations from among the information banks controlled by the Department of Employment and Social Development, the Canada Revenue Agency and the Canada Employment Insurance Commission.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 15; 1996, c. 11, ss. 97, 99; 1997, c. 1, s. 19; 1999, c. 31, s. 91(F); 2005, c. 35, s. 66, c. 38, ss. 111, 146; 2012, c. 19, s. 695; 2013, c. 40, s. 237.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Information that may be released</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Text>The information that may be searched for and released under this Part is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the address of the person who, as the case may be,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>is in arrears under the support provision to which the application relates,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>is believed to have possession of the child or children who is or are the object of the custody provision or access right to which the application relates, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>is believed to have possession of the child or children who is or are the object of the investigation pursuant to section 282 or 283 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to which the application relates;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the name and address of the employer of the person referred to in paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the address of the child or children to whom the application relates; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the name and address of the employer of every child to whom the application relates.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Processing of Applications</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Request to information bank directors</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Text>Forthwith on the receipt of an application under section 13, the Minister shall transmit a search request to the information bank directors who shall, in accordance with the regulations, cause their designated information banks to be searched forthwith and periodically during the twelve month period immediately following the receipt by the Minister of the application.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 17; 1993, c. 8, s. 11.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Transfer of information between information banks</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Text>Subject to the regulations, information in any information banks that may be searched under this Part may be released by one information bank director to the other information bank director to assist that other director in conducting a search under this Part.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Transmission of information to Minister</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Text>Where information requested in an application under section 13 is found in an information bank that may be searched under this Part, the information bank director of that information bank shall cause to be transmitted to the Minister, in accordance with the regulations, all information obtained during any search conducted pursuant to section 17.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 19; 1993, c. 8, s. 12.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>New information</MarginalNote><Label>19.1</Label><Text>Where new information is obtained during a periodic search, the Minister shall not release the information to an applicant under section 13 unless the Minister is satisfied that the applicant still requires the information for the reasons set out in the application.</Text><HistoricalNote>1993, c. 8, s. 12.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Release of information to applicant</MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Text>The Minister shall release information under this Part to an applicant under section 13 only if the Minister is satisfied that the safeguards established by the agreement under section 3 with the province of that applicant are in place.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Exception for security name changes</MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Text>No information may be released under this Part in respect of any person whose identity has been changed for security or law enforcement purposes.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations by Governor in Council</MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prescribing the form of an application for the release of information under this Part and the information that must be contained therein;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>prescribing the manner in which an application for the searching of information banks and the release of information under this Part may be made;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>designating, for the purposes of section 15, the information banks that may be searched under this Part;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>setting out the manner in which searches for information under this Part are to be conducted;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>prescribing the conditions under which information may be released under section 18 by one information bank director to the other information bank director;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>establishing the procedures to be followed for the transmission to the Minister of information found in any information bank searched under this Part; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>generally, for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Part.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 22; 1997, c. 1, s. 20.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Garnishment of Federal Moneys to Satisfy Support Orders and Support Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this Part,</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>garnishable moneys</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>sommes saisissables</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>garnishable moneys</DefinedTermEn> means moneys authorized to be paid by Her Majesty by or under such Acts of Parliament or provisions thereof or programs thereunder as are designated by the regulations;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>garnishee summons</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>bref de saisie-arrêt</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>garnishee summons</DefinedTermEn> includes any document or court order of similar nature;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>garnishment</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinitionEnOnly>Version anglaise seulement</DefinitionEnOnly></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>garnishment</DefinedTermEn> includes attachment;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Her Majesty</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Sa Majesté</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Her Majesty</DefinedTermEn> means Her Majesty in right of Canada;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>judgment debtor</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>débiteur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>judgment debtor</DefinedTermEn> means a person named in a garnishee summons in respect of whom garnishable moneys are sought to be garnisheed under this Part;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Justice;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>provincial garnishment law</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>droit provincial en matière de saisie-arrêt</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>provincial garnishment law</DefinedTermEn> means the law of a province relating to garnishment as it applies to the enforcement of support orders and support provisions;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>support order</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ordonnance alimentaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>support order</DefinedTermEn> means an order or judgment for maintenance, alimony or family financial support that is enforceable in any province;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>support provision</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>entente alimentaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>support provision</DefinedTermEn> means a provision in an agreement relating to the payment of maintenance or family financial support that is enforceable by a garnishee summons under provincial garnishment law.</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Refund of tax payable to client not discounter</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding the acquisition by a discounter from a client of a right to a refund of tax for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tax Rebate Discounting Act</XRefExternal>, the refund of tax remains, for the purposes of this Part, payable to the client and not the discounter.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 23; 1992, c. 1, s. 66; 1993, c. 8, s. 13(F).</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Garnishment of Her Majesty</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Her Majesty may be garnisheed</MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any other Act of Parliament preventing the garnishment of Her Majesty, Her Majesty may, for the enforcement of support orders and support provisions, be garnisheed in accordance with this Part in respect of all garnishable moneys.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Provincial garnishment law applies</MarginalNote><Label>25</Label><Text>Subject to section 26 and any regulations made under this Part, garnishment under this Part shall be in accordance with provincial garnishment law.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 25; 1993, c. 8, s. 14.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Inconsistencies with provincial garnishment law</MarginalNote><Label>26</Label><Text>In the event of any inconsistency between this Part or a regulation made under this Part and provincial garnishment law, the provincial garnishment law is overridden to the extent of the inconsistency.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Location of garnishable moneys</MarginalNote><Label>27</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Part, garnishable moneys are deemed to be located in the jurisdiction of every court requested to issue a garnishee summons in respect thereof.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Garnishee Summons</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Service binds Her Majesty for five years</MarginalNote><Label>28</Label><Text>Subject to this Part and the regulations, service of the following documents on the Minister, namely,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a garnishee summons, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 1997, c. 1, s. 21]</Repealed></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an application in the form prescribed by the regulations,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>binds Her Majesty for five years in respect of all garnishable moneys payable to the judgment debtor named in the garnishee summons.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 28; 1993, c. 8, s. 15; 1997, c. 1, s. 21.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Calculation of five year period</MarginalNote><Label>29</Label><Text>For the purposes of section 28, the five year period referred to in that section commences on the expiration of the period prescribed by the regulations that immediately follows the service of the garnishee summons on the Minister.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 29; 1993, c. 8, s. 15.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Garnishee Summons of Continuing Effect</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Garnishee summons of continuing effect</MarginalNote><Label>30</Label><Text>Subject to section 31, where a garnishee summons of continuing effect is served on the Minister under this Part and garnishable moneys become payable to the judgment debtor in the five year period during which Her Majesty is bound by the garnishee summons, Her Majesty shall, at the expiration of that period, continue to be bound in accordance with the garnishee summons in respect of all subsequent payments of garnishable moneys to the judgment debtor that are authorized by the same Act of Parliament, provision thereof or program thereunder that authorized the payments of the garnishable moneys to the judgment debtor in the period during which Her Majesty was originally bound by the garnishee summons.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 30; 1993, c. 8, s. 15.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>31</Label><Text>Her Majesty shall cease to be bound under section 30 in respect of any garnishable moneys authorized by any particular Act of Parliament, provision thereof or program thereunder if no such moneys become payable to the judgment debtor for any period of one hundred and eighty consecutive days.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Service of Documents</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Time of service</MarginalNote><Label>32</Label><Text>A garnishee summons served on the Minister has effect only if it is served on the Minister in the first thirty days following the first day on which it could have been validly served on the Minister.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Place of service</MarginalNote><Label>33</Label><Text>Service of documents on the Minister in connection with garnishment proceedings permitted by this Part must be effected at the place specified in the regulations.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Method of service</MarginalNote><Label>34</Label><Text>In addition to any method of service permitted in accordance with provincial garnishment law, service of documents on the Minister under this Part may be effected by registered mail or by any other method prescribed in the regulations.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Service by registered mail</MarginalNote><Label>35</Label><Text>Where service of a document on the Minister under this Part is effected by registered mail, the document shall be deemed to be served on the day of its receipt by the Minister.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Administrative Procedures</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Notice to ministers</MarginalNote><Label>36</Label><Text>Forthwith after receipt of the documents referred to in section 28, the Minister shall notify every minister responsible for garnishable moneys of the service thereof and provide each such minister with such information as may be necessary to assist that other minister in determining whether any garnishable moneys are payable to the judgment debtor.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 36; 1993, c. 8, s. 16.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Initial report by ministers</MarginalNote><Label>37</Label><Text>Forthwith after being notified pursuant to section 36, each minister responsible for garnishable moneys shall report to the Minister on whether such moneys are payable or are foreseeably payable to the judgment debtor.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation to monitor and report back</MarginalNote><Label>38</Label><Text>In addition to reporting under section 37, each minister responsible for garnishable moneys shall continue to monitor the payments of those moneys the entire time during which Her Majesty is bound in respect of payments thereof and report to the Minister whenever any payments to the judgment debtor become payable or foreseeably payable.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Additional information with every report</MarginalNote><Label>39</Label><Text>When reporting that garnishable moneys are payable or are foreseeably payable to the judgment debtor, each minister shall also inform the Minister of the amounts payable and the times when those moneys became, or will become, payable.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right to search information banks</MarginalNote><Label>40</Label><Text>Subject to the regulations, every minister responsible for garnishable moneys is entitled to have any of the information banks that may be searched under Part I searched for any information that minister deems necessary to confirm the identity of any judgment debtor.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Response to Garnishee Summons</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Response time</MarginalNote><Label>41</Label><Text>The Minister, on behalf of Her Majesty, shall respond to every garnishee summons within the time prescribed by the regulations.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Methods of response to garnishee summons</MarginalNote><Label>42</Label><Text>In addition to any method of responding to a garnishee summons permitted by provincial garnishment law, the Minister may respond to a garnishee summons by registered mail or by any other method prescribed by the regulations.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Response by registered mail</MarginalNote><Label>43</Label><Text>Where the Minister responds to a garnishee summons by registered mail, the receipt issued in accordance with regulations relating to registered mail made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Post Corporation Act</XRefExternal> shall be received in evidence and is, unless the contrary is shown, proof that the Minister has responded to the garnishee summons.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Discharge of Liability</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Effect of payment into court</MarginalNote><Label>44</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A payment into court by the Minister is, to the extent of the payment, a good and sufficient discharge of Her Majesty’s liability under this Part and under the legislation governing the garnishable moneys.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of payment to provincial enforcement service</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where a payment to a provincial enforcement service as defined in section 2 is permitted under the provincial garnishment law of the province of a provincial enforcement service, a payment to the provincial enforcement service by the Minister is, to the extent of the payment, a good and sufficient discharge of Her Majesty’s liability under this Part and under the legislation governing the garnishable moneys.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Notice to Judgment Debtor</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Notice to judgment debtor</MarginalNote><Label>45</Label><Text>Where a garnishee summons is served on the Minister under this Part, the Minister shall, in the form, within the time and in the manner prescribed by the regulations, notify the judgment debtor named in the garnishee summons of that service.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 45; 1993, c. 8, s. 17.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><Label>46 to 48</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 1993, c. 8, s. 17]</Repealed></Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Recovery of Payments</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Payments to judgment debtor</MarginalNote><Label>49</Label><Text>Where a judgment debtor is paid any garnishable moneys to which he is not entitled by reason of garnishment proceedings permitted under this Part, the amount thereof is a debt due to Her Majesty by the judgment debtor and may be recovered as such in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> or the legislation governing the particular garnishable moneys paid to the judgment debtor.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Payments to party that instituted proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>50</Label><Text>Subject to section 51, where garnishable moneys are paid under this Part to or for the benefit of a party that instituted garnishment proceedings permitted under this Part in excess of the amount that should be paid to or for the benefit of that party, the amount thereof is a debt due to Her Majesty by that party and may be recovered as such in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> or by deduction or set-off against any garnishable moneys payable to or for the benefit of that party under this Part.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>51</Label><Text>Where it is determined that the reason for the payment of excess moneys referred to in section 50 is that the judgment debtor was not entitled to the garnishable moneys garnisheed under this Part, the amount of the excess is a debt due to Her Majesty by the judgment debtor and may be recovered as such in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> or the legislation governing the garnishable moneys garnisheed under this Part.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Ranking of Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>52</Label><Text>When a judgment debtor is indebted to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>Her Majesty, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>Her Majesty in right of a province on account of taxes payable to any province, and an agreement exists between Canada and the province under which Canada is authorized to collect the tax on behalf of the province,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>Her Majesty ranks in priority over the party that instituted the garnishment proceedings permitted under this Part with respect to any garnishable moneys that are payable to the judgment debtor notwithstanding that a garnishee summons in respect of those moneys has been served on the Minister, and the amount of the indebtedness may be recovered or retained in any manner authorized by law.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 52; 2001, c. 4, s. 81.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Multiple garnishee summonses</MarginalNote><Label>53</Label><Text>Where more than one garnishee summons is served on the Minister under this Part in respect of the same judgment debtor and the garnishable moneys payable to the judgment debtor are insufficient to satisfy all the garnishee summonses, payment shall be made on a proportional basis.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No execution against Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>54</Label><Text>No execution shall issue on a judgment given against Her Majesty in garnishment proceedings permitted by this Part.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Garnishment, Attachment and Pension Diversion Act</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Garnishment, Attachment and Pension Diversion Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>55</Label><Text>In the event that a garnishee summons that binds Her Majesty may be honoured under this Part or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Garnishment, Attachment and Pension Diversion Act</XRefExternal>, the garnishee summons shall be honoured first under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Garnishment, Attachment and Pension Diversion Act</XRefExternal> and secondly under this Part.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Prohibitions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition on disentitlement</MarginalNote><Label>56</Label><Text>No person may be disentitled or disqualified in respect of any payment or future payment of garnishable moneys solely on the ground that garnishment proceedings permitted by this Part may be or have been taken in respect of that person.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition on dismissal</MarginalNote><Label>57</Label><Text>No person may be dismissed, suspended or laid off solely on the ground that garnishment proceedings permitted by this Part may be or have been taken in respect of that person.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Fee</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Fee</MarginalNote><Label>58</Label><Text>A fee in the amount prescribed by the regulations is chargeable in respect of the processing of every garnishee summons served on the Minister.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Chargeable against judgment debtor</MarginalNote><Label>59</Label><Text>Subject to any regulations respecting the remittance thereof, the fee referred to in section 58 is a debt due to Her Majesty by the judgment debtor and may, subject to section 60, be recovered by deduction or set-off against any garnishable moneys payable to the judgment debtor.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>60</Label><Text>The fee referred to in section 58 may not be recovered out of any garnishable moneys to be used to honour a garnishee summons.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>61</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>designating Acts of Parliament, provisions thereof and programs thereunder for the purposes of the definition <DefinedTermEn>garnishable moneys</DefinedTermEn>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>prescribing the percentage of the amount of garnishable moneys, in relation to the Act of Parliament or provision thereof or program thereunder by or under which the garnishable moneys are authorized to be paid, that is to be exempt from the enforcement of support orders and support provisions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>prescribing the form of the application referred to in paragraph 28(c);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>prescribing the period of time before which Her Majesty becomes bound by the service of the documents referred to in section 28;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>specifying the place where service of documents on the Minister must be effected in connection with garnishment proceedings permitted under this Part;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>prescribing the methods in which service of documents in connection with garnishment proceedings permitted under this Part may be effected on the Minister;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>respecting the conducting of searches for the purposes of this Part of the information banks that may be searched under Part I;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>prescribing the time within which and the methods by which the Minister must respond to garnishee summonses;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>prescribing the form of the notification referred to in section 45 and the time within which and the manner in which it must be sent;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>prescribing a fee in respect of the processing of garnishee summonses and the manner of collecting the fee;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>respecting the remission, in whole or in part, of the fee referred to in section 58; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>generally, for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Part.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 61; 1993, c. 8, s. 18.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Licence Denial</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>62</Label><Text>The definitions in this section apply in this Part.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>appropriate Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre compétent</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>appropriate Minister</DefinedTermEn> means a minister of the Crown in right of Canada who is responsible for the issuance of any type or class of licence set out in the schedule.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>debtor</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>débiteur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>debtor</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is in arrears under a support order or a support provision.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>licence</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>autorisation</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>licence</DefinedTermEn> means a licence, a permit, a certificate or an authorization of any kind, and includes a passport within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Canadian Passport Order</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>licence denial application</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>demande de refus d’autorisation</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>licence denial application</DefinedTermEn> means an application made under section 67.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Justice.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>persistent arrears</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>être en défaut de façon répétée</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>persistent arrears</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of a support order or support provision, means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>arrears in any amount where the arrears are due to the failure to make in full the payments required in respect of any three payment periods, within the meaning of the support order or the support provision, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>accumulated arrears of $3000 or more.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>prescribed</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinitionEnOnly>Version anglaise seulement</DefinitionEnOnly></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>prescribed</DefinedTermEn> means prescribed by the regulations.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>provincial enforcement service</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>autorité provinciale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>provincial enforcement service</DefinedTermEn> has the meaning assigned by section 2.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>schedule licence</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>autorisation visée</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>schedule licence</DefinedTermEn> means a licence of a type or class set out in the schedule.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>support order</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ordonnance alimentaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>support order</DefinedTermEn> has the meaning assigned by subsection 23(1).</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>support provision</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>disposition alimentaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>support provision</DefinedTermEn> means a provision in an agreement relating to the payment of maintenance or family financial support that is enforceable under provincial law.</Text></Definition><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 62; 1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Amendments to schedule</MarginalNote><Label>63</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, add to or delete from the schedule any type or class of licence that may be issued to an individual under an Act of Parliament or under an order made pursuant to a prerogative of the Crown.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 63; 1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Purpose of Part</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose of Part</MarginalNote><Label>64</Label><Text>The purpose of this Part is to help provincial enforcement services enforce support orders and support provisions by providing for the denial of certain licences to debtors who are in persistent arrears.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 64; 1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Application of Part</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Application of Part</MarginalNote><Label>65</Label><Text>This Part applies notwithstanding the provisions of any other Act of Parliament, of any regulation or order made under any other Act of Parliament or of any order made pursuant to a prerogative of the Crown respecting the issuance, renewal or suspension of licences.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 65; 1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Royal prerogative</MarginalNote><Label>66</Label><Text>Nothing in this Part in any manner limits or affects Her Majesty’s royal prerogative with respect to passports.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 4 (2nd Supp.), s. 66; 1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Licence Denial Application</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>67</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where a debtor is in persistent arrears under a support order or a support provision, a provincial enforcement service may apply to the Minister that the following actions be taken against the debtor:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that no new schedule licences be issued to the debtor;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that all schedule licences held by the debtor be suspended; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>that schedule licences held by the debtor not be renewed.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An application must be in the prescribed form and must contain the prescribed information concerning</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the identity of the debtor; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the support order or support provision.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of supporting affidavit</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An application must be accompanied by an affidavit in the prescribed form. The affidavit must be submitted by an officer of the provincial enforcement service and must contain the following statements:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that the provincial enforcement service is satisfied that the debtor is in persistent arrears under the support order or the support provision;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that the provincial enforcement service has made reasonable attempts to enforce the support order or the support provision before making the licence denial application; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>that the provincial enforcement service has sent a notice to the debtor, at the debtor’s last known address,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>stating that the provincial enforcement service has reasonable grounds to believe that the debtor is in persistent arrears under the support order or support provision,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>stating that the provincial enforcement service intends to make a licence denial application in relation to the debtor,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>informing the debtor of the consequences to the debtor of a licence denial application, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>advising the debtor that a licence denial application will not be made if the debtor enters into a payment plan that is acceptable to the provincial enforcement service or satisfies the provincial enforcement service that the debtor is unable to pay the amount in arrears and that the making of the application is not reasonable in the circumstances.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time for making application</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An application may be made only after thirty days have expired after the notice referred to in subsection (3) was received by the debtor.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deemed receipt</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A notice referred to in subsection (3) is deemed to have been received by a debtor ten days after it is sent to the debtor.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Processing of Licence Denial Applications</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Informing appropriate Ministers</MarginalNote><Label>68</Label><Text>Immediately on the receipt of a licence denial application and the affidavit referred to in subsection 67(3), the Minister shall inform each appropriate Minister of the receipt of the application, and shall provide the appropriate Minister with such information as may be necessary to help the appropriate Minister determine whether the debtor to whom the application relates is the holder of a schedule licence.</Text><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Obligations of Appropriate Ministers</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Determination — does debtor hold schedule licence</MarginalNote><Label>69</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On being informed of a licence denial application in respect of a debtor, an appropriate Minister shall immediately determine whether the debtor is the holder of a schedule licence issued by the appropriate Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Suspension and non-renewal of schedule licences</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If an appropriate Minister determines that a debtor is the holder of a schedule licence, the appropriate Minister shall suspend the schedule licence and, where applicable, refuse to renew the schedule licence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to debtor</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An appropriate Minister who takes any action under subsection (2) against a debtor shall send the debtor a notice in writing informing the debtor that the action has been taken.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Refusal to issue schedule licence</MarginalNote><Label>70</Label><Text>An appropriate Minister who is informed of a licence denial application in respect of a debtor shall refuse to issue a schedule licence to the debtor.</Text><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>No Appeal</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>No appeal</MarginalNote><Label>71</Label><Text>Notwithstanding the provisions of any other Act of Parliament, of any regulation or order made under any other Act of Parliament or of any order made pursuant to a prerogative of the Crown, no appeal lies from any action taken under this Part.</Text><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Request to Terminate Application of Part</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Request to terminate application of Part</MarginalNote><Label>72</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A provincial enforcement service shall immediately request that all actions taken under this Part in respect of a debtor be terminated where</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the provincial enforcement service is satisfied that the debtor</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>is no longer in arrears under all support orders and support provisions against the debtor that have been enforced by a licence denial application,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>is complying, in respect of all support orders and support provisions against the debtor that have been enforced by a licence denial application, with a payment plan that the provincial enforcement service considers reasonable, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>is unable to pay the amount in arrears and that the application of this Part against the debtor is not reasonable in the circumstances; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the provincial enforcement service ceases to enforce all support orders and support provisions against the debtor that have been enforced by a licence denial application.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prescribed manner</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A request under subsection (1) must be made to the Minister in the prescribed manner.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Informing appropriate Ministers</MarginalNote><Label>73</Label><Text>Where the Minister receives a request under section 72, the Minister shall immediately inform each appropriate Minister of the receipt of the request.</Text><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation of appropriate Ministers</MarginalNote><Label>74</Label><Text>Immediately on being informed under section 73, each appropriate Minister shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>cancel the suspension of every schedule licence suspended by that appropriate Minister and inform the licence holder that the suspension has been cancelled;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>stop refusing to renew schedule licences of the debtor solely on the basis of this Part; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>stop refusing to issue schedule licences to the debtor solely on the basis of this Part.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>When licence not revived</MarginalNote><Label>75</Label><Text>The cancellation of the suspension of a schedule licence pursuant to section 74 does not operate to revive the licence if the term of the licence expired while the suspension was in force.</Text><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Offence</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>76</Label><Text>Every person who is notified that a passport issued to the person has been suspended under this Part and who fails to return the passport forthwith to a Passport Office, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Canadian Passport Order</XRefExternal>, or who subsequently uses the passport after being so notified, is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to a fine not exceeding $5,000 or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months or to both.</Text><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>No Liability</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>No liability</MarginalNote><Label>77</Label><Text>No action lies against Her Majesty in right of Canada, any Minister of the Crown in right of Canada or any officer or employee of Her Majesty in right of Canada for anything done or omitted to be done, or purported to be done or omitted to be done, in good faith in the administration of this Part or the discharge of any obligation, power or duty under this Part.</Text><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>78</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations prescribing anything that by this Part is to be or may be prescribed.</Text><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Release Authorization and Confidentiality</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Release Authorization</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Release authorization</MarginalNote><Label>79</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any provision in any other Act of Parliament that prohibits or restricts the release of information, the following information may be released for the purposes of this Act:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>information in any information bank that may be searched under Part I,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>information that is necessarily incidental to the garnishment of moneys under Part II, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>information that is necessarily incidental to the administration of Part III.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Prohibition, Offence and Punishment</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition</MarginalNote><Label>80</Label><Text>No officer or employee of Her Majesty, and no person who is hired on a contractual basis by Her Majesty to assist in the administration of this Act, who obtains any information pursuant to this Act shall, except as provided in this Act, knowingly communicate or knowingly allow the information to be communicated to any person, or knowingly allow any person to inspect or have access to any statement or other writing containing the information.</Text><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>81</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes section 80 is guilty of an offence, and is liable on summary conviction to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months or to a fine not exceeding $1,000, or to both.</Text><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Limitation period</MarginalNote><Label>82</Label><Text>Any proceedings under section 81 may be instituted at any time within but not later than three years after the time when the subject-matter of the proceedings arose.</Text><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 1, s. 22.</HistoricalNote></Section></Body><Schedule><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 62 and 63)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Licences</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><DocumentInternal><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText>Canadian Passport Order</TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes" xml:lang="en"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Passport</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Passeport</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></Provision></Group><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText>Aeronautics Act</TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes" xml:lang="en"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Air traffic controller</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Contrôleur de la circulation aérienne</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Aircraft maintenance engineer</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Technicien d’entretien d’aéronefs</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Airline transport pilot — aeroplane</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Pilote de ligne — avion</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Airline transport pilot — helicopter</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Pilote de ligne — hélicoptère</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Balloon pilot</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Pilote de ballon</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Commercial pilot — aeroplane</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Pilote professionnel — avion</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Commercial pilot — helicopter</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Pilote professionnel — hélicoptère</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Flight engineer</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Mécanicien navigant</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Foreign licence validation</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Validation de licence étrangère</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Glider pilot</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Pilote de planeur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Medical certificate</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Certificat médical</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Pilot — gyroplane</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Pilote — autogire</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Pilot — recreational — aeroplane</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Pilote de loisir — avion</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Pilot — recreational — helicopter</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Pilote de loisir — hélicoptère</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Pilot — ultra-light aeroplane</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Pilote — avion ultra-léger</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Private pilot — aeroplane</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Pilote privé — avion</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Private pilot — helicopter</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Pilote privé — hélicoptère</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></Provision></Group><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText>Canada Shipping Act or Canada Shipping Act, 2001</TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes" xml:lang="en"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Able seafarer</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Navigant qualifié</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Able seaman</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Matelot qualifié</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Air cushion vehicle (ACV) engineer, class I</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien d’aéroglisseur, classe I</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Air cushion vehicle (ACV) engineer, class II</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien d’aéroglisseur, classe II</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Air cushion vehicle (ACV) type rating</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Qualification de type d’aéroglisseur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Ballast control operator</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Opérateur des commandes de ballasts</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Barge supervisor, MODU/inland</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Surveillant de chaland, UMFM/eaux internes</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Barge supervisor, MODU/self-elevating</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Surveillant de chaland, UMFM/auto-élévatrice</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Barge supervisor, MODU/surface</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Surveillant de chaland, UMFM/surface</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Barge supervisor, MOU/self-elevating</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Superviseur de barge, UML/auto-élévatrice</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Barge supervisor, MOU/surface</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Superviseur de barge, UML/surface</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Bridge watch rating</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Matelot de quart à la passerelle</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Bridge watchman</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Homme de quart à la passerelle</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Certificate of service as master of a fishing vessel of less than 60 gross tonnage</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Brevet de service de capitaine de bâtiment de pêche, jauge brute de moins de 60</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Certificate of service as master of a fishing vessel of not more than 100 tons, gross tonnage</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Brevet de service de capitaine de bateau de pêche d’au plus 100 tonneaux de jauge brute</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Certificate of service as master of a ship of not more than 1 600 tons, gross tonnage</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Brevet de service de capitaine de navire d’au plus 1 600 tonneaux de jauge brute</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Certificate of service as master of a steamship of not more than 350 tons, gross tonnage</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Brevet de service de capitaine de navire à vapeur d’au plus 350 tonneaux de jauge brute</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Chief engineer, motor ship</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien en chef, navire à moteur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Chief engineer, motor-driven fishing vessel</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien en chef, navire de pêche à moteur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Chief engineer, steamship</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien en chef, navire à vapeur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Chief mate</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Premier officier de pont</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Chief mate 150 gross tonnage, domestic</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Premier officier de pont, jauge brute de 150, navigation intérieure</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Chief mate 500 gross tonnage, domestic</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Premier officier de pont, jauge brute de 500, navigation intérieure</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Chief mate, limited</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Premier officier de pont, avec restrictions</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Chief mate, near coastal</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Premier officier de pont, à proximité du littoral</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Compass adjuster</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Expert en compensation de compas</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Electrician</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Électricien</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Engine-room assistant</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Adjoint de la salle des machines</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Engine-room rating</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Matelot de la salle des machines</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>First mate, inland waters</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Premier lieutenant, eaux intérieures</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>First mate, intermediate run ferry</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Premier lieutenant de transbordeur à trajet intermédiaire</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>First mate, intermediate voyage</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Premier officier de pont, voyage intermédiaire</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>First mate, limited</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Premier officier de pont, avec restrictions</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>First mate, local voyage</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Premier officier de pont, voyage local</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>First mate, long run ferry</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Premier lieutenant de transbordeur à trajet long</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>First mate, short run ferry</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Premier lieutenant de transbordeur à trajet court</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>First-class engineer, motor ship</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien de première classe, navire à moteur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>First-class engineer, steamship</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien de première classe, navire à vapeur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Fishing master</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine de bateau de pêche</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Fishing master, first-class</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine de bâtiment de pêche, première classe</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Fishing master, first-class</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine de bateau de pêche, première classe</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Fishing master, fourth-class</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine de bâtiment de pêche, quatrième classe</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Fishing master, fourth-class</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine de bateau de pêche, quatrième classe</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Fishing master, restricted</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine de bateau de pêche, avec restrictions</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Fishing master, second-class</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine de bâtiment de pêche, deuxième classe</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Fishing master, second-class</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine de bateau de pêche, deuxième classe</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Fishing master, third-class</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine de bâtiment de pêche, troisième classe</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Fishing master, third-class</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine de bateau de pêche, troisième classe</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Fishing mate</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Lieutenant de bateau de pêche</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Fourth-class engineer, motor ship</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien de quatrième classe, navire à moteur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Fourth-class engineer, steamship</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien de quatrième classe, navire à vapeur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>High-speed craft (HSC) type rating</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Qualification de type d’engin à grande vitesse</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Liquefied gas tanker familiarization</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Familiarisation pour bâtiment-citerne pour gaz liquéfié</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Maintenance supervisor, MODU/self-elevating</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Surveillant de la maintenance, UMFM/auto-élévatrice</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Maintenance supervisor, MODU/surface</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Surveillant de la maintenance, UMFM/surface</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Maintenance supervisor, MOU/self-elevating</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Chef de l’entretien, UML/auto-élévatrice</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Maintenance supervisor, MOU/surface</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Chef de l’entretien, UML/surface</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master 150 gross tonnage, domestic</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine, jauge brute de 150, navigation intérieure</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master 500 gross tonnage, domestic</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine, jauge brute de 500, navigation intérieure</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master 500 gross tonnage, near coastal</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine, jauge brute de 500, à proximité du littoral</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master 3 000 gross tonnage, domestic</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine, jauge brute de 3 000, navigation intérieure</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master 3 000 gross tonnage, domestic limited to a near coastal voyage, class 2 if the voyage is a “minor waters voyage” as defined in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Shipping Act</XRefExternal>, in the version that was in force immediately before the coming into force of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Shipping Act, 2001</XRefExternal></BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine, jauge brute de 3 000, navigation intérieure, limité aux voyages à proximité du littoral, classe 2, s’il sagit de voyages en « eaux secondaires » au sens de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur la marine marchande du Canada</XRefExternal>, dans sa version en vigueur avant l’entrée en vigueur de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi de 2001 sur la marine marchande du Canada</XRefExternal></BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master 3 000 gross tonnage, near coastal</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine, jauge brute de 3 000, à proximité du littoral</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master mariner</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine au long cours</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master, inland waters</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine, eaux intérieures</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master, intermediate run ferry</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine de transbordeur à trajet intermédiaire</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master, intermediate voyage</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine, voyage intermédiaire</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master, limited</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine, avec restrictions</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master, local voyage</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine, voyage local</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master, long run ferry</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine de transbordeur à trajet long</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master, near coastal</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine, à proximité du littoral</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master, ship of not more than 350 gross tonnage or tug, home trade or inland waters</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine, navire d’au plus 350 tonneaux de jauge brute ou remorqueur, cabotage ou eaux intérieures</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master, ship of not more than 350 tons, gross tonnage, or tug, home trade voyage</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine, navire d’au plus 350 tonneaux de jauge brute ou remorqueur, cabotage</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master, ship of not more than 350 tons, gross tonnage, or tug, inland waters voyage</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine, navire d’au plus 350 tonneaux de jauge brute ou remorqueur, eaux intérieures</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master, ship of not more than 350 tons, gross tonnage, or tug, local voyage</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine, navire d’au plus 350 tonneaux de jauge brute ou remorqueur, voyage local</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Master, short run ferry</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Capitaine de transbordeur à trajet court</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>MODU</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>UMFM</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Offshore installation manager, MODU/inland</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Directeur d’installation extracôtière, UMFM/eaux internes</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Offshore installation manager, MODU/self-elevating</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Directeur d’installation extracôtière, UMFM/auto-élévatrice</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Offshore installation manager, MODU/surface</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Directeur d’installation extracôtière, UMFM/surface</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Offshore installation manager, MOU/self-elevating</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Chef de l’installation au large, UML/auto-élévatrice</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Offshore installation manager, MOU/surface</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Chef de l’installation au large, UML/surface</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Oil and chemical tanker familiarization</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Familiarisation pour pétrolier et bâtiment-citerne pour produits chimiques</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Passenger safety management</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Gestion de la sécurité des passagers</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Proficiency in chemical tankers</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Compétence en transporteurs de produits chimiques</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Proficiency in compass deviation</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Compétence en dérive du compas</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Proficiency in fast rescue boats</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Aptitude à l’exploitation des canots de secours rapides</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Proficiency in liquefied gas tankers</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Compétence en transporteurs de gaz liquéfié</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Proficiency in oil tankers</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Compétence en pétroliers</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Proficiency in survival craft and rescue boats other than fast rescue boats</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Aptitude à l’exploitation des bateaux de sauvetage et canots de secours, autres que des canots de secours rapides</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Restricted engineer, motor ship</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien, avec restrictions, navire à moteur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Restricted proficiency in survival craft and rescue boats other than fast rescue boats</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Aptitude à l’exploitation des bateaux de sauvetage et canots de secours, autres que des canots de secours rapides, avec restrictions</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Restricted watchkeeping mate, ship</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier de pont de quart de navire, avec restrictions</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Ro-ro passenger, level 1</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Navire roulier à passagers, niveau 1</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Ro-ro passenger, level 2</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Navire roulier à passagers, niveau 2</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Second engineer, motor ship</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien en second, navire à moteur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Second engineer, steamship</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien en second, navire à vapeur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Second mate, inland waters</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Deuxième lieutenant, eaux intérieures</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Second-class engineer, motor ship</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien de deuxième classe, navire à moteur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Second-class engineer, steamship</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien de deuxième classe, navire à vapeur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Ship’s cook</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Cuisinier de navire</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Small vessel machinery operator</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Opérateur des machines de petits bâtiments</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Specialized passenger safety management (ro-ro vessels)</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Gestion spécialisée de la sécurité des passagers (bâtiments rouliers)</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Supervisor of a chemical transfer operation</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Surveillant d’opérations de transbordement de produits chimiques</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Supervisor of a liquefied gas transfer operation</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Surveillant d’opérations de transbordement de gaz liquéfié</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Supervisor of an oil transfer operation</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Surveillant d’opérations de transbordement de pétrole</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Supervisor of an oil transfer operation in Arctic waters (north of 60° N)</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Surveillant d’opérations de transbordement de pétrole, eaux de l’Arctique (au nord de 60° N.)</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Third-class engineer, motor ship</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien de troisième classe, navire à moteur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Third-class engineer, steamship</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien de troisième classe, navire à vapeur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Watchkeeping engineer, motor-driven fishing vessel</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien de quart, bateau de pêche à moteur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Watchkeeping engineer, motor-driven fishing vessel</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier mécanicien de quart, bâtiment de pêche à moteur</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Watchkeeping mate</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier de pont de quart</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Watchkeeping mate fishing</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Lieutenant de quart de navire de pêche</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Watchkeeping mate, MODU/inland</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier de pont de quart, UMFM/eaux internes</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Watchkeeping mate, MODU/self-elevating</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier de pont de quart, UMFM/auto-élévatrice</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Watchkeeping mate, MODU/surface</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier de pont de quart, UMFM/surface</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Watchkeeping mate, near coastal</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier de pont de quart, à proximité du littoral</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Watchkeeping mate, ship</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Officier de pont de quart de navire </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></Provision></Group></DocumentInternal><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 1, s. 23; SOR/98-511; SOR/2011-37.</HistoricalNote></Schedule><Schedule id="RelatedProvs"><ScheduleFormHeading type="amending"><TitleText>RELATED PROVISIONS</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><BillPiece><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 1993, c. 8, ss. 19(3), (4)</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Idem</MarginalNote><Label>(19)</Label><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Sections 7, 12, 13, 14, 17, 19 and 19.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Family Orders and Agreements Enforcement Assistance Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted or amended by sections 6 and 8 to 12 of this Act, apply only to applications for the release of information received under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Family Orders and Agreements Enforcement Assistance Act</XRefExternal> after the coming into force of those sections.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Idem</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Sections 28 to 30 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Family Orders and Agreements Enforcement Assistance Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 15 of this Act, apply only to garnishee summonses served after the coming into force of that section.</Text></Subsection></Section></BillPiece></Schedule></Statute>