<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE Statute PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Statute v2.0.0//EN" "Dtd/Version_2.0.0/Statute/Statute.dtd"><Statute bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes"><Identification><LongTitle>An Act relating to the forgiveness of debts incurred or assumed in respect of certain official development assistance loans made by the Government of Canada to the Governments of Togo and of the Islamic Republic of Mauritania and also to the former East African Community</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Forgiveness of Certain Official Development Assistance Debts Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Forgiveness of Certain Official Development Assistance Debts</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>1987</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>30</DD></Date></Stages><Stages stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>06</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber official="no">F-30.2</ConsolidatedNumber><AnnualStatuteId revised-statute="no"><AnnualStatuteNumber>27</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>1987</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter></Identification><Introduction><Enacts><Provision language-align="no" format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Forgiveness of Certain Official Development Assistance Debts Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Debts owing by Togo</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The official development assistance debts owing by the Government of Togo to the Government of Canada under the loan agreements entered into between those governments and referred to in Part I of the schedule are hereby forgiven.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Debt owing by Mauritania</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The official development assistance debt owing by the Government of the Islamic Republic of Mauritania to the Government of Canada under the loan agreement entered into between those governments and referred to in Part II of the schedule is hereby forgiven.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Debts owing in relation to loans made to the East African Community</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The debts assumed by the governments of the United Republic of Tanzania, of the Republic of Uganda and of Kenya in accordance with agreements entered into between those governments and the Government of Canada and referred to in Part IV of the schedule, being agreements for the apportionment of liabilities that arose, before the dissolution of the former East African Community, under the loan agreements referred to in Part III of the schedule, are hereby forgiven.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Deletion from the accounts of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>The amount outstanding as recorded in the accounts of Canada in respect of the debts forgiven by sections 2 to 4 is hereby written off as a budgetary expenditure and deleted from those accounts.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label><FootnoteRef idref="F-30.2_en_1">*</FootnoteRef>6</Label><Text>This Act shall come into force on a day to be fixed by proclamation.</Text><Footnote id="F-30.2_en_1" placement="section" status="editorial" xml:space="default"><Label>*</Label><Text>[Note: Act in force June 30, 1988, <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/88-121.]</Text></Footnote></Section></Body><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 2 to 4)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><DocumentInternal><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group1-part"><TitleText>Part I</TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Loan agreement entered into between the Government of Togo and the Government of Canada and dated August 19, 1969, as modified by an agreement entered into between those parties and dated September 9, 1972.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Loan agreement entered into between the Government of Canada and the Government of Togo and dated March 7, 1977, as modified by amending agreement no. 1 entered into between those parties and dated November 6, 1980.</Text></Provision></Group><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group1-part"><TitleText>Part II</TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Loan agreement entered into between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Islamic Republic of Mauritania and dated December 10, 1975.</Text></Provision></Group><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group1-part"><TitleText>Part III</TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Loan agreement entered into between the East African Community and the Government of Canada and dated October 28, 1970, as modified by an agreement entered into between those parties and dated March 15, 1971.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Loan agreement entered into between the East African Community and the Government of Canada and dated December 18, 1972, as modified by an agreement entered into between those parties and dated August 5, 1974.</Text></Provision></Group><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group1-part"><TitleText>Part IV</TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Agreement entered into between the Government of the United Republic of Tanzania and the Government of Canada and dated March 28, 1984.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Agreement entered into between the Government of the Republic of Uganda and the Government of Canada and dated March 28, 1984.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>Agreement entered into between the Government of Kenya and the Government of Canada and dated March 28, 1984.</Text></Provision></Group></DocumentInternal></Schedule></Statute>