<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE Statute PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Statute v2.0.0//EN" "Dtd/Version_2.0.0/Statute/Statute.dtd"><Statute bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes"><Identification><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Hazardous Products Act and the Canada Labour Code, to enact the Hazardous Materials Information Review Act and to amend other Acts in relation thereto</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Hazardous Products Act and the Canada Labour Code, to enact the Hazardous Materials Information Review Act and to amend other Acts in relation thereto</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Hazardous Materials Information Review</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>06</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber official="no">H-2.71</ConsolidatedNumber><AnnualStatuteId revised-statute="yes"><AnnualStatuteNumber>24 (3rd Supp.)</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>1985</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><ReaderNote><Note status="official" xml:space="default">[<Emphasis style="italic">1987, c. 30, assented to 30th June, 1987</Emphasis>]</Note></ReaderNote></Identification><Body><Heading level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>Hazardous Products Act</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>1 and 2</Label><Text>[Amendments]</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Canada Labour Code</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>3 to 8</Label><Text>[Amendments]</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Part III</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>9 to 51</Label><Text>[See <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Materials Information Review Act</XRefExternal>]</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Related Amendments, Transitional and Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Related Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>52 and 53</Label><Text>[Amendments]</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Transitional</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>54</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding anything in this Act but subject to subsection (3), no person who, on the day on which subsection 11(1) or (2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Materials Information Review Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by this Act, comes into force, would but for this section be entitled to file a claim for exemption under that subsection in relation to a controlled product is entitled to file a claim for exemption in relation to that controlled product under that subsection unless, during the period beginning on the first day of the second month after the coming into force of this section and ending on the last day of the sixth month after the coming into force of this section, that person has, in accordance with this section, filed a notice of intent to file a claim for exemption in relation to that controlled product with the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Form and content of notice and accompanying fee</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A notice of intent referred to in subsection (1) shall be in such form and contain such information as the Minister may, by order, determine and shall be accompanied by a fee of five hundred dollars.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may, by order, on the application of any person and on payment of a fee of five hundred dollars, exempt a controlled product specified in the order from the application of subsection (1) where the Minister is satisfied that reasonable grounds exist to allow the exemption.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Fee still payable</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The payment of a fee under subsection (2) or (3) does not relieve a person of the obligation to pay any fee required to be paid on the filing of a claim for exemption under section 11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Materials Information Review Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>In this section,</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>controlled product</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>produit contrôlé</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>controlled product</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal>, as amended by this Act;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Consumer and Corporate Affairs.</Text></Definition></Subsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 54; 1992, c. 1, s. 145(F).</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Termination</MarginalNote><Label>55</Label><Text>Section 54 or any provision thereof shall cease to have effect on a day or days to be fixed by proclamation.</Text></Section><Section><Label>56</Label><Text>[Amendment]</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Review by Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review by Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>57</Label><Text>On the expiration of two years after the coming into force of section 12 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by this Act, that section shall stand referred to such committee of the House of Commons, of the Senate or of both Houses of Parliament as may be designated or established for that purpose and the committee shall, as soon as practicable thereafter, undertake a comprehensive review of the exemptions provided by that section and shall, within one year after the review is undertaken or within such further time as the House of Commons may authorize, submit a report thereon to Parliament including any recommendations pertaining to the continuation of any of those exemptions.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label><FootnoteRef idref="H-2.71_en_1">*</FootnoteRef>58</Label><Text>This Act or any provision thereof, or any provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> as amended or enacted by this Act, shall come into force on October 31, 1988 or on such earlier day or days as may be fixed by proclamation.</Text><Footnote id="H-2.71_en_1" placement="section" status="editorial" xml:space="default"><Label>*</Label><Text>[Note: Part III in force October 1, 1987, <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/87-220.]</Text></Footnote></Section></Body><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE</Label></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no"><Text>[Amendment]</Text></Provision></Schedule></Statute>