<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE Statute PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Statute v2.0.0//EN" "Dtd/Version_2.0.0/Statute/Statute.dtd"><Statute bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes"><Identification><LongTitle>An Act to prohibit the sale and importation of hazardous products that are intended for use, handling or storage in a work place</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Hazardous Products Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Hazardous Products</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>06</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber official="yes">H-3</ConsolidatedNumber></Chapter></Identification><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal>.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. H-3, s. 1.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>In this Act,</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>advertise</DefinedTermEn><Repealed>[Repealed, 2010, c. 21, s. 72]</Repealed></Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>analyst</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>analyste</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>analyst</DefinedTermEn> means an individual designated as an analyst under subsection 21(1);</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>container</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>contenant</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>container</DefinedTermEn> includes a bag, barrel, bottle, box, can, cylinder, drum or similar package or receptacle but does not include a storage tank;</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>controlled product</DefinedTermEn><Repealed>[Repealed, 2010, c. 21, s. 72]</Repealed></Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>controlled product</DefinedTermEn> or <DefinedTermEn>hazardous product</DefinedTermEn><Repealed>[Repealed, 2014, c. 20, s. 111]</Repealed></Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>document</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>document</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>document</DefinedTermEn> means anything on which information that is capable of being understood by an individual or being read by a computer or other device is recorded or marked;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>hazardous product</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>produit dangereux</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>hazardous product</DefinedTermEn> means any product, mixture, material or substance that is classified in accordance with the regulations made under subsection 15(1) in a category or subcategory of a hazard class listed in Schedule 2;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>import</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>importer</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>import</DefinedTermEn> means to import into Canada;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>inspector</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>inspecteur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>inspector</DefinedTermEn> means an individual designated as an inspector under subsection 21(1);</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>label</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>étiquette</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>label</DefinedTermEn> means a group of written, printed or graphic information elements that relate to a hazardous product, which group is designed to be affixed to, printed on or attached to the hazardous product or the container in which the hazardous product is packaged;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>manufactured article</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>article manufacturé</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>manufactured article</DefinedTermEn> means any article that is formed to a specific shape or design during manufacture, the intended use of which when in that form is dependent in whole or in part on its shape or design, and that, when being installed, if the intended use of the article requires it to be installed, and under normal conditions of use, will not release or otherwise cause an individual to be exposed to a hazardous product;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Health;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>mixture</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>mélange</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>mixture</DefinedTermEn> means a combination of, or a solution that is composed of, two or more ingredients that, when they are combined, do not react with each other, but excludes any such combination or solution that is a substance; </Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>person</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>personne</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>person</DefinedTermEn> means an individual or an organization as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>prescribed</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinitionEnOnly>Version anglaise seulement</DefinitionEnOnly></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>prescribed</DefinedTermEn>, for the purposes of Part II, means prescribed by regulations made under subsection 15(1), and, for the purposes of Part III, means prescribed by regulations made under section 27;</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>prohibited product</DefinedTermEn><Repealed>[Repealed, 2010, c. 21, s. 72]</Repealed></Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>restricted product</DefinedTermEn><Repealed>[Repealed, 2010, c. 21, s. 72]</Repealed></Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>review officer</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>réviseur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>review officer</DefinedTermEn> means an individual designated as a review officer under section 26.2;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>safety data sheet</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>fiche de données de sécurité</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>safety data sheet</DefinedTermEn> means a document that contains, under the headings that, by virtue of the regulations made under subsection 15(1), are required to appear in the document, information about a hazardous product, including information related to the hazards associated with any use, handling or storage of the hazardous product in a work place;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>sell</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>vendre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>sell</DefinedTermEn> includes</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>offer for sale or distribution, expose for sale or distribution, have in possession for sale or distribution or distribute  —  whether for consideration or not  —  to one or more recipients, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>make any transfer of possession that creates a bailment or, in Quebec, make any transfer of possession of a movable, for a specific purpose, without transferring ownership, and with the obligation to deliver the movable to a specified person or to return it, such as a transfer by means of a deposit, a lease, a pledge, a loan for use or a contract of carriage;</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>substance</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>substance</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>substance</DefinedTermEn> means any chemical element or chemical compound  —  that is in its natural state or that is obtained by a production process  — whether alone or together with</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any additive that is necessary to preserve the stability of the chemical element or chemical compound,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any solvent that is necessary to preserve the stability or composition of the chemical element or chemical compound, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any impurity that is derived from the production process;</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>supplier</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>fournisseur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>supplier</DefinedTermEn> means a person who, in the course of business, sells or imports a hazardous product;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>work place</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>lieu de travail</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>work place</DefinedTermEn> has the meaning assigned by regulations made under subsection 15(1).</Text></Definition><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. H-3, s. 2; R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 1992, c. 1, s. 145(F); 1996, c. 8, s. 25; 2010, c. 21, s. 72; 2014, c. 20, s. 111.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>[Repealed, 2010, c. 21, s. 73]</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>3</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2010, c. 21, s. 73]</Repealed></Text></Section><Section><Label>4</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2010, c. 21, s. 73]</Repealed></Text></Section><Section><Label>5</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2010, c. 21, s. 73]</Repealed></Text></Section><Section><Label>5.1</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2010, c. 21, s. 73]</Repealed></Text></Section><Section><Label>6</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2010, c. 21, s. 73]</Repealed></Text></Section><Section><Label>7</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2010, c. 21, s. 73]</Repealed></Text></Section><Section><Label>8</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2010, c. 21, s. 73]</Repealed></Text></Section><Section><Label>9</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2010, c. 21, s. 73]</Repealed></Text></Section><Section><Label>10</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2010, c. 21, s. 73]</Repealed></Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Hazardous Products</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>11</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2014, c. 20, s. 112]</Repealed></Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Restrictions on application</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>This Part does not apply in respect of the sale or importation of any</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a) to (c)</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2014, c. 20, s. 113]</Repealed></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>nuclear substance, within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Nuclear Safety and Control Act</XRefExternal>, that is radioactive;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>hazardous waste, being a hazardous product that is sold for recycling or recovery or is intended for disposal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f) and (g)</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2014, c. 20, s. 113]</Repealed></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>tobacco or a tobacco product as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tobacco Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>manufactured article; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>anything listed in Schedule 1.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. H-3, s. 12; R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 1997, c. 9, s. 105, c. 13, s. 62; 2002, c. 28, s. 86; 2010, c. 21, s. 74; 2014, c. 20, s. 113.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Prohibitions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition re sale</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Materials Information Review Act</XRefExternal>, no supplier shall sell a hazardous product that is intended for use, handling or storage in a work place in Canada unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the supplier has in their possession a safety data sheet for the hazardous product that meets the requirements set out in the regulations made under subsection 15(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>on the sale of the hazardous product to any person or government, the supplier provides to the person or government the safety data sheet referred to in paragraph (a), or causes it to be provided, if on that sale the person or government acquires possession or ownership of that hazardous product; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the hazardous product or the container in which the hazardous product is packaged has a label that meets the requirements set out in the regulations made under subsection 15(1) affixed to it, printed on it or attached to it in a manner that meets the requirements set out in the regulations made under that subsection.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>government</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>government</DefinedTermEn> means any of the following or their institutions:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the federal government;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a corporation named in Schedule III to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a provincial government or a public body established under an Act of the legislature of a province; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an aboriginal government as defined in subsection 13(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. H-3, s. 13; R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 1999, c. 31, s. 128(F); 2014, c. 20, s. 114.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition re importation</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>Subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Materials Information Review Act</XRefExternal>, no supplier shall import a hazardous product that is intended for use, handling or storage in a work place in Canada unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the supplier obtains or prepares, on or before the importation of the hazardous product, a safety data sheet for the hazardous product that meets the requirements set out in the regulations made under subsection 15(1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the hazardous product or the container in which the hazardous product is packaged has a label that meets the requirements set out in the regulations made under subsection 15(1) affixed to it, printed on it or attached to it in a manner that meets the requirements set out in the regulations made under that subsection.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. H-3, s. 14; R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 2014, c. 20, s. 114.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition re sale</MarginalNote><Label>14.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite section 13, no supplier shall sell a hazardous product that contains asbestos and is intended for use, handling or storage in a work place in Canada unless, subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Materials Information Review Act</XRefExternal>, the supplier complies with the requirements set out in paragraphs 13(1)(a) to (b) and the hazardous product meets the requirements set out in the regulations made under subsection 15(2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition re importation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite section 14, no supplier shall import a hazardous product that contains asbestos and is intended for use, handling or storage in a work place in Canada unless, subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Materials Information Review Act</XRefExternal>, the supplier complies with the requirements set out in paragraphs 14(a) and (b) and the hazardous product meets the requirements set out in the regulations made under subsection 15(2).</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 20, s. 114.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>False information  — hazardous product or container</MarginalNote><Label>14.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No supplier shall sell or import a hazardous product that is intended for use, handling or storage in a work place in Canada if the hazardous product or the container in which the hazardous product is packaged has affixed to, printed on or attached to it information about the hazardous product that is false, misleading or likely to create an erroneous impression, with respect to the information that is required to be included in a label or safety data sheet for that hazardous product in order for the supplier to comply with the requirements set out in paragraphs 13(1)(a) to (b) or 14(a) and (b), as the case may be.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Safety data sheet  —  sale</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No supplier shall sell a hazardous product that is intended for use, handling or storage in a work place in Canada if the safety data sheet for the hazardous product that is in their possession in order to comply with the requirement set out in paragraph 13(1)(a), or that they provide or cause to be provided in order to comply with the requirement set out in paragraph 13(1)(a.1), is false, misleading or likely to create an erroneous impression, with respect to the information that is required to be included in a label or safety data sheet for that hazardous product in order for the supplier to meet the requirements set out in paragraphs 13(1)(a) to (b).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Safety data sheet  — importation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No supplier shall import a hazardous product that is intended for use, handling or storage in a work place in Canada if the safety data sheet for the hazardous product that the supplier obtains or prepares in order to comply with the requirement set out in paragraph 14(a) is false, misleading or likely to create an erroneous impression, with respect to the information that is required to be included in a label or safety data sheet for that hazardous product in order for the supplier to comply with the requirements set out in paragraphs 14(a) and (b).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Course of sale</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>No supplier who sells a hazardous product that is intended for use, handling or storage in a work place in Canada shall, in the course of selling the hazardous product, communicate by any means any information about the hazardous product that is false, misleading or likely to create an erroneous impression, with respect to the information that is required to be included in a label or safety data sheet for that hazardous product in order for the supplier to comply with the requirements set out in paragraphs 13(1)(a) to (b).</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 20, s. 114.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Preparing and Maintaining Documents</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Requirements</MarginalNote><Label>14.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every supplier who sells or imports a hazardous product that is intended for use, handling or storage in a work place in Canada shall prepare and maintain</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a document containing a true copy of a label that represents the label that is affixed to, printed on or attached to the hazardous product or the container in which the hazardous product is packaged in order to meet the requirement set out in paragraph 13(1)(b) or 14(b), as the case may be, when they sell or import the hazardous product;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a document containing a true copy of a safety data sheet for the hazardous product that represents the safety data sheet that is in their possession in order to meet the requirement set out in paragraph 13(1)(a) or that they obtain or prepare in order to meet the requirement set out in paragraph 14(a), as the case may be, when they sell or import the hazardous product;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if the supplier obtained the hazardous product from another person, a document that indicates the person’s name and address, the quantity of the hazardous product obtained by the supplier and the month and year in which they obtained it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a document that indicates, for any sales of the hazardous product that result in a transfer of ownership or possession, the locations at which those sales took place, the period during which they took place, and, for each month in that period, the quantity sold during the month; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the prescribed documents.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Period for keeping documents</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The supplier shall keep the documents for six years after the end of the year to which they relate or for any other period that may be prescribed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Keeping and providing documents</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The supplier shall keep the documents at the supplier’s place of business in Canada or at any prescribed place and shall, on written request, within the time and in the manner specified in the request, provide them to the Minister or an inspector.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemption  — outside Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister may, subject to any terms and conditions that he or she may specify, exempt a supplier from the requirement to keep documents in Canada if the Minister considers it unnecessary or impractical for the supplier to keep them in Canada.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 20, s. 114.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to section 19, the Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>defining, for the purposes of Schedule 2, any word or expression used in Schedule 2 but not defined in this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>establishing, for any hazard class listed in Schedule 2, categories and subcategories of that hazard class;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>respecting the classification of products, mixtures, materials and substances in a category or subcategory of a hazard class listed in Schedule 2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>respecting safety data sheets;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c.1)</Label><Text>respecting labels;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>respecting the preparation and maintenance of documents, including by specifying the documents to be prepared and maintained, where they are to be kept and for how long;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2014, c. 20, s. 115]</Repealed></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>exempting from the application of this Part and the regulations made under this subsection or any provision of this Part or those regulations, on any terms and conditions that may be specified in those regulations,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the sale or importation of any hazardous product or class of hazardous products either generally or in the quantities or concentrations, in the circumstances, at the places, premises or facilities, for the purposes or in the containers that are specified in those regulations, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>any class of suppliers;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g) and (h)</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2014, c. 20, s. 115]</Repealed></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>defining the expression <DefinedTermEn>work place</DefinedTermEn> for the purposes of this Part;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>requiring any supplier who sells or imports a hazardous product that is intended for use, handling or storage in a work place in Canada to provide, as soon as feasible, any information that is included in the safety data sheet that is in the supplier’s possession for the hazardous product to any prescribed safety professional or health professional who requests that information for a prescribed purpose;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>requiring a prescribed safety professional or health professional  —  to whom a supplier who sells or imports a hazardous product that is intended for use, handling or storage in a work place in Canada has provided information about the hazardous product that the supplier is exempt from disclosing under any Act of Parliament  —  to keep confidential, except for the purpose for which it is provided, any of that information that the supplier specifies as being confidential, if that information was provided at the request of the safety professional or health professional for a prescribed purpose;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Materials Information Review Act</XRefExternal>, requiring any supplier who sells or imports a hazardous product that is intended for use, handling or storage in a work place in Canada to identify, as soon as feasible, on request of any person within a class of persons specified in the regulations made under this subsection, the source for any toxicological data used in the preparation of any safety data sheet that the supplier has provided or caused to be provided in order to meet the requirement set out in paragraph 13(1)(a.1) or has obtained or prepared in order to meet the requirement set out in paragraph 14(a), as the case may be;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(m)</Label><Text>prescribing any other matter or thing that by this Part is to be or may be prescribed; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(n)</Label><Text>generally for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Part.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the sale or importation of any hazardous product referred to in subsection 14.1(1) or (2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Externally produced material</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A regulation made under subsection (1) or (2) may incorporate by reference documents produced by a person or body other than the Minister, including by</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an organization established for the purpose of writing standards, such as an organization accredited by the Standards Council of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an industrial or trade organization; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a government.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reproduced or translated material</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A regulation made under subsection (1) or (2) may incorporate by reference documents that the Minister reproduces or translates from documents produced by a person or body other than the Minister</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>with any adaptations of form and reference that will facilitate their incorporation into the regulation; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in a form that sets out only the parts of them that apply for the purposes of the regulation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Jointly produced documents</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A regulation made under subsection (1) or (2) may incorporate by reference documents that the Minister produces jointly with another government for the purpose of harmonizing the regulation with other laws.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Internally produced standards</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A regulation made under subsection (1) or (2) may incorporate by reference technical or explanatory documents that the Minister produces, including</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>specifications, classifications, illustrations, graphs or other information of a technical nature; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>test methods, procedures, operational standards, safety standards or performance standards of a technical nature.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Incorporation as amended from time to time</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Documents may be incorporated by reference as amended from time to time.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Subsections (3) to (7) are for greater certainty and do not limit any authority to make regulations incorporating material by reference that exists apart from those subsections.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>government</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>government</DefinedTermEn> means any of the following or their institutions:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the federal government;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a corporation named in Schedule III to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a provincial government or a public body established under an Act of the legislature of a province;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an aboriginal government as defined in subsection 13(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a government of a foreign state or of a subdivision of a foreign state; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>an international organization of states.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. H-3, s. 15; R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 1999, c. 31, s. 129; 2014, c. 20, s. 115.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><Label>16</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2014, c. 20, s. 116]</Repealed></Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Interim Orders</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Interim orders — regulations</MarginalNote><Label>16.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may make an interim order that contains any provision that may be contained in a regulation made under this Part if the Minister believes that immediate action is required to deal with a significant risk, direct or indirect, to health or safety.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interim orders  — section 18</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may make an interim order in which any power referred to in section 18 is deemed to be exercised, if the Minister believes that immediate action is required to deal with a significant risk, direct or indirect, to health or safety.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Cessation of effect</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An interim order has effect from the time that it is made but ceases to have effect on the earliest of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>14 days after it is made, unless it is approved by the Governor in Council,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the day on which it is repealed,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in the case of an interim order made under subsection (1), the day on which a regulation made under this Part that has the same effect as the interim order comes into force and, in the case of an interim order made under subsection (2), the day on which an order made by the Governor in Council under this Part that has the same effect as the interim order comes into force, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>one year after the interim order is made or any shorter period that may be specified in the interim order.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contravention of unpublished order</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>No person shall be convicted of an offence consisting of a contravention of an interim order that, at the time of the alleged contravention, had not been published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> unless it is proved that, at the time of the alleged contravention, the person had been notified of the interim order or reasonable steps had been taken to bring the purport of the interim order to the notice of those persons likely to be affected by it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemption from <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An interim order</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is exempt from the application of sections 3, 5 and 11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>shall be published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> within 23 days after it is made.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deeming</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>For the purpose of any provision of this Part other than this section and section 19, any reference to regulations made under this Act is deemed to include interim orders, and any reference to a regulation made under a specified provision of this Act is deemed to include a reference to the portion of an interim order containing any provision that may be contained in a regulation made under the specified provision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of order</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>A copy of each interim order must be tabled in each House of Parliament within 15 days after it is made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>House not sitting</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>In order to comply with subsection (7), the interim order may be sent to the Clerk of the House if the House is not sitting.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2004, c. 15, s. 68; 2014, c. 20, s. 117.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><Label>17</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2014, c. 20, s. 118]</Repealed></Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to Schedules 1 and 2</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Amendments to Schedules 1 and 2</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Text>Subject to section 19, the Governor in Council may, by order,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>amend Schedule 1 to add, delete or amend a reference to anything; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>amend Schedule 2 to add, delete or amend a reference to a hazard class.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. H-3, s. 18; R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 2014, c. 20, s. 119.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Consultation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Text>A regulation under subsection 15(1) or an order under section 18 may be made by the Governor in Council only on the recommendation of the Minister made after consultation by the Minister with the government of each province and with any organizations representative of workers, organizations representative of employers and organizations representative of suppliers that the Minister considers appropriate.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. H-3, s. 19; R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 2014, c. 20, s. 120.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Tests, Studies and Compilation of Information</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Minister’s order</MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister has reasonable grounds to believe that a product, mixture, material or substance may be a hazardous product, the Minister may, in writing, order a person who is engaged in the business of selling or importing the product, mixture, material or substance to compile information relating to the formula, composition, chemical ingredients or hazardous properties of the product, mixture, material or substance, and any other information that the Minister considers necessary, for the purpose of determining whether the product, mixture, material or substance is or may be a danger to the health or safety of any individual who may handle it in a work place or be exposed to it in a work place.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Minister’s order</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>If the Minister has reasonable grounds to believe that a person is engaged in the business of selling or importing a product, mixture, material or substance that is a hazardous product, the Minister may, in writing, order the person to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>conduct tests or studies on the product, mixture, material or substance to obtain the information that the Minister considers necessary to verify compliance or prevent non-compliance with the provisions of this Act or of the regulations made under subsection 15(1) or (2); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>compile any information related to the formula, composition, chemical ingredients or hazardous properties of the product, mixture, material or substance that the Minister considers necessary to verify compliance or prevent non-compliance with the provisions of this Act or of the regulations made under subsection 15(1) or (2).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Providing information to Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person to whom an order under subsection (1) or (1.1) is directed shall provide to the Minister, in the time, form and manner specified in the order, the information or the results of the tests or studies that are required by the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information privileged</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (4), information received by the Minister from a person under subsection (1) or (1.1) is privileged and, notwithstanding the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> or any other Act or law, shall not be disclosed to any other person except as may be necessary for the administration and enforcement of this Act or for the purposes of section 15.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information privileged</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister shall not, when carrying out the consultations referred to in section 19, for the purposes of subsection 15(1), disclose the name of any person from whom the Minister has received information under subsection (1) or (1.1) or any of that information that is specified, in writing, by the person as being confidential.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, orders made under subsection (1) or (1.1) are not statutory instruments within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. H-3, s. 20; R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 2014, c. 20, s. 121.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Administration and Enforcement</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Inspectors and Analysts</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Inspectors and analysts</MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may designate as an inspector or analyst for the purposes of any provision of this Act or of the regulations any individual or class of individuals who, in the Minister’s opinion, is qualified to be so designated. However, if the individual is employed by a provincial government, or a public body established under an Act of the legislature of a province, the Minister may make the designation only after obtaining the approval of that government or public body.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate to be produced</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall furnish every inspector with a certificate of designation and, on entering any place in accordance with subsection 22(1), an inspector shall, on request, produce the certificate to the person in charge of that place.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Objectives, guidelines and codes of practice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may establish objectives, guidelines and codes of practice respecting the exercise of an inspector’s or analyst’s powers, and the performance of an inspector’s or analyst’s duties or functions, under this Act.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. H-3, s. 21; R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 2014, c. 20, s. 122.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Inspection and Analysis</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Powers of inspectors</MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection 22.1(1), an inspector may, for a purpose related to verifying compliance or preventing non-compliance with the provisions of this Act or of the regulations, at any reasonable time enter any place, including a conveyance, in which the inspector has reasonable grounds to believe that an activity regulated under this Act is conducted or a thing to which this Act applies is located, and may, for that purpose,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>examine or test any product, mixture, material or substance found in the place that the inspector has reasonable grounds to believe is a hazardous product and take samples of it, and examine any other thing that the inspector believes on reasonable grounds is used or is capable of being used for the manufacture, preparation, preservation, packaging, sale, importation or storage of a hazardous product;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>open and examine any receptacle or package that is found in the place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>examine a document that is found in the place, make a copy of it or take an extract from it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>use or cause to be used a computer or other device that is at the place to examine a document that is contained in or available to a computer system or reproduce it or cause it to be reproduced in the form of a printout or other intelligible output and remove the output for examination or copying;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>use or cause to be used any copying equipment that is at the place and remove the copies for examination;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>take photographs and make recordings and sketches;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>order the owner or person having possession, care or control of any product, mixture, material or substance found in the place that the inspector has reasonable grounds to believe is a hazardous product to move it or, for any time that may be necessary, not to move it or to restrict its movement;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>order the owner or person having possession, care or control of the conveyance to move it or, for any time that may be necessary, not to move it or to restrict its movement;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>order the owner or person in charge of the place to establish their identity to the inspector’s satisfaction; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>remove anything from the place for the purpose of examination, conducting tests or taking samples.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conveyance</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>For the purpose of entering a conveyance, an inspector may order the owner or person having possession, care or control of the conveyance to stop it or move it to a place where the inspector can enter it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of samples</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>A sample taken under this section may be disposed of in any manner that an inspector considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Individual accompanying inspector</MarginalNote><Label>(1.3)</Label><Text>An inspector may be accompanied by any individual that they believe is necessary to help them exercise their powers or perform their duties or functions under this section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Entering private property</MarginalNote><Label>(1.4)</Label><Text>An inspector who is exercising powers or performing duties or functions under this section and any individual accompanying them may enter private property  —  other than a dwelling-house  —  and pass through it in order to gain entry to a place referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Assistance to inspectors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The owner or person in charge of the place and every person found in it shall give the inspector all reasonable assistance and provide the inspector with any information that the inspector may require for the purpose of exercising the inspector’s powers or performing the inspector’s duties or functions under this section.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. H-3, s. 22; R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 2014, c. 20, s. 123.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Warrant or consent required to enter dwelling-house</MarginalNote><Label>22.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the place mentioned in subsection 22(1) is a dwelling-house, an inspector is not authorized to enter it without the consent of the occupant except under the authority of a warrant issued under subsection (2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authority to issue warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A justice of the peace may, on <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application, issue a warrant authorizing, subject to the conditions specified in the warrant, the individual who is named in it to enter a dwelling-house if the justice of the peace is satisfied by information on oath that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the dwelling-house is a place described in subsection 22(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>entry to the dwelling-house is necessary for the purposes referred to in subsection 22(1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>entry to the dwelling-house was refused or there are reasonable grounds to believe that it will be refused or to believe that consent to entry cannot be obtained from the occupant.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Use of force</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In executing a warrant issued under subsection (2), the inspector shall not use force unless they are accompanied by a peace officer and the use of force is authorized in the warrant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Telewarrant</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If an inspector believes that it would not be practical to appear personally to make an application for a warrant under subsection (2), the warrant may be issued by telephone or other means of telecommunication on application submitted by telephone or other means of telecommunication and section 487.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> applies for that purpose with any necessary modifications.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 20, s. 123.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Seizure</MarginalNote><Label>22.2</Label><Text>An inspector may seize and detain anything that they have reasonable grounds to believe</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>was used in the contravention of any provision of this Act or of the regulations; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is something in relation to which a provision of this Act or of the regulations was contravened.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 20, s. 123.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Certain information privileged</MarginalNote><Label>22.3</Label><Text>All information that, under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Materials Information Review Act</XRefExternal>, a supplier is exempt from disclosing under this Act and that is obtained by an inspector in the exercise of their powers or the performance of their duties or functions under this Act is privileged and, notwithstanding the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> or any other Act or law, shall not be disclosed to any other person except for the purposes of the administration and enforcement of this Act.</Text><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 20, s. 123.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Analysis and examination</MarginalNote><Label>22.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An inspector may submit to an analyst, for analysis or examination, anything seized by the inspector, or any sample of it, or any samples taken by the inspector.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate or report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An analyst who has made an analysis or examination may issue a certificate or report setting out the results of the analysis or examination.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 20, s. 123.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Obstruction</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Text>No person shall obstruct, or provide false or misleading information either orally or in writing to, an inspector while the inspector is exercising powers or performing duties or functions under the provisions of this Act or of the regulations.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. H-3, s. 23; R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 2014, c. 20, s. 123.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Dealing with Seized Things</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Storage of seized things</MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An inspector who seizes a thing under this Act may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on notice to and at the expense of its owner or the person having possession, care or control of it at the time of its seizure, store it at the place where it was seized or move it to, and store it at, another place; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>order its owner or the person having possession, care or control of it at the time of its seizure to store it at their expense at the place where it was seized or to move it to, and store it at, another place at their expense.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interference</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Except with the authorization of an inspector, no person shall remove, alter or interfere in any way with a thing seized under this Act by an inspector.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 2014, c. 20, s. 123.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Release of seized things</MarginalNote><Label>24.1</Label><Text>An inspector who seizes a thing under this Act shall release it if they are satisfied that the provisions of this Act and of the regulations that relate to it have been complied with.</Text><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 20, s. 123.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application for restoration</MarginalNote><Label>25</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a thing has been seized under this Act, its owner or the person having possession, care or control of it at the time of its seizure may, within 120 days after the date of the seizure, on prior notice having been given in accordance with subsection (2) to the Minister, apply to a provincial court judge within whose territorial jurisdiction the seizure was made for an order of restoration under subsection (3).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The notice referred to in subsection (1) shall be delivered to the Minister at Ottawa at least 30 clear days before the day on which the application to the provincial court judge is to be made, by means of registered mail, a method of courier service that provides a record of delivery and requires a signature on delivery, or any other prescribed method, and shall specify</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the provincial court judge to whom the application is to be made;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the place and time at which the application is to be heard;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the thing in respect of which the application is to be made; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the evidence on which the applicant intends to rely to establish that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the applicant was the owner or the person having possession, care or control of the thing at the time of its seizure, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the thing was not used in the contravention of any provision of this Act or of the regulations and it is not something in relation to which a provision of this Act or of the regulations was contravened.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order of restoration</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to section 26, the provincial court judge shall order that the thing seized be restored without delay to the applicant if, on the hearing of an application made under subsection (1), the judge is satisfied that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the applicant was the owner or the person having possession, care or control of the thing at the time of its seizure;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>the thing was not used in the contravention of any provision of this Act or of the regulations and it is not something in relation to which a provision of this Act or of the regulations was contravened; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the thing is not and will not be required as evidence in any proceedings in respect of an offence under section 28.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No application for restoration</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If no application has been made under subsection (1) for the restoration of a thing seized under this Act within 120 days after the date of the seizure, the Minister may dispose of it, at the expense of its owner or the person having possession, care or control of it at the time of its seizure, as the Minister thinks fit.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 2014, c. 20, s. 123.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Forfeiture  — conviction for offence</MarginalNote><Label>26</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a person has been convicted of an offence under section 28, the court may order that a thing seized under this Act by means of or in respect of which the offence was committed be forfeited to Her Majesty in right of Canada. The thing forfeited may be disposed of, as the Minister directs, at the expense of its owner, the person who was entitled to possession of it at the time of its seizure or the person who has been convicted of the offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Forfeiture  — consent of owner</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the owner of a thing seized under this Act consents in writing to its forfeiture, the thing is forfeited to Her Majesty in right of Canada and may be disposed of, at the expense of its owner, as the Minister directs.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 2014, c. 20, s. 123.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Orders for Taking Measures</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Taking measures</MarginalNote><Label>26.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may order a supplier to take any measure that the Minister considers necessary to remedy a non-compliance, or to prevent non-compliance, with the provisions of this Act or of the regulations, if the Minister believes on reasonable grounds that any provision of this Act or of the regulations has been contravened in relation to the hazardous product.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Measures</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The measures referred to in subsection (1) include measures related to the label or safety data sheet for the hazardous product or to stopping the sale or importation of the hazardous product or causing it to be stopped.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The order shall be provided in the form of a written notice that sets out the reasons for the measure and the time within which and manner in which the measure is to be carried out.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, orders made under subsection (1) are not statutory instruments within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 20, s. 123.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Review of Orders for Taking Measures</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review officer</MarginalNote><Label>26.2</Label><Text>The Minister may designate as a review officer for the purposes of reviewing orders under section 26.3 any individual or class of individuals who, in the Minister’s opinion, is qualified to be so designated.</Text><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 20, s. 123.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Request for review</MarginalNote><Label>26.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to any other provision of this section, an order made under section 26.1 shall be reviewed by a review officer other than the individual who made the order, on the written request of the person who was ordered under it to take a measure, but only on grounds that involve questions of fact alone or questions of mixed law and fact.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of and time for making request</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The written request shall state the grounds for review and set out the evidence, including evidence that was not considered by the individual who made the order, that supports those grounds and the decision that is sought. It shall be delivered to the Minister within seven days after the day on which the order is provided under subsection 26.1(3).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No authority to review</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The review is not to be done if the request does not comply with subsection (2) or is frivolous, vexatious or not made in good faith.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons for refusal</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The person who made the request shall, without delay, be notified in writing of the reasons for not doing the review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review initiated by review officer</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A review officer  —  other than the individual who made the order  —  may review an order made under section 26.1, whether or not a request is made under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order in effect</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>An order made under section 26.1 continues to apply during a review unless the review officer decides otherwise.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Completion of review</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>A review officer shall complete the review no later than 30 days after the day on which the request is delivered to the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extension of period for review</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The review officer may extend the review period by no more than 30 days if they are of the opinion that more time is required to complete the review. They may extend the review period more than once.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons for extension</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>If the review period is extended, the person who made the request shall, without delay, be notified in writing of the reasons for extending it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Decision on completion of review</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>On completion of a review, the review officer shall confirm, amend, terminate or cancel the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(11)</Label><Text>The person who made the request or, if there is no request, the person to whom the order was directed, shall, without delay, be notified in writing of the reasons for the review officer’s decision under subsection (10).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of amendment</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>An order made under section 26.1 that is amended is subject to review under this section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certain information privileged</MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>All information that, under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Materials Information Review Act</XRefExternal>, a supplier is exempt from disclosing under this Act and that is obtained by a review officer in the exercise of their powers or the performance of their duties or functions under this section is privileged and, notwithstanding the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> or any other Act or law, shall not be disclosed to any other person except as may be necessary for the purposes of the administration and enforcement of this Act.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 20, s. 123.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>27</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>respecting the performance of an inspector’s, analyst’s or review officer’s duties or functions and the circumstances in which an inspector or a review officer may exercise their powers;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>respecting the taking of samples and the seizure, detention, forfeiture or disposition of anything under this Part;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(a.2)</Label><Text>respecting the form of notices referred to in subsections 25(2) and 26.1(3) and the time within which and manner in which orders are to be provided under subsection 26.1(3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(a.3)</Label><Text>respecting the measures referred to in section 26.1;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(a.4)</Label><Text>respecting the review of orders under section 26.3;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(a.5)</Label><Text>prescribing anything that by this Part is to be prescribed; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>generally for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Part.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 2014, c. 20, s. 124.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Interim Orders</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Interim orders</MarginalNote><Label>27.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may make an interim order that contains any provision that may be contained in a regulation made under this Part if the Minister believes that immediate action is required to deal with a significant risk, direct or indirect, to health or safety.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Cessation of effect</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An interim order has effect from the time that it is made but ceases to have effect on the earliest of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>14 days after it is made, unless it is approved by the Governor in Council,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the day on which it is repealed,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the day on which a regulation made under this Part, that has the same effect as the interim order, comes into force, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>one year after the interim order is made or any shorter period that may be specified in the interim order.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contravention of unpublished order</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No person shall be convicted of an offence consisting of a contravention of an interim order that, at the time of the alleged contravention, had not been published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> unless it is proved that, at the time of the alleged contravention, the person had been notified of the interim order or reasonable steps had been taken to bring the purport of the interim order to the notice of those persons likely to be affected by it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemption from <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An interim order</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is exempt from the application of sections 3, 5 and 11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>shall be published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> within 23 days after it is made.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deeming</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For the purpose of any provision of this Part other than this section, any reference to regulations made under this Act is deemed to include interim orders, and any reference to a regulation made under a specified provision of this Act is deemed to include a reference to the portion of an interim order containing any provision that may be contained in a regulation made under the specified provision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of order</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A copy of each interim order must be tabled in each House of Parliament within 15 days after it is made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>House not sitting</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>In order to comply with subsection (6), the interim order may be sent to the Clerk of the House if the House is not sitting.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2004, c. 15, s. 69.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Offence, Punishment and Procedure</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>28</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes a provision of this Act, a provision of the regulations or an order made under this Act is guilty of an offence and is liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $5,000,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, for a first offence, to a fine of not more than $250,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months or to both and, for a subsequent offence, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than 18 months or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Defence of due diligence</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>No person shall be found guilty of an offence under subsection (1) if they establish that they exercised due diligence to prevent the commission of the offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence  —  fault</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>Every person who knowingly or recklessly contravenes a provision of this Act, a provision of the regulations or an order made under this Act is guilty of an offence and is liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine in an amount that is at the discretion of the court or to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, for a first offence, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than 18 months or to both and, for a subsequent offence, to a fine of not more than $1,000,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Parties to offence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person other than an individual commits an offence under subsection (1) or (1.2), an officer, director, or agent or mandatary, of the person who directed, authorized, assented to, acquiesced in or participated in the commission of the offence is a party to and guilty of the offence and is liable on conviction to the punishment provided for the offence, whether or not the person has been prosecuted or convicted.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation period</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Proceedings by way of summary conviction in respect of an offence under paragraph (1)(b) or (1.2)(b) may be instituted at any time within two years after the day on which the subject matter of the proceedings arises.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sentencing considerations</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A court that imposes a sentence shall take into account, in addition to any other principles that it is required to consider, the harm or risk of harm caused by the commission of the offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of offence</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>In a prosecution for an offence under subsection (1) or (1.2), it is sufficient proof of the offence to establish that it was committed by an employee, or agent or mandatary, of the accused, even if the employee, or agent or mandatary, is not identified or prosecuted for the offence, unless the accused establishes that the offence was committed without the knowledge or consent of the accused and that the accused exercised due diligence to prevent its commission.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 2014, c. 20, s. 125.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Continuing offence</MarginalNote><Label>28.1</Label><Text>If an offence under section 28 is committed or continued on more than one day, it constitutes a separate offence for each day on which it is committed or continued.</Text><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 20, s. 125.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Exception, etc., need not be mentioned</MarginalNote><Label>29</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No exception, exemption, excuse or qualification prescribed by law is required to be set out or negatived, as the case may be, in an information or indictment for an offence under section 28 of this Act or under section 463, 464 or 465 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> in respect of an offence under section 28.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Burden of proof</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In any prosecution for an offence mentioned in subsection (1), the burden of proving that an exception, exemption, excuse or qualification prescribed by law operates in favour of the accused is on the accused and the prosecutor is not required, except by way of rebuttal, to prove that the exception, exemption, excuse or qualification does not operate in favour of the accused, whether or not it is set out in the information or indictment.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Analyst’s certificate</MarginalNote><Label>30</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to this section, a certificate of an analyst stating that the analyst has analysed or examined a product, mixture, material or substance and stating the result of the analysis or examination is admissible in evidence in any prosecution for an offence mentioned in subsection 29(1) and, in the absence of any evidence to the contrary, is proof of the statements contained in the certificate without proof of the signature or official character of the person appearing to have signed the certificate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Attendance of analyst</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The party against whom a certificate of an analyst is produced pursuant to subsection (1) may, with leave of the court, require the attendance of the analyst for the purposes of cross-examination.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No certificate shall be admitted in evidence pursuant to subsection (1) unless the party intending to produce it has, before the trial, given to the party against whom it is intended to be produced reasonable notice of that intention together with a copy of the certificate.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 2014, c. 20, s. 126.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Self-incrimination</MarginalNote><Label>30.1</Label><Text>The information and results contained in the documents that a person provides under an order made under section 20 may not be used or received to incriminate the person in any proceeding against them in respect of an offence under this Act.</Text><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 20, s. 127.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Trial of offence</MarginalNote><Label>31</Label><Text>A complaint or information in respect of an offence under section 28 may be heard, tried or determined by a provincial court judge or a justice of the peace if the accused is resident within, is carrying on business within or happens to be within the territorial jurisdiction of the provincial court judge or justice of the peace, although the matter of the complaint or information did not arise in that territorial jurisdiction.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 2014, c. 20, s. 127.</HistoricalNote></Section></Body><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 1</Label><OriginatingRef>(Paragraph 12(j))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Non-Application of Part II</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><List first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Item><Label>1</Label><Text>Any pest control product as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Pest Control Products Act</XRefExternal></Text></Item><Item><Label>2</Label><Text>Any explosive as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Explosives Act</XRefExternal></Text></Item><Item><Label>3</Label><Text>Any cosmetic, device, drug or food, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Food and Drugs Act</XRefExternal></Text></Item><Item><Label>4</Label><Text>Any consumer product as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Consumer Product Safety Act</XRefExternal></Text></Item><Item><Label>5</Label><Text>Any wood or product made of wood</Text></Item></List><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. H-3, sch. I; 2010, c. 21, s. 75; 2014, c. 20, s. 128.</HistoricalNote></Schedule><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 2</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 2)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Hazard Classes</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><DocumentInternal><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group1-part"><TitleText>Physical Hazard Classes</TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><List first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Item><Label>1</Label><Text>Explosives</Text></Item><Item><Label>2</Label><Text>Flammable gases</Text></Item><Item><Label>3</Label><Text>Flammable aerosols</Text></Item><Item><Label>4</Label><Text>Oxidizing gases</Text></Item><Item><Label>5</Label><Text>Gases under pressure</Text></Item><Item><Label>6</Label><Text>Flammable liquids</Text></Item><Item><Label>7</Label><Text>Flammable solids</Text></Item><Item><Label>8</Label><Text>Self-reactive substances and mixtures</Text></Item><Item><Label>9</Label><Text>Pyrophoric liquids</Text></Item><Item><Label>10</Label><Text>Pyrophoric solids</Text></Item><Item><Label>11</Label><Text>Self-heating substances and mixtures</Text></Item><Item><Label>12</Label><Text>Substances and mixtures which, in contact with water, emit flammable gases</Text></Item><Item><Label>13</Label><Text>Oxidizing liquids</Text></Item><Item><Label>14</Label><Text>Oxidizing solids</Text></Item><Item><Label>15</Label><Text>Organic peroxides</Text></Item><Item><Label>16</Label><Text>Corrosive to metals</Text></Item><Item><Label>17</Label><Text>Combustible dusts</Text></Item><Item><Label>18</Label><Text>Simple asphyxiants</Text></Item><Item><Label>19</Label><Text>Pyrophoric gases</Text></Item><Item><Label>20</Label><Text>Physical hazards not otherwise classified</Text></Item></List></Provision></Group><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group1-part"><TitleText>Health Hazard Classes</TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><List first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Item><Label>1</Label><Text>Acute toxicity</Text></Item><Item><Label>2</Label><Text>Skin corrosion/irritation</Text></Item><Item><Label>3</Label><Text>Serious eye damage/eye irritation</Text></Item><Item><Label>4</Label><Text>Respiratory or skin sensitization</Text></Item><Item><Label>5</Label><Text>Germ cell mutagenicity</Text></Item><Item><Label>6</Label><Text>Carcinogenicity</Text></Item><Item><Label>7</Label><Text>Reproductive toxicity</Text></Item><Item><Label>8</Label><Text>Specific target organ toxicity — single exposure</Text></Item><Item><Label>9</Label><Text>Specific target organ toxicity — repeated exposure</Text></Item><Item><Label>10</Label><Text>Aspiration hazard</Text></Item><Item><Label>11</Label><Text>Biohazardous infectious materials</Text></Item><Item><Label>12</Label><Text>Health hazards not otherwise classified</Text></Item></List></Provision></Group></DocumentInternal><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 2; 2014, ch. 20, art. 128.</HistoricalNote></Schedule><Schedule id="RelatedProvs"><ScheduleFormHeading type="amending"><TitleText>RELATED PROVISIONS</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><BillPiece><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — R.S., 1985, c. 24 (3rd Supp.), s. 57</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review by Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>57</Label><Text>On the expiration of two years after the coming into force of section 12 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by this Act, that section shall stand referred to such committee of the House of Commons, of the Senate or of both Houses of Parliament as may be designated or established for that purpose and the committee shall, as soon as practicable thereafter, undertake a comprehensive review of the exemptions provided by that section and shall, within one year after the review is undertaken or within such further time as the House of Commons may authorize, submit a report thereon to Parliament including any recommendations pertaining to the continuation of any of those exemptions.</Text></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 1996, c. 8, s. 32(2)</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>32</Label><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every reference to the Minister of Consumer and Corporate Affairs in any order, regulation or other instrument made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Materials Information Review Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> shall be read as a reference to the Minister of Health unless the context otherwise requires or unless the relevant power, duty or function has been assigned to another minister.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 20, s. 129</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>129</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section and sections <XRefInternal>130</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>138</XRefInternal>.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>controlled product</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in section 2 of the former Act. (<DefinedTermFr>produit contrôlé</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>former Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> as it read immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>114</XRefInternal> comes into force. (<DefinedTermFr>ancienne loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Same meaning</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Unless a contrary intention appears, words and expressions used in sections <XRefInternal>130</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>138</XRefInternal> have the same meanings as in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 20, s. 130</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Sale of controlled product</MarginalNote><Label>130</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 13 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a supplier in respect of the sale of a controlled product if the supplier sells the controlled product on or after the day on which section <XRefInternal>114</XRefInternal> comes into force but before a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of this section and if the supplier would not, were section 13 of the former Act in force at the time, be in contravention of that section 13 in respect of that sale.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Importation of controlled product</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 14 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a supplier in respect of the importation of a controlled product if the supplier imports the controlled product on or after the day on which section <XRefInternal>114</XRefInternal> comes into force but before a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of this section and if the supplier would not, were section 14 of the former Act in force at the time, be in contravention of that section 14 in respect of that importation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Hazardous product that is not controlled product</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Sections 13 and 14 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> do not apply to a supplier in respect of the sale or importation of a hazardous product that is not a controlled product if the supplier sells or imports the hazardous product on or after the day on which section <XRefInternal>114</XRefInternal> comes into force but before a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 20, s. 131</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Resale of controlled product</MarginalNote><Label>131</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 13 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a supplier in respect of the sale of a controlled product that was sold to them if the supplier sells the controlled product on or after the day fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of section <XRefInternal>130</XRefInternal> but before a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of this section and if the supplier would not, were section 13 of the former Act in force at the time, be in contravention of that section 13 in respect of that sale.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Hazardous product that is not controlled product</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 13 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a supplier in respect of the sale of a hazardous product that was sold to them and that is not a controlled product if the supplier sells the hazardous product on or after the day fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of section <XRefInternal>130</XRefInternal> but before a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 20, s. 132</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Importation of controlled product for own use in work place</MarginalNote><Label>132</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 14 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a supplier in respect of the importation of a controlled product that the supplier intends only to use in their work place if the supplier imports the controlled product on or after the day fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of section <XRefInternal>130</XRefInternal> but before a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of this section and if the supplier would not, were section 14 of the former Act in force at the time, be in contravention of that section 14 in respect of that importation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Hazardous product that is not controlled product</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 14 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a supplier in respect of the importation of a hazardous product that the supplier intends only to use in their work place and that is not a controlled product if the supplier imports the hazardous product on or after the day fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of section <XRefInternal>130</XRefInternal> but before a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 20, s. 133</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Sale of controlled product</MarginalNote><Label>133</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 14.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a supplier in respect of the sale of a controlled product that contains asbestos and that meets the requirements set out for hazardous products in regulations made under subsection 15(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> if the supplier sells the controlled product on or after the day on which section <XRefInternal>114</XRefInternal> comes into force but before a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of this section and if the supplier would not, were section 13 of the former Act in force at the time, be in contravention of that section 13 in respect of that sale.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Importation of controlled product</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 14.1(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a supplier in respect of the importation of a controlled product that contains asbestos and that meets the requirements set out for hazardous products in regulations made under subsection 15(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> if the supplier imports the controlled product on or after the day on which section <XRefInternal>114</XRefInternal> comes into force but before a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of this section and if the supplier would not, were section 14 of the former Act in force at the time, be in contravention of that section 14 in respect of that importation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 20, s. 134</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Resale of controlled product</MarginalNote><Label>134</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 14.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a supplier in respect of the sale of a controlled product that contains asbestos, that was sold to them and that meets the requirements set out for hazardous products in regulations made under subsection 15(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> if the supplier sells the controlled product on or after the day fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of section <XRefInternal>133</XRefInternal> but before a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of this section and if the supplier would not, were section 13 of the former Act in force at the time, be in contravention of that section 13 in respect of that sale.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Importation of controlled product for own use in work place</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 14.1(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a supplier in respect of the importation of a controlled product that contains asbestos, that the supplier intends only to use in their work place and that meets the requirements set out for hazardous products in regulations made under subsection 15(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> if the supplier imports the controlled product on or after the day fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of section <XRefInternal>133</XRefInternal> but before a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of this section and if the supplier would not, were section 14 of the former Act in force at the time, be in contravention of that section 14 in respect of that importation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 20, s. 135</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Sale or importation of controlled product — false information</MarginalNote><Label>135</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 14.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a supplier in respect of the sale or importation of a controlled product if the supplier sells or imports the controlled product on or after the day on which section <XRefInternal>114</XRefInternal> comes into force but before a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of this section and if the supplier would not, were section 13 or 14, as the case may be, of the former Act in force at the time, be in contravention of that section 13 or 14 in respect of that sale or importation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Hazardous product that is not controlled product</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 14.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a supplier in respect of the sale or importation of a hazardous product that is not a controlled product if the supplier sells or imports the hazardous product on or after the day on which section <XRefInternal>114</XRefInternal> comes into force but before a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 20, s. 136</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Resale of controlled product — false information</MarginalNote><Label>136</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 14.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a supplier in respect of the sale of a controlled product that was sold to them if the supplier sells the controlled product on or after the day fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of section <XRefInternal>135</XRefInternal> but before a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of this section and if the supplier would not, were section 13 of the former Act in force at the time, be in contravention of that section 13 in respect of that sale.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Hazardous product that is not controlled product</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 14.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a supplier in respect of the sale of a hazardous product that was sold to them and that is not a controlled product if the supplier sells the hazardous product on or after the day fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of section <XRefInternal>135</XRefInternal> but before a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 20, s. 137</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Importation of controlled product for own use in work place — false information</MarginalNote><Label>137</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 14.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a supplier in respect of the importation of a controlled product that the supplier intends only to use in their work place if the supplier imports the controlled product on or after the day fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of section <XRefInternal>135</XRefInternal> but before a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of this section and if the supplier would not, were section 14 of the former Act in force at the time, be in contravention of that section 14 in respect of that importation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Hazardous product that is not controlled product</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 14.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a supplier in respect of the importation of a hazardous product that the supplier intends only to use in their work place and that is not a controlled product if the supplier imports the hazardous product on or after the day fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of section <XRefInternal>135</XRefInternal> but before a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council for the purposes of this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2014, c. 20, s. 138</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Reference to regulations</MarginalNote><Label>138</Label><Text>For the purposes of sections <XRefInternal>130</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>137</XRefInternal>, any references in the former Act to the Ingredient Disclosure List, to regulations, or to anything prescribed by regulation, are considered to be references to that List or those regulations as they read immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>114</XRefInternal> comes into force.</Text></Section></BillPiece></Schedule></Statute>