<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE Statute PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Statute v2.0.0//EN" "Dtd/Version_2.0.0/Statute/Statute.dtd"><Statute bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes"><Identification><LongTitle>An Act respecting the identification of criminals</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Identification of Criminals Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Identification of Criminals</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>06</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber official="yes">I-1</ConsolidatedNumber></Chapter></Identification><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Identification of Criminals Act</XRefExternal>.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. I-1, s. 1.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Her Majesty</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Binding on Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>1.1</Label><Text>This Act is binding on Her Majesty in right of Canada or a province.</Text><HistoricalNote>1992, c. 47, s. 73.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Identification of Criminals</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Fingerprints and photographs</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following persons may be fingerprinted or photographed or subjected to such other measurements, processes and operations having the object of identifying persons as are approved by order of the Governor in Council:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any person who is in lawful custody charged with or convicted of</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>an indictable offence, other than an offence that is designated as a contravention under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Contraventions Act</XRefExternal> in respect of which the Attorney General, within the meaning of that Act, has made an election under section 50 of that Act, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>an offence under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any person who has been apprehended under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Extradition Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any person alleged to have committed an indictable offence, other than an offence that is designated as a contravention under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Contraventions Act</XRefExternal> in respect of which the Attorney General, within the meaning of that Act, has made an election under section 50 of that Act, who is required pursuant to subsection 501(3) or 509(5) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to appear for the purposes of this Act by an appearance notice, promise to appear, recognizance or summons; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>any person who is in lawful custody pursuant to section 83.3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Use of force</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Such force may be used as is necessary to the effectual carrying out and application of the measurements, processes and operations described under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The results of the measurements, processes and operations to which a person has been subjected pursuant to subsection (1) may be published for the purpose of affording information to officers and others engaged in the execution or administration of the law.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. I-1, s. 2; 1992, c. 47, s. 74; 1996, c. 7, s. 39; 1999, c. 18, s. 88; 2001, c. 41, ss. 23.1, 35.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No liability for acting under Act</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>No liability, civil or criminal, for anything lawfully done under this Act shall be incurred by any person</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>having custody of a person described in subsection 2(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>acting in the aid or under the direction of a person having such custody; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>concerned in the publication of results under subsection 2(3).</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. I-1, s. 3; 1992, c. 47, s. 75.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Destruction of Fingerprints and Photographs</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Destruction of fingerprints and photographs</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>Where a person charged with an offence that is designated as a contravention under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Contraventions Act</XRefExternal> is fingerprinted or photographed and the Attorney General, within the meaning of that Act, makes an election under section 50 of that Act, the fingerprints or photographs shall be destroyed.</Text><HistoricalNote>1992, c. 47, s. 76; 1996, c. 7, s. 40.</HistoricalNote></Section></Body></Statute>