<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE Statute PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Statute v2.0.0//EN" "Dtd/Version_2.0.0/Statute/Statute.dtd"><Statute bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes"><Identification><LongTitle>An Act to authorize rearrangements and transfers of duties in the federal public administration</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Public Service Rearrangement and Transfer of Duties Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Public Service Rearrangement and Transfer of Duties</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>06</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber official="yes">P-34</ConsolidatedNumber></Chapter></Identification><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Rearrangement and Transfer of Duties Act</XRefExternal>.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. P-34, s. 1.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Transfer of Functions and Amalgamation of Departments</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Transferring functions and combining departments</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>transfer any powers, duties or functions or the control or supervision of any portion of the federal public administration from one minister to another, or from one department in, or portion of, the federal public administration to another; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>amalgamate and combine any two or more departments under one minister and under one deputy minister.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. P-34, s. 2; 2003, c. 22, s. 207.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Substituting of Minister or Department</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Duties and powers of minister and department</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>Where under this Act, or under any other lawful authority, any power, duty or function, or the control or supervision of any portion of the federal public administration, is transferred from one minister to another, or from one department in, or portion of, the federal public administration to another, the minister, department, or portion to whom or which the power, duty, function, control or supervision is transferred, and the appropriate officers of that department or portion, shall, in relation thereto, be substituted for and have and carry out the respective powers and duties that formerly belonged to or were to be carried out by the minister, department or portion and the respective officers of the department or portion from whom or which the power, duty, function, control or supervision is so transferred.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. P-34, s. 3; 2003, c. 22, s. 208.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Death of Minister</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Death of minister</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>Where a minister to whom any powers, duties or functions have been transferred by name pursuant to this Act dies or otherwise ceases to be a minister, those powers, duties or functions may be transferred to another minister.</Text><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 14(2nd Supp.), s. 31.</HistoricalNote></Section></Body></Statute>