<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Statute PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Statute v2.0.0//EN" "Dtd/Version_2.0.0/Statute/Statute.dtd"><Statute bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes"><Identification><BillNumber>C-51</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>62-63-64</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2013-2014-2015</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to encourage and facilitate information sharing between Government of Canada institutions in order to protect Canada against activities that undermine the security of Canada</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Security of Canada Information Sharing Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Security of Canada Information Sharing</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>06</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2015</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber official="no">S-6.9</ConsolidatedNumber><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>20, s. 2</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2015</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><ReaderNote><Note status="editorial">[Enacted by section 2 of chapter 20 of the Statutes of Canada, 2015, in force August 1, 2015, <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/2015-64.]</Note></ReaderNote></Identification><Introduction><Preamble salutation="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the people of Canada are entitled to live free from threats to their lives and their security;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas activities that undermine the security of Canada are often carried out in a clandestine, deceptive or hostile manner, are increasingly global, complex and sophisticated, and often emerge and evolve rapidly;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas there is no more fundamental role for a government than protecting its country and its people;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas Canada is not to be used as a conduit for the carrying out of activities that threaten the security of another state;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas protecting Canada and its people against activities that undermine the security of Canada often transcends the mandate and capability of any one Government of Canada institution;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas Parliament recognizes that information needs to be shared — and disparate information needs to be collated — in order to enable the Government to protect Canada and its people against activities that undermine the security of Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas information in respect of activities that undermine the security of Canada is to be shared in a manner that is consistent with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</XRefExternal> and the protection of privacy;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>And whereas Government of Canada institutions are accountable for the effective and responsible sharing of information;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Canada Information Sharing Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>activity that undermines the security of Canada</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>activité portant atteinte à la sécurité du Canada</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>activity that undermines the security of Canada</DefinedTermEn> means any activity, including any of the following activities, if it undermines the sovereignty, security or territorial integrity of Canada or the lives or the security of the people of Canada:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>interference with the capability of the Government of Canada in relation to intelligence, defence, border operations, public safety, the administration of justice, diplomatic or consular relations, or the economic or financial stability of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>changing or unduly influencing a government in Canada by force or unlawful means;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>espionage, sabotage or covert foreign-influenced activities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>terrorism;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>proliferation of nuclear, chemical, radiological or biological weapons;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>interference with critical infrastructure;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>interference with the global information infrastructure, as defined in section 273.61 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>an activity that causes serious harm to a person or their property because of that person’s association with Canada; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>an activity that takes place in Canada and undermines the security of another state.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedDefinition><Text>For greater certainty, it does not include advocacy, protest, dissent and artistic expression.</Text></ContinuedDefinition></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Government of Canada institution</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>institution fédérale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Government of Canada institution</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a government institution — as defined in section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> — other than one that is listed in Schedule 1; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an institution that is listed in Schedule 2.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>people of Canada</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>population du Canada</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>people of Canada</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the people in Canada; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any citizen, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> — or any permanent resident, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> — who is outside Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Purpose and Principles</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to encourage and facilitate the sharing of information among Government of Canada institutions in order to protect Canada against activities that undermine the security of Canada.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Guiding principles</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>Information sharing under this Act is to be guided by the following principles:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>effective and responsible information sharing protects Canada and Canadians;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>respect for caveats on and originator control over shared information is consistent with effective and responsible information sharing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>entry into information-sharing arrangements is appropriate when Government of Canada institutions share information regularly;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the provision of feedback as to how shared information is used and as to whether it is useful in protecting against activities that undermine the security of Canada facilitates effective and responsible information sharing; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>only those within an institution who exercise its jurisdiction or carry out its responsibilities in respect of activities that undermine the security of Canada ought to receive information that is disclosed under this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Disclosure of Information</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Disclosure of information</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to any provision of any other Act of Parliament, or of any regulation made under such an Act, that prohibits or restricts the disclosure of information, a Government of Canada institution may, on its own initiative or on request, disclose information to the head of a recipient Government of Canada institution whose title is listed in Schedule 3, or their delegate, if the information is relevant to the recipient institution’s jurisdiction or responsibilities under an Act of Parliament or another lawful authority in respect of activities that undermine the security of Canada, including in respect of their detection, identification, analysis, prevention, investigation or disruption.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Further disclosure under subsection (1)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Information received under subsection (1) may be further disclosed under that subsection.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Further disclosure — other than under this Act</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the use and further disclosure, other than under this Act, of information that is disclosed under subsection 5(1) are neither authorized nor prohibited by this Act, but must be done in accordance with the law, including any legal requirements, restrictions and prohibitions.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No presumption</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>The act of disclosing information under this Act does not create a presumption</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that the disclosing institution is conducting a joint investigation or decision-making process with the recipient institution and therefore has the same obligations, if any, as the recipient institution to disclose or produce information for the purposes of a proceeding; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that there has been a waiver of any privilege, or of any requirement to obtain consent, for the purposes of any other disclosure of that information either in a proceeding or to an institution that is not a Government of Canada institution.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Non-derogation</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act limits or affects any authority to disclose information under another Act of Parliament or a provincial Act, at common law or under the royal prerogative.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Protection from Civil Proceedings</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>No civil proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>No civil proceedings lie against any person for their disclosure in good faith of information under this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Powers of Governor in Council</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness, make regulations for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Act, including regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>respecting the manner of disclosure under section 5;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>requiring records to be kept and retained in respect of that disclosure; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>respecting the manner in which those records are kept and retained.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amendments to Schedules 1 and 2</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make an order adding the name of an institution to Schedule 1 or 2 or deleting one from either of those Schedules.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amendments to Schedule 3</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make an order adding the name of a Government of Canada institution and the title of its head to Schedule 3, deleting the name of an institution and the title of its head from that Schedule or amending the name of an institution or the title of a head that is listed in that Schedule. An addition is authorized only if the institution has jurisdiction or responsibilities under an Act of Parliament or another lawful authority in respect of activities that undermine the security of Canada, including in respect of their detection, identification, analysis, prevention, investigation or disruption.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body><Schedule><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 1</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 2 and subsection 10(2))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Excluded Institutions</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading></Schedule><Schedule><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 2</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 2 and subsection 10(2))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Additional Institutions</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Office of the Communications Security Establishment Commissioner</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bureau du commissaire du Centre de la sécurité des télécommunications</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></Schedule><Schedule><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 3</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsections 5(1) and 10(3))</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><TableGroup pointsize="8"><Caption position="over">RECIPIENT GOVERNMENT OF CANADA INSTITUTIONS AND THEIR HEADS</Caption><table frame="topbot"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="5.37*" /><colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="3.93*" /><thead><row topdouble="yes" topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Column 1</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Column 2</entry></row><row rowsep="1" topmarginspacing="2" valign="bottom"><entry align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="1">Recipient Institution</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">Head</entry></row></thead><tbody><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canada Border Services Agency</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Agence des services frontaliers du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry>President of the Canada Border Services Agency</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canada Revenue Agency</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Agence du revenu du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry>Commissioner of Revenue</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Armed Forces</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Forces armées canadiennes</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry>Chief of the Defence Staff</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Food Inspection Agency</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Agence canadienne d’inspection des aliments</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry>President of the Canadian Food Inspection Agency</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Nuclear Safety Commission</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission canadienne de sûreté nucléaire</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry>President of the Canadian Nuclear Safety Commission</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Security Intelligence Service</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Service canadien du renseignement de sécurité</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry>Director of the Canadian Security Intelligence Service</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Communications Security Establishment</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Centre de la sécurité des télécommunications</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Chief of the Communications Security Establishment</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Department of Citizenship and Immigration</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Ministère de la Citoyenneté et de l’Immigration</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry>Minister of Citizenship and Immigration</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Department of Finance</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Ministère des Finances</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Minister of Finance</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Ministère des Affaires étrangères, du Commerce et du Développement</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry>Minister of Foreign Affairs</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Department of Health</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Ministère de la Santé</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry>Minister of Health</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Department of National Defence</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Ministère de la Défense nationale</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry>Minister of National Defence</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Department of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Ministère de la Sécurité publique et de la Protection civile</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Department of Transport</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Ministère des Transports</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry>Minister of Transport</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Financial Transactions and Reports Analysis Centre of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Centre d’analyse des opérations et déclarations financières du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry>Director of the Financial Transactions and Reports Analysis Centre of Canada</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Public Health Agency of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Agence de la santé publique du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry>President of the Public Health Agency of Canada</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Royal Canadian Mounted Police</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Gendarmerie royale du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 20, ss. 2 "Sch. 3", 9.</HistoricalNote></Schedule></Statute>