<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE Statute PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Statute v2.0.0//EN" "Dtd/Version_2.0.0/Statute/Statute.dtd"><Statute bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes"><Identification><LongTitle>An Act to replace the Yukon Act in order to modernize it and to implement certain provisions of the Yukon Northern Affairs Program Devolution Transfer Agreement, and to repeal and make amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Yukon Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Yukon</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2002</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>27</DD></Date></Stages><Stages stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>06</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber official="no">Y-2.01</ConsolidatedNumber><AnnualStatuteId revised-statute="no"><AnnualStatuteNumber>7</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2002</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter></Identification><Introduction><Preamble salutation="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Yukon is a territory that has a system of responsible government that is similar in principle to that of Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Text>And Whereas the enactment of legislation is required to implement certain provisions of the Yukon Northern Affairs Program Devolution Transfer Agreement, negotiated by representatives of certain first nations, the Government of Canada and the Yukon Government;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="no" format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yukon Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The definitions in this section apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>adjoining area</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>zone adjacente</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>adjoining area</DefinedTermEn> means the area outside Yukon and landward of the northern limit described in Schedule 2.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>federal agent corporation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>société mandataire fédérale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>federal agent corporation</DefinedTermEn> has the meaning assigned to the expression “agent corporation” by subsection 83(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>federal conservation area</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>aire de conservation fédérale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>federal conservation area</DefinedTermEn> means an area that is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a national park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>public real property under the administration of the Minister of the Environment that is subject to measures imposed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Wildlife Act</XRefExternal> for the conservation of wildlife; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a protection area for migratory birds prescribed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Migratory Birds Convention Act, 1994</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>former Act</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ancienne loi</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>former Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yukon Act</XRefExternal>, chapter Y-2 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>gas</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>gaz</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>gas</DefinedTermEn> means natural gas and all substances produced in association with natural gas, but does not include oil or coal-bed methane.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>national park</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>parc national</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>national park</DefinedTermEn> means a park and includes a park reserve as those terms are defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>oil</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>pétrole</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>oil</DefinedTermEn> means crude petroleum, regardless of gravity, produced at a well-head in liquid form and any other hydrocarbons, except gas and coal-bed methane. It includes hydrocarbons that may be extracted or recovered from surface or subsurface deposits of oil sand, bitumen, bituminous sand or oil shale or from other types of deposits, but does not include coal.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>public real property</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>biens réels domaniaux</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>public real property</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>land in Yukon that belongs to Her Majesty in right of Canada, including mines and minerals, and buildings, structures, improvements and other fixtures on, above or below the surface of the land; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any estate, right, title or interest, including an easement, a servitude and a lease, held by Her Majesty in right of Canada in or to land in Yukon.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>waters</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>eaux</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>waters</DefinedTermEn> means any inland water, whether in a liquid or frozen state, on or below the surface of land.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Yukon</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Yukon</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Yukon</DefinedTermEn> means the territory consisting of the area described in Schedule 1.</Text></Definition></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Aboriginal rights</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>For greater certainty, nothing in this Act shall be construed so as to abrogate or derogate from the protection provided for existing aboriginal or treaty rights of the aboriginal peoples of Canada by the recognition and affirmation of those rights in section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Government</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Executive Power</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A Commissioner of Yukon shall be appointed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The order in council appointing the Commissioner shall be published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2002, c. 7, s. 68]</Repealed></Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2002, c. 7, ss. 4, 68.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Administrator</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may appoint an Administrator to act as Commissioner during the Commissioner’s absence or illness or other inability or when that office is vacant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Absence or inability</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The senior judge, within the meaning of subsection 22(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Judges Act</XRefExternal>, of the Supreme Court of Yukon may act as Administrator during the Administrator’s absence or illness or other inability or when that office is vacant.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Oaths</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>Before assuming office, the Commissioner and the Administrator shall take and subscribe the oath of office and the oath of allegiance prescribed by the Governor in Council.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Salaries</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>The salary of the Commissioner and of the Administrator shall be fixed by the Governor in Council and paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund of Canada.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Executive Council</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>The Executive Council of Yukon established under the former Act is hereby continued. Its members shall be appointed by the Commissioner.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Seat of government</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>The seat of the Yukon Government is at Whitehorse but the Legislature may designate another place in Yukon as the seat of government.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Legislative Power</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Legislative Assembly</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Legislative Assembly of Yukon</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>The Council established by the former Act is hereby continued as the Legislative Assembly of Yukon. Each member of the Legislative Assembly is elected to represent an electoral district in Yukon.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Duration of Legislative Assembly</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No Legislative Assembly shall continue for longer than five years after the date of the return of the writs for a general election, but the Commissioner may dissolve it before then.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Writs</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Writs for the election of members of the Legislative Assembly shall be issued on the instructions of the Commissioner.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Oaths of office</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>Before assuming office, each member of the Legislative Assembly shall take and subscribe before the Commissioner the oath of office prescribed by the Legislature of Yukon and the oath of allegiance set out in the Fifth Schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Yearly session</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>The Legislative Assembly shall sit at least once every 12 months.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Speaker</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Legislative Assembly shall elect one member to be Speaker, who shall preside over the Legislative Assembly when it is sitting.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Vote</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Speaker may only vote in the Legislative Assembly in the case of a tie.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Quorum</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Text>A majority of the members of the Legislative Assembly, including the Speaker, constitutes a quorum.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Rules of procedure</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Text>The Legislative Assembly may make rules for its operations and procedures, except in relation to the classes of subjects with respect to which the Legislature may make laws under paragraph 18(1)(b).</Text></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Legislature</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Legislature of Yukon</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Text>The institution referred to in the former Act as the Commissioner in Council and which consisted of the Commissioner and the Council of the Yukon Territory is hereby continued as the Legislature of Yukon, consisting of the Commissioner and the Legislative Assembly.</Text></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Legislative Powers</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Legislative powers</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Legislature may make laws in relation to the following classes of subjects in respect of Yukon:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the election of members of the Legislative Assembly, including the name and number of electoral districts and the qualifications of electors and of candidates for election;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the disqualification of persons from sitting or voting as members of the Legislative Assembly and the privileges, indemnity and expenses of those members;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Executive Council;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the establishment and tenure of public offices in Yukon and the appointment, conditions of employment and payment of office-holders;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>municipal and local institutions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>direct taxation and licensing in order to raise revenue for territorial, municipal or local purposes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the levying of a tax on furs or any portions of fur-bearing animals to be shipped or taken from Yukon to any place outside Yukon;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>the incorporation of companies with territorial objects, other than railway, steamship, air transport, canal, telegraph or telephone companies, but including street railway companies;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the solemnization of marriage;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>property and civil rights;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>the administration of justice, including the constitution, maintenance and organization of territorial courts, both of civil and of criminal jurisdiction, and including procedure in civil matters in those courts;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>the establishment, maintenance and management of prisons, jails or lock-ups;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(m)</Label><Text>the conservation of wildlife and its habitat, other than in a federal conservation area;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(n)</Label><Text>waters, other than waters in a federal conservation area, including the deposit of waste in those waters, the definition of what constitutes waste and the disposition of any right in respect of those waters under subsection 48(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(o)</Label><Text>education, but any law respecting education must provide that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a majority of the ratepayers of any part of Yukon may establish any school in that part that they think fit and make the necessary assessment and collection of rates for it, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the minority of the ratepayers in that part of Yukon, whether Protestant or Roman Catholic, may establish separate schools in that part and, if they do so, are liable only to assessments of the rates that they impose on themselves in respect of those schools;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(p)</Label><Text>immigration;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(q)</Label><Text>public real property — including the timber and wood on that property — under the administration and control of the Commissioner, including the disposition of that property under subsection 45(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(r)</Label><Text>intoxicants, including the definition of what constitutes an intoxicant;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(s)</Label><Text>hospitals and charities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(t)</Label><Text>agriculture;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(u)</Label><Text>the entering into of intergovernmental agreements by the Commissioner or any other official of the Yukon Government;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>the expenditure of money for territorial purposes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(w)</Label><Text>the adoption and use of an official seal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(x)</Label><Text>generally, all matters of a merely local or private nature;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(y)</Label><Text>the imposition of fines, penalties, imprisonment or other punishments in respect of the contravention of the provisions of a law of the Legislature; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z)</Label><Text>any other matter that may be designated by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Oil and gas in adjoining area</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Legislature may make laws in relation to the classes of subjects described in subsection (1) in respect of oil and gas in the adjoining area.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Importation of intoxicants</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Legislature may make laws relating to the importation of intoxicants into Yukon from any other place in Canada or elsewhere and defining what constitutes an intoxicant for the purposes of those laws.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Laws relating to natural resources</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Legislature may make laws in relation to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the exploration for non-renewable natural resources in Yukon and oil and gas in the adjoining area;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the development, conservation and management of non-renewable natural resources in Yukon, oil and gas in the adjoining area and forestry resources in Yukon, including laws in relation to the rate of primary production from those resources;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>oil and gas pipelines located entirely within Yukon;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the development, conservation and management of sites and facilities in Yukon for the generation and production of electrical energy;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the export, from Yukon to another part of Canada, of the primary production from non-renewable natural resources and forestry resources in Yukon, and of electrical energy generated or produced from facilities in Yukon; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the export, from the adjoining area to another part of Canada, of the primary production from oil and gas in that area.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Export of natural resources</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Laws made under paragraph (1)(e) or (f) may not authorize or provide for discrimination in prices or in supplies exported.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Taxation of natural resources</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Legislature may make laws in relation to the raising of money by any mode of taxation in respect of resources referred to in paragraph (1)(b) and primary production from those resources and in respect of sites and facilities referred to in paragraph (1)(d) and the production of electrical energy from them. The Legislature may make such laws whether or not the production is exported, in whole or in part, from Yukon or, in the case of oil and gas from the adjoining area, from that area.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No differentiation based on place of export</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A law made under subsection (3) may not authorize or provide for taxation that differentiates between production that is not exported and that which is exported to another part of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>primary production</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>primary production</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>production from a non-renewable natural resource if</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the product is in a form in which the resource exists on its recovery or severance from its natural state, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the product is a product that results from processing or refining the resource, and is not a manufactured product or a product that results from refining crude oil, upgraded heavy crude oil, gases or liquids derived from coal, or a synthetic equivalent of crude oil; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>production from a forestry resource if the product consists of sawlogs, poles, lumber, wood chips, sawdust or any other primary wood product, or wood pulp, and is not a product manufactured from wood.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Existing powers or rights</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Nothing in subsections (1) to (5) derogates from any powers or rights that the Legislature has under any other provision of this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Restrictions on powers</MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Nothing in subsections 18(1) and (2) and section 19 shall be construed as giving the Legislature greater powers than are given to legislatures of the provinces under sections 92, 92A and 95 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Water-power</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite subsections 18(1) and (2) and section 19, the Legislature may not make laws in respect of the right to the use and flow of waters for the production or generation of water-power to which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Dominion Water Power Act</XRefExternal> applies.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Agreement implementation Acts</MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Text>Despite subsection 20(1), the Legislature may, in exercising its powers under sections 18 and 19 for the purpose of implementing aboriginal land claim agreements or aboriginal self-government agreements, make laws that are in relation to the matters coming within class 24 of section 91 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Laws re conservation of wildlife</MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite subsection 20(1), any law of the Legislature in relation to the conservation of wildlife, unless the contrary intention appears in it, applies to and in respect of Indians and Inuit.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Hunting for food</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Nothing in paragraph 18(1)(m) or subsection (1) shall be construed as authorizing the Legislature to make laws restricting or prohibiting Indians and Inuit from hunting for food on unoccupied public real property, other than a species that is declared by order of the Governor in Council to be in danger of becoming extinct. This subsection does not apply to laws that implement the Agreement given effect by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Western Arctic (Inuvialuit) Claims Settlement Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Cessation of application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>After a final agreement referred to in section 4 or 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yukon First Nations Land Claims Settlement Act</XRefExternal> is given effect by or under that Act, subsection (2) does not apply in respect of persons eligible to be enrolled under the agreement or the traditional territory identified in it.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Borrowing and lending</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Legislature may make laws</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for the borrowing of money by the Commissioner on behalf of Yukon for territorial, municipal or local purposes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for the lending of money by the Commissioner to any person in Yukon; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>for the investing by the Commissioner of surplus money standing to the credit of the Yukon Consolidated Revenue Fund.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The aggregate of all borrowings must not exceed the maximum amount set under subsection (4).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Charge on Yukon C.R.F.</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The repayment of money borrowed under a law made under paragraph (1)(a), and the payment of interest on that money, is a charge on and payable out of the Yukon Consolidated Revenue Fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Maximum amount — borrowings</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister of Finance, set the maximum amount of the aggregate of all borrowings.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister of Finance, make regulations respecting borrowings for the purposes of subsections (2) and (4), including regulations respecting</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>what constitutes, or is deemed to constitute, borrowing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the entities, or classes of entities, whose borrowings must be taken into account; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the manner in which the value of a borrowing is determined.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote>2002, c. 7, s. 23; 2012, c. 19, s. 216.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Withholding of assent</MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, in writing, direct the Commissioner to withhold his or her assent to a bill that has been introduced in the Legislative Assembly.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consent of Governor in Council</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A bill in respect of which a direction has been given may not become law without the Governor in Council’s assent, which assent may not be given later than one year after the day on which the bill is adopted by the Legislative Assembly.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Transmittal of laws</MarginalNote><Label>25</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A copy of every law made by the Legislature shall be transmitted by the Clerk of the Legislative Assembly to the Governor in Council within 30 days after it is made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disallowance</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may disallow any law made by the Legislature or any provision of any such law at any time within one year after it is made.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Conflicting laws</MarginalNote><Label>26</Label><Text>In the event of a conflict between a law of the Legislature and a federal enactment, the federal enactment prevails to the extent of the conflict.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Official languages</MarginalNote><Label>27</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The ordinance entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Languages Act</XRefExternal> made on May 18, 1988 under the former Act and any successor to it may not be repealed, amended or otherwise rendered inoperable by the Legislature without the concurrence of Parliament by way of an amendment to this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Additional rights and services</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Nothing in subsection (1) shall be construed as preventing the Commissioner or any other public officer or the Legislature or any other institution of the Yukon Government — whether by amending the ordinance referred to in that subsection, without the concurrence of Parliament, or by any other means — from granting rights in respect of, or providing services in, English and French or any languages of the aboriginal peoples of Canada in addition to the rights and services provided for in that ordinance.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Yukon Consolidated Revenue Fund</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment of fund</MarginalNote><Label>28</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>All public moneys and revenue over which the Legislature has the power of appropriation shall form a fund to be known as the Yukon Consolidated Revenue Fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Establishment of bank accounts</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The member of the Executive Council designated for that purpose by a law of the Legislature shall establish, in the name of the Yukon Government, accounts with banks, or authorized foreign banks within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank Act</XRefExternal> that are not subject to the restrictions and requirements referred to in subsection 524(2) of that Act, in respect of their business in Canada, that the member designates for the deposit of public moneys and revenue.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Recommendation of Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>29</Label><Text>It is not lawful for the Legislative Assembly to adopt or pass any vote, resolution, address or bill for the appropriation of any part of the public revenue, or of any tax, for any purpose that has not been first recommended to the Legislative Assembly by message of the Commissioner, in the session in which the vote, resolution, address or bill is proposed.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Appropriation of moneys granted by Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>30</Label><Text>When a sum of money is granted to Her Majesty in right of Canada by Parliament to defray expenses for a specified public service in Yukon, the power of appropriation by the Legislature over that sum is subject to the specified purpose for which it is granted.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Yukon Public Accounts</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Fiscal year</MarginalNote><Label>31</Label><Text>The Yukon Government’s fiscal year is the period beginning on April 1 in one year and ending on March 31 in the next year.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Submission of Yukon Public Accounts to Legislative Assembly</MarginalNote><Label>32</Label><Text>The Commissioner, with the consent of the Executive Council, shall, on or before such day of the fiscal year as the Legislative Assembly may fix, lay before the Legislative Assembly a report called the Yukon Public Accounts for the preceding fiscal year and the Legislative Assembly shall consider the report.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Form and contents</MarginalNote><Label>33</Label><Text>The Yukon Public Accounts shall be prepared in any form that the Commissioner, with the consent of the Executive Council, directs. They shall be prepared in accordance with accounting principles recommended for the public sector by the Canadian Institute of Chartered Accountants or its successor and shall include</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>consolidated financial statements for the Yukon Government that present</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the financial position as at the end of the fiscal year,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the accumulated surplus or deficit as at the end of the fiscal year,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the results of its operations for the fiscal year, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the changes in the financial position for the fiscal year;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the opinion of the Auditor General of Canada referred to in subsection 34(1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any other information or statements that are required in support of the consolidated financial statements by or under any law of the Legislature.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Annual audit</MarginalNote><Label>34</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Auditor General of Canada shall audit the accounts, including those related to the Yukon Consolidated Revenue Fund, and financial transactions of the Yukon Government in each fiscal year in accordance with auditing standards recommended by the Canadian Institute of Chartered Accountants or its successor and shall express his or her opinion as to whether</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the consolidated financial statements present fairly, in all material respects and in accordance with accounting principles recommended for the public sector by that Institute or its successor, the financial position of the Yukon Government as at the end of the fiscal year and the results of its operations in, and changes in its financial position for, the fiscal year; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the transactions of the Yukon Government that have come to the notice of the Auditor General in the course of the audit are within the powers of the Yukon Government under this or any other Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Auditor General shall report to the Legislative Assembly any matter falling within the scope of the audit that, in his or her opinion, should be reported to the Assembly.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Supplementary report</MarginalNote><Label>35</Label><Text>The Auditor General of Canada may, at any time, inquire into and submit a supplementary report to the Legislative Assembly about any matter relating to the activities of the Yukon Government, including whether</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>accounts have not been faithfully and properly maintained or public money has not been fully accounted for or paid, where so required by law, into the Yukon Consolidated Revenue Fund;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>essential records have not been maintained or the rules and procedures applied have been insufficient to safeguard and control public property, to secure an effective check on the assessment, collection and proper allocation of the revenue and to ensure that expenditures have been made only as authorized;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>money has been expended for purposes other than those for which it was appropriated by the Legislature or has been expended without due regard to economy or efficiency; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>satisfactory procedures have not been established to measure and report the effectiveness of programs, where such procedures could appropriately and reasonably be implemented.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Inquiry and report</MarginalNote><Label>36</Label><Text>At the request of the Commissioner, made with the consent of the Executive Council, the Auditor General of Canada may, if in his or her opinion it does not interfere with the Auditor General’s primary responsibilities, inquire into and report to the Legislative Assembly on</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any matter relating to the financial affairs of the Yukon Government or to public property in Yukon; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any person or organization that has received or is seeking financial aid from the Yukon Government.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Powers of Auditor General</MarginalNote><Label>37</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of carrying out the Auditor General of Canada’s functions under this Act, the Auditor General has all the powers that he or she has under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Auditor General Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Access to information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Except as provided by any law made by the Legislature that expressly refers to this subsection, the Auditor General is entitled to free access at all convenient times to information that relates to the fulfilment of his or her responsibilities and is entitled to require and receive from the public service of Yukon any information, reports and explanations that he or she considers necessary for that purpose.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Administration of Justice</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Judicature</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment of judges</MarginalNote><Label>38</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall appoint the judges of any superior, district or county courts that are now or may be constituted in Yukon.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Tenure of office of judges</MarginalNote><Label>39</Label><Text>The judges of the superior, district and county courts in Yukon shall hold office during good behaviour but are removable by the Governor General on address of the Senate and House of Commons and shall cease to hold office on attaining the age of 75 years.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Supreme Court of Yukon</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Judges of the Supreme Court of Yukon</MarginalNote><Label>40</Label><Text>A judge, other than a deputy judge, of the Supreme Court of the Northwest Territories or of the Nunavut Court of Justice is, by reason of holding that office, a judge of the Supreme Court of Yukon.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Deputy judges</MarginalNote><Label>41</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may appoint any person who is or has been a judge of a superior, district or county court of a province or a barrister or advocate of at least 10 years standing at the bar of a province to be a deputy judge of the Supreme Court of Yukon and fix his or her remuneration and allowances.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of appointment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A deputy judge may be appointed for any particular case or cases or for any specified period.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tenure of office</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A deputy judge holds office during good behaviour but is removable by the Governor General on address of the Senate and House of Commons.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A deputy judge shall be sworn to the faithful performance of his or her duties in the same manner as a judge of the Supreme Court of Yukon and, during his or her appointment, temporarily has and may exercise and perform all the powers, duties and functions of a judge of the Court.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction to try civil cases</MarginalNote><Label>42</Label><Text>The Supreme Court of Yukon has and may exercise and perform, in the Northwest Territories or Nunavut, all the powers, duties and functions of the Court with respect to a civil case, other than a civil case where the Court sits with a jury.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction to try criminal cases</MarginalNote><Label>43</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A judge of the Supreme Court of Yukon has and may exercise and perform, anywhere in Canada, all the powers, duties and functions of the Court with respect to any criminal offence committed or charged to have been committed in Yukon.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of laws</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>All laws applicable to criminal proceedings in Yukon apply in like manner to proceedings held under this section at any other place in Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Enforcement of decisions</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Any judgment, conviction, sentence or order pronounced or made in any proceedings held under this section outside Yukon may be enforced or executed at the place at which it is pronounced or made or elsewhere, either in or outside Yukon, as a judge of the Supreme Court of Yukon may direct, and the proper officers of Yukon have and may exercise all powers and authority necessary for the enforcement or execution of it at the place where it is directed to be enforced or executed, notwithstanding that the place is not in Yukon.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Court of Appeal of Yukon</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Sittings</MarginalNote><Label>44</Label><Text>The Court of Appeal of Yukon may sit in Yukon and, unless the laws of the Legislature provide otherwise, in any other place in Canada.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Real Property, Water, Oil and Gas</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Administration and Control</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>45</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to this Act and section 37 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northern Pipeline Act</XRefExternal>, the Commissioner has the administration and control of public real property and of oil and gas in the adjoining area and may, with the consent of the Executive Council, use, sell or otherwise dispose of that property, or any products of that property, that oil or gas, or any interest in that oil or gas, and retain the proceeds of the disposition.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall, on the date of the coming into force of subsection (1), list public real property that is excluded from the administration and control of the Commissioner.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Public real property acquired on behalf of a federal minister</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the entire or any lesser interest in land that is not public real property is acquired on behalf of a federal minister or federal agent corporation, the interest is not under the administration and control of the Commissioner.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Relinquishment</MarginalNote><Label>46</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may, with the consent of the Executive Council and with the approval of the Governor in Council, relinquish the administration and control of public real property or any interest in oil and gas in the adjoining area, either in perpetuity or for any lesser term.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Administration of relinquished interest</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The instrument indicating the Governor in Council’s approval must identify the federal minister or federal agent corporation that will have the administration of the relinquished public real property or interest.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Transfer to Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>47</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on acceptance by the Commissioner given with the consent of the Executive Council, transfer to the Commissioner, either in perpetuity or for any lesser term, the administration and control of public real property or any interest in oil and gas in the adjoining area.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right to waters vested in Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>48</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The rights in respect of all waters in Yukon belong to Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to this Act, the Commissioner has the administration and control of all rights in respect of waters in Yukon — other than waters in a federal conservation area — and, with the consent of the Executive Council, may exercise those rights or sell or otherwise dispose of them and may retain the proceeds of the disposition.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) and (2) are subject to any rights granted by or under an Act of Parliament in respect of waters.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Dominion Water Power Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection (2) does not apply to the right to the use and flow of waters for the production or generation of water-power to which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Dominion Water Power Act</XRefExternal> applies.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Restrictions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Taking of administration by Governor in Council</MarginalNote><Label>49</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister, may take from the Commissioner the administration and control of public real property and transfer the administration of the property to a federal minister or a federal agent corporation if the Governor in Council considers it necessary to do so for</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the national interest, including</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>national defence or security,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the establishment, or changes to the boundaries, of a national park, historic site or other area protected under an Act of Parliament, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the creation of the infrastructure required for initiatives in respect of transportation or energy;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the welfare of Indians and Inuit; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the settlement of an aboriginal land claim or the implementation of an aboriginal land claim agreement.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Taking of administration — adjoining area</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister, may take from the Commissioner the administration and control of any interest in oil and gas in the adjoining area for the purpose of the settlement of an aboriginal land claim or the implementation of an aboriginal land claim agreement and transfer the administration of that interest to a federal minister or a federal agent corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister, before recommending the taking of the administration and control, other than for a purpose related to national defence or security, shall consult the member of the Executive Council responsible for the public real property, or in the case of the adjoining area, the oil and gas.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition order — public real property in Yukon</MarginalNote><Label>50</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister, may by order prohibit the issuance under this Act of interests in, or the authorization under this Act of the conduct of activities on, public real property specified in the order if the Governor in Council considers that the prohibition is required</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>before the administration and control of the property is taken under paragraph 49(1)(a) or (b); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for the settlement of an aboriginal land claim or the implementation of an aboriginal land claim agreement.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition order — lands in adjoining area</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister, may by order prohibit the issuance under this Act of interests in, or the authorization under this Act of the conduct of activities on, lands in the adjoining area specified in the order, if the Governor in Council considers that the existence of the interests or the conduct of the activities would be incompatible with or would interfere with</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any use to which the Government of Canada intends the lands to be put, including, in particular, their use as a national park or an airport or their use for purposes of national defence or navigation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the exercise, in relation to those lands, of any powers of the Government of Canada, including, in particular, powers respecting national security or the protection of the environment; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the settlement of an aboriginal land claim or the implementation of an aboriginal land claim agreement.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition order — waters in Yukon</MarginalNote><Label>51</Label><Text>The Governor in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister, may by order prohibit any use of waters in Yukon specified in the order, or the deposit of waste directly or indirectly into those waters, if the Governor in Council considers</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that the use, or the deposit of waste, would be incompatible with or would interfere with a particular undertaking that is in the national interest; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that the prohibition is required for the settlement of an aboriginal land claim or the implementation of an aboriginal land claim agreement.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Procedure</MarginalNote><Label>52</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall, before an order under section 50 is made, notify the member of the Executive Council who is responsible for the public real property or, in the case of the adjoining area, the oil or gas that is the subject of the order and shall, before an order under section 51 is made, notify the member of the Executive Council who is responsible for water resources.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>After notification is given and at least 60 days before an order is made, the Minister shall publish in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> and in a newspaper that, in the opinion of the Minister, has a large circulation in Yukon notice of the proposed order. The order may not be made more than 120 days after the notice is published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interim prohibition</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The prohibition takes effect before an order is made under section 50 or 51 on publication of the notice of the proposed order in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> and continues for a period of 120 days unless, during that period, the Minister publishes in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> notice of the Minister’s intention not to recommend the proposed order. The Minister shall also publish during that period the notice of the Minister’s intention in a newspaper that, in the opinion of the Minister, has a large circulation in Yukon.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consideration of representations</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Before the Minister recommends that an order be made, the Minister shall consider any representations received within 60 days after the date of publication of the notice of the proposed order in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>If proposed order varied</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>No further notice need be given under subsections (1) and (2) if the scope of application of the order is reduced to cover a smaller area or fewer activities than set out in the notice of the proposed order.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Duration of prohibition orders</MarginalNote><Label>53</Label><Text>A prohibition order made under section 50 or 51 may not be made for a period that exceeds five years.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Exercise of Federal Powers</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Adjoining area</MarginalNote><Label>54</Label><Text>The Government of Canada, including its agencies, shall exercise any powers in respect of the management of lands in the adjoining area in a manner consistent with the powers of the Yukon Government, including its agencies, in respect of oil and gas in that area to the extent that the objectives of the Government of Canada in so exercising its powers are not compromised.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Northern pipeline</MarginalNote><Label>55</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite the laws of the Legislature, the minister responsible for the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northern Pipeline Act</XRefExternal> may grant, with or without conditions, an application made to a person or entity required by a law of the Legislature to hold a public hearing on the matter if the application is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for rights or renewal of rights in respect of waters for the purpose of constructing the pipeline referred to in that Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for permission to expropriate lands or any interest in lands for the purposes of that pipeline if the application is made by a person who holds or has applied for the water rights described in paragraph (a).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of subsection (1)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) applies only if the public hearing does not begin within six months after the application is made or is not completed within 60 days after the hearing begins or a decision is not given within 45 days after the completion of the hearing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation required</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The minister may only grant the application after consultation with the person or entity required to hold the public hearing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of exercise of power</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A decision of the minister to grant an application under subsection (1) is deemed to have been made under the laws of the Legislature.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Legislative Amendment</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Consultation re bills</MarginalNote><Label>56</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Before a bill that amends or repeals this Act is introduced in the House of Commons by a federal minister, the Minister shall consult with the Executive Council with respect to the proposed amendment or repeal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Assembly may recommend amendments</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Legislative Assembly may make any recommendations to the Minister that it considers appropriate with respect to the amendment or repeal of this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>57</Label><Text>The Commissioner, within the meaning of the former Act, who is in office immediately before the coming into force of section 4 shall continue in office according to the terms of his or her appointment.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Duration of Council</MarginalNote><Label>58</Label><Text>Despite section 11, the members of the Council, within the meaning of the former Act, that are in office immediately before the coming into force of section 10 shall continue in office as members of the Legislative Assembly for the remainder of the period provided under subsection 9(3) of the former Act, but the Commissioner may dissolve the Legislative Assembly before then.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Existing rights and interests</MarginalNote><Label>59</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The laws of the Legislature apply with respect to a right or interest granted under an access order, permit, licence or other authorization, lease or agreement for lease or sale that exists immediately before the coming into force of any provision of this Act that repeals or renders inapplicable the provision of an Act of Parliament under which the right or interest arises.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation — additional conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A law of the Legislature may only provide, in respect of a right or interest described in subsection (1), for additional conditions in respect of the exercise of the right or interest if those conditions are applicable to all similar rights or interests.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation — cancellation, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A law of the Legislature may only provide, in respect of a right or interest described in subsection (1), for the cancellation, suspension or limitation of the right or interest if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the circumstances for the cancellation, suspension or limitation of the right or interest are identical to those that would have applied before the coming into force of a provision described in subsection (1); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the cancellation, suspension or limitation of the right or interest is for a failure to comply with a condition in respect of the exercise of the right or interest and the law applies to all similar rights or interests.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>However, paragraph (b) does not apply to claims as defined in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yukon Placer Mining Act</XRefExternal>, chapter Y-3 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985, or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yukon Quartz Mining Act</XRefExternal>, chapter Y-4 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation — expropriation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A law of the Legislature may only provide, in respect of a right or interest described in subsection (1), for the expropriation of the right or interest if the holder of that right or interest is compensated under that law.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — claims</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection (2), paragraph (3)(a) and subsection (4) apply to claims described in subsection (3) that are renewed in conformity with the laws of the Legislature.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — rights and interests under the former Act</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) to (4) do not apply to rights or interests arising under the former Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Reference to Government of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>60</Label><Text>Any reference to the Government of Canada, or any of its agents, in an access order, permit, licence or other authorization, lease or agreement for lease or sale referred to in subsection 59(1) shall be read as a reference to the Yukon Government.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Pending applications</MarginalNote><Label>61</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every proceeding with respect to a right or interest granted under an access order, permit, licence or other authorization, lease or agreement for lease or sale that is commenced before the coming into force of any provision of this Act that repeals or renders inapplicable the provision of an Act of Parliament under which the right or interest arises shall be taken up and continued under and in conformity with the laws of the Legislature without any further formality.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply to civil or criminal proceedings before a court.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Validity of laws of Legislature</MarginalNote><Label>62</Label><Text>A law of the Legislature that specifically provides that it applies to matters governed by an Act of Parliament that is repealed by any of sections 281 to 284 or made inapplicable by any of sections 238 to 247 is considered for all purposes to have been validly made if it is made before the coming into force of that section and would have been validly made, if made after that coming into force. However, it has no force and effect before that coming into force.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>Agreement</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>63</Label><Text>In sections 64 to 67, <DefinedTermEn>Agreement</DefinedTermEn> means the Yukon Northern Affairs Program Devolution Transfer Agreement made on October 29, 2001.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Indemnification by Yukon</MarginalNote><Label>64</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Yukon Government shall indemnify the Government of Canada, or any of its employees or agents, against all costs, charges or expenses, including an amount paid to settle an action or satisfy a judgement, that are reasonably incurred by the Government of Canada, or any of its employees or agents, in respect of any claim, action or other proceeding brought against the Government of Canada, or any of its employees or agents, arising out of any act or omission of the Yukon Government, or any of its employees or agents, in respect of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>public real property not under the administration and control of the Commissioner immediately before the coming into force of this section or water rights, if the act or omission occurs while the Commissioner has administration and control of the property or rights;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a right or interest granted under an access order, permit, licence or other authorization, lease or agreement for lease or sale that exists immediately before the date of coming into force of any provision of this Act that repeals or renders inapplicable the provision of the Act of Parliament under which the right or interest arises, if the act or omission occurs after that date;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>security that is assigned to the Yukon Government under the Agreement;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>records provided under the Agreement to the Yukon Government, unless the act or omission is made pursuant to the Agreement; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>remediation work required by the Agreement.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Indemnification respecting obligations to employees of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Yukon Government shall indemnify the Government of Canada, or any of its employees or agents, against all costs, charges or expenses, including an amount paid to settle an action or satisfy a judgement, that are reasonably incurred by the Government of Canada, or any of its employees or agents, in respect of any claim, action or other proceeding brought against the Government of Canada, or any of its employees or agents, arising out of a failure by the Yukon Government, or any of its employees or agents, to meet the obligations of the Yukon Government under the Agreement in respect of employees of the Government of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Indemnification of first nations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Yukon Government shall indemnify a first nation, or any of its employees or agents, against all costs, charges or expenses, including an amount paid to settle an action or satisfy a judgement, that are reasonably incurred by that first nation, or any of its employees or agents, in respect of any claim, action or other proceeding brought against the first nation, or any of its employees or agents, arising out of any act or omission of the Yukon Government, or any of its employees or agents, in respect of remediation work done on the first nation’s land as required by the Agreement.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Indemnification by Canada</MarginalNote><Label>65</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Government of Canada shall indemnify the Yukon Government, or any of its employees or agents, against all costs, charges or expenses, including an amount paid to settle an action or satisfy a judgement, that are reasonably incurred by the Yukon Government, or any of its employees or agents, in respect of any claim, action or other proceeding brought against the Yukon Government, or any of its employees or agents, arising out of any act or omission of the Government of Canada, or any of its employees or agents, in respect of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>public real property not under the administration and control of the Commissioner immediately before the coming into force of this section, if the act or omission occurred while the Commissioner did not have the administration and control of the property;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>water rights in Yukon, if the act or omission occurred before the Commissioner had administration and control of the water rights;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a right or interest granted under an access order, permit, licence or other authorization, lease or agreement for lease or sale that exists immediately before the date of coming into force of any provision of this Act that repeals or renders inapplicable the provision of the Act of Parliament under which the right or interest arises, if the act or omission occurs before that date;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>security that is required to be assigned to the Yukon Government under the Agreement;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>records that are required to be provided to the Yukon Government under the Agreement; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>remediation work required by the Agreement.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Indemnification by Canada for exercise of power</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Government of Canada shall indemnify the Yukon Government, or any of its employees or agents, against all costs, charges or expenses, including an amount paid to settle an action or satisfy a judgement, that are reasonably incurred by the Yukon Government, or any of its employees or agents, in respect of any claim, action or other proceeding brought against the Yukon Government, or any of its employees or agents, arising out of the exercise of a power under sections 49 to 51 or 55.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Indemnification of first nations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Government of Canada shall indemnify a first nation, or any of its employees or agents, against all costs, charges or expenses, including an amount paid to settle an action or satisfy a judgement, that are reasonably incurred by that first nation, or any of its employees or agents, in respect of any claim, action or other proceeding brought against the first nation, or any of its employees or agents, arising out of any act or omission of the Government of Canada, or any of its employees or agents, in respect of remediation work done on the first nation’s land as required by the Agreement.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Limitation on indemnification</MarginalNote><Label>66</Label><Text>The Government of Canada, the Yukon Government or a first nation is not entitled to be indemnified under section 64 or 65 if it has settled the claim, action or proceeding without the written consent of the government that is required to indemnify it under that section.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Information privileged</MarginalNote><Label>67</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The communication pursuant to the Agreement by the Government of Canada to the Yukon Government of information, however recorded, that is subject to solicitor-client privilege does not constitute a waiver of the privilege.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure with consent</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No employee or agent of the Yukon Government shall, except with the written permission of the Minister, knowingly communicate, disclose or make available any information referred to in subsection (1), or permit it to be communicated, disclosed or made available, to a person who is not an employee or agent of the Yukon Government.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Amendments to this Act</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>68 to 76</Label><Text>[Amendments]</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Amendments to Other Acts</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>77 to 271</Label><Text>[Amendments]</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>272 to 278</Label><Text>[Amendments]</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Repeals</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>279 to 284</Label><Text>[Repeals]</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>By order</MarginalNote><Label><FootnoteRef idref="Y-2.01_en_1">*</FootnoteRef>285</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act, other than sections 70 to 75 and section 77, subsection 117(2) and sections 167, 168, 210, 211, 221, 227, 233, 272 to 278 and 283, come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Amendments to this Act</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sections 70 to 75 come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Repeal of Act</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 77, subsection 117(2) and sections 167, 168, 210, 211, 221, 227, 233 and 283 come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text><Footnote id="Y-2.01_en_1" placement="section" status="editorial" xml:space="default"><Label>*</Label><Text>[Note: Sections 272 to 278 in force on assent March 27, 2002; sections 1 to 69, 76 and 78 to 116, subsection 117(1) and sections 118 to 166, 169 to 209, 212 to 220, 222 to 226, 228 to 232, 234 to 271, 279 to 282 and 284 in force April 1, 2003, <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/2003-48.]</Text></Footnote></Subsection></Section></Body><Schedule spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 1</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 2)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Description of Yukon</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Text>Yukon shall be bounded as follows: On the south, by the Province of British Columbia and the State of Alaska; on the west, by the said State of Alaska; on the north, by that part of the Arctic Ocean called Beaufort Sea; and on the east, by a line beginning at the intersection of the north boundary of British Columbia with a line passing through a boundary pipe post set in concrete, trench and mound, numbered 600, planted by the British Columbia-Yukon-Northwest Territories Boundary Commission approximately 1 chain westerly of the left bank of the Liard River, said line having a bearing of 309 degrees with reference to the meridian through said post; thence northwesterly along said line to a point on the line of watershed separating the streams flowing into the Liard River below the La Biche River or into the Mackenzie River from those flowing into the La Biche River, into the Liard River above the La Biche River, or into the Yukon River; thence northwesterly along said line of watershed to the line of watershed of the basin of Peel River; thence northerly along the line of watershed between the Peel and Mackenzie Rivers to the sixty-seventh degree of north latitude; thence westerly along the parallel of the sixty-seventh degree of north latitude to the line of watershed between the Peel and Yukon Rivers; thence northerly along the said line of watershed to the trail across the portage in McDougall Pass between Rat and Bell Rivers; thence due north to the northern limit of the Yukon territory; the said territory to include the islands within twenty statute miles from the shores of the Beaufort Sea as far as the aforesaid due north line from McDougall Pass.</Text></Provision></Schedule><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 2</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 2)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Northern Limit of Adjoining Area</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Text>All topographic features referred to below are according to the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Gazetteer of Canada (Yukon Territory)</XRefExternal>, Fifth Edition, Ottawa, 1988, and Canadian Hydrographic Service Charts 7661 (Demarcation Bay to Phillips Bay, 21st edition) and 7662 (Mackenzie Bay, 33rd edition), produced at a scale of 1:150,000 by the Department of Fisheries and Oceans at Ottawa.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Text>A line following the ordinary low water mark of the northern coast of the mainland of the Yukon territory, except</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>at any coastal indentation such as a bay, lagoon, arm, cove, basin or other inlet: a straight line across the entrance of the indentation at the ordinary low water mark, provided</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the line measures 4 kilometres or less, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the area of the indentation, including any islands or parts of islands lying within the indentation, is greater than that of a semicircle whose diameter is the straight line;</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>at Phillips Bay: a straight line from the most easterly point on the ordinary low water mark on the northwesterly extremity of the entrance of the said Bay near Stokes Point to the most northwesterly point on the ordinary low water mark on the northeasterly extremity of the entrance of the said Bay near Kay Point; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>at Shoalwater Bay: a straight line from the most northeasterly point on the ordinary low water mark on the westerly extremity of the entrance of the said Bay to the most westerly point on the ordinary low water mark on the easterly extremity of the entrance of the said Bay.</Text></Provision></Provision></Schedule><Schedule id="NifProvs"><ScheduleFormHeading type="amending"><TitleText>AMENDMENTS NOT IN FORCE</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><BillPiece><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2002, c. 7, s. 69</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>69</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 22(1) of this Act is renumbered as section 22 and subsections 22(2) and (3) are repealed on the first day on which the final agreements of all first nations, within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yukon First Nations Land Claims Settlement Act</XRefExternal>, chapter 34 of the Statutes of Canada, 1994, are in effect.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall publish a notice of that day in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2002, c. 7, s. 70</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>70</Label><Text>Paragraph 33(b) of this Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the opinion of the Auditor General of Yukon referred to in subsection 34(1); and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2002, c. 7, s. 71</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>71</Label><Text>This Act is amended by adding the following after section 33:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Auditor General of Yukon</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment of Auditor General</MarginalNote><Label>33.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner, with the consent of the Executive Council, shall appoint a qualified auditor as the Auditor General of Yukon.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Terms of appointment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Auditor General of Yukon shall hold office during good behaviour for a term of 10 years, but may be removed by the Commissioner on address of the Legislative Assembly.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appointment of Auditor General of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Auditor General of Canada may act as Auditor General of Yukon if the Auditor General of Canada is of the opinion that it will not interfere with his or her primary responsibilities. Sections 33.2, 37.2 and 37.4 do not apply if the Auditor General of Canada acts as Auditor General of Yukon.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Pension benefits</MarginalNote><Label>33.2</Label><Text>The provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal>, other than those relating to tenure of office, apply to the Auditor General of Yukon.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Duties</MarginalNote><Label>33.3</Label><Text>The Auditor General of Yukon shall make such examinations and inquiries as the Auditor General considers necessary to enable him or her to report as required by this Act.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2002, c. 7, s. 72</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>72</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 34(1) of this Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Annual audit</MarginalNote><Label>34</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Auditor General of Yukon shall audit the accounts, including those related to the Yukon Consolidated Revenue Fund, and financial transactions of the Yukon Government in each fiscal year in accordance with auditing standards recommended by the Canadian Institute of Chartered Accountants or its successor and shall express his or her opinion as to whether</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2002, c. 7, s. 73</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>73</Label><Text>The portion of section 35 of this Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Supplementary report</MarginalNote><Label>35</Label><Text>The Auditor General of Yukon may, at any time, inquire into and submit a supplementary report to the Legislative Assembly about any matter relating to the activities of the Yukon Government, including whether</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2002, c. 7, s. 74</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>74</Label><Text>The portion of section 36 of this Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Inquiry and report</MarginalNote><Label>36</Label><Text>At the request of the Commissioner, made with the consent of the Executive Council, the Auditor General of Yukon may, if in his or her opinion it does not interfere with the Auditor General’s primary responsibilities, inquire into and report to the Legislative Assembly on</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2002, c. 7, s. 75</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>75</Label><Text>Section 37 of this Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Access to information</MarginalNote><Label>37</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Except as provided by any law made by the Legislature that expressly refers to this subsection, the Auditor General of Yukon is entitled to free access at all convenient times to information that relates to the fulfilment of his or her responsibilities and is entitled to require and receive from members of the public service of Yukon any information, reports and explanations that he or she considers necessary for that purpose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Stationing of officers in departments</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In order to carry out his or her duties more effectively, the Auditor General may station any person employed in his or her office in any portion of the public service of Yukon, and the Yukon Government shall provide the necessary office accommodation for that person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Oath of secrecy</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Auditor General shall require every person employed in his or her office who is to examine, pursuant to this Act, the accounts of a portion of the public service of Yukon or of a corporation that is expressly declared under any law of the Legislature to be an agent of the Yukon Government to comply with any security requirements applicable to, and to take any oath of secrecy required to be taken by, persons employed in that public service or that corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers of Auditor General</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Auditor General may, for the purpose of auditing the accounts of Yukon, in the same manner and to the same extent as a court of record, summon and enforce the attendance of witnesses and compel them to give oral and written evidence on oath and to produce such documents and things as the Auditor General considers necessary for a full review.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Auditor General may request information</MarginalNote><Label>37.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Auditor General of Yukon may request a corporation that is expressly declared under any law of the Legislature to be an agent of the Yukon Government to obtain and furnish such information and explanations from its present or former directors, officers, employees, agents and auditors or those of any of its subsidiaries as are, in the Auditor General’s opinion, necessary to fulfil his or her responsibilities.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Direction of the Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If, in the opinion of the Auditor General, a corporation fails to provide any or sufficient information or explanations in response to a request made under subsection (1), the Auditor General may so advise the Commissioner. The Commissioner may then, with the consent of the Executive Council, direct the officers of the corporation to give the Auditor General such information and explanations and access to any records, documents, books, accounts and vouchers of the corporation or any of its subsidiaries as is, in the opinion of the Auditor General, necessary to fulfil his or her responsibilities.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reliance on audit reports of corporations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In order to fulfil his or her responsibilities, the Auditor General may rely on the report of a duly appointed auditor of a corporation referred to in subsection (1) or of any subsidiary of that corporation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment of officers, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>37.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Auditor General of Yukon shall appoint, in accordance with the laws of the Legislature governing employment in the public service of Yukon, such officers and employees as are necessary to enable him or her to perform the Auditor General’s duties.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Suspension or dismissal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Auditor General may, in accordance with the laws referred to in subsection (1), suspend or dismiss from the performance of his or her duty any person employed in the Auditor General’s office.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contract for professional services</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Auditor General may, within the total dollar limitations established for his or her office in appropriation laws, contract for professional services.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Delegation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Auditor General may delegate any of his or her powers under this section to any person or organization that under a law of the Legislature is responsible for the management of the public service of Yukon.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>37.3</Label><Text>The Auditor General of Yukon may designate a member of his or her staff to sign on the Auditor General’s behalf any opinion that he or she is required to give and any report other than a report to the Legislative Assembly, and any member so signing an opinion or report shall indicate beneath his or her signature his or her position in the office of the Auditor General and the fact that he or she is signing on behalf of the Auditor General.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Special report</MarginalNote><Label>37.4</Label><Text>The Auditor General of Yukon may make a special report to the Legislative Assembly if he or she is of the opinion that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the amounts provided for his or her office in the estimates are inadequate to enable the Auditor General to fulfil his or her responsibilities; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the laws of the Legislature governing employment in the public service of Yukon may undermine the independence of the Office of the Auditor General or otherwise interfere with the performance of his or her duties.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
                    — 2002, c. 7, s. 76</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>76</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 55 of this Act is repealed on the day on which the National Energy Board gives leave to open the last section or part of the pipeline referred to in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northern Pipeline Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall publish a notice of that day in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></BillPiece></Schedule></Statute>