<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE Statute PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Statute v2.0.0//EN" "Dtd/Version_2.0.0/Statute/Statute.dtd"><Statute bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes"><Identification><LongTitle>An Act to establish standards for the manufacture of the national flag of Canada</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">National Flag of Canada Manufacturing Standards Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>National Flag of Canada Manufacturing Standards</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>06</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber official="yes">N-9</ConsolidatedNumber></Chapter></Identification><Body><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Flag of Canada Manufacturing Standards Act</XRefExternal>.</Text><HistoricalNote>1984, c. 28, s. 1.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Standards with respect to use</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On or before June 28, 1985, the Canadian General Standards Board shall establish standards for manufacture of the national flag of Canada corresponding to the intended use of the flag under varying conditions, including indoor use, outdoor use, one-event-only use and such other uses as the Board may determine that the national flag of Canada may reasonably be subjected to.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review of standards</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Canadian General Standards Board shall, at least once every three years, review the standards and corresponding uses referred to in subsection (1) for the purpose of ensuring their adequacy relative to technological advances in the production of materials and dyes used in the manufacture of flags.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>1984, c. 28, s. 2.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Purchase or use of national flag</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No Crown corporation, department, board, agency or office of the Government of Canada shall, after June 28, 1986, purchase or use a national flag of Canada for government purposes unless it has been manufactured in compliance with the applicable standards for manufacture and use thereof established by the Canadian General Standards Board pursuant to section 2.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply in respect of flags purchased for a use for which standards are not established by the Canadian General Standards Board.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote>1984, c. 28, s. 3.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Flags to be identified</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>All flags, whether manufactured in Canada or imported into Canada, that are manufactured in compliance with the standards for manufacture referred to in section 2 shall bear a mark identifying that flag as having met the standards for manufacture established by the Canadian General Standards Board.</Text><HistoricalNote>1984, c. 28, s. 4.</HistoricalNote></Section></Body></Statute>