<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE Statute PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Statute v2.0.0//EN" "Dtd/Version_2.0.0/Statute/Statute.dtd"><Statute bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes"><Identification><LongTitle>An Act respecting benefits for persons who served in the Women’s Royal Naval Services and the South African Military Nursing Service</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Women’s Royal Naval Services and the South African Military Nursing Service (Benefits) Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Women’s Royal Naval Services and the South African Military Nursing Service (Benefits)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>06</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber official="no">W-11.4</ConsolidatedNumber><AnnualStatuteId revised-statute="yes"><AnnualStatuteNumber>297</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>1952</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter></Identification><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Women’s Royal Naval Services and the South African Military Nursing Service (Benefits) Act</XRefExternal>.</Text><HistoricalNote>1946, c. 34, s. 1.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition "Member" W.R.N.S.</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>In this Act, "member" in relation to the Women’s Royal Naval Services means a person who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>enrolled in the Women’s Royal Naval Service,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>enrolled in Queen Alexandra’s Royal Naval Nursing Service or the reserve therefor, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>enrolled as a medical or dental practitioner employed with the Medical Branch or Dental Branch of The Royal Navy with naval status for general service.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote>1946, c. 34, s. 2.</HistoricalNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>War Service Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Members of W.R.N.S. and S.A.M.N.S. deemed to be veterans, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>Every person domiciled and resident in Canada who served outside Canada at any time since September 10, 1939 as a member of the Women’s Royal Naval Services or of the South African Military Nursing Service and was domiciled in Canada at the time of becoming such a member is deemed, on the termination of that service,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to be a veteran within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Veterans' Land Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Veterans Insurance Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">War Veterans Allowance Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Veterans Affairs Act</XRefExternal>, to have served in the naval, army or air forces of Her Majesty;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>for the purposes of section 26 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">War Service Grants Act</XRefExternal>, to have served on active service in any of the naval, army or air forces of His Majesty other than those raised in Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in the case of a member of the Women’s Royal Naval Services, for the purposes of section 65 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Pension Act</XRefExternal>, to have served in the naval, army or air forces or the merchant navy of the United Kingdom; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>in the case of a member of the South African Military Nursing Service, for the purposes of section 66 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Pension Act</XRefExternal>, to have served in the naval, army or air forces or the merchant navy of a member of the Commonwealth other than Canada and the United Kingdom.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote>1946, c. 34, s. 3; 2000, c. 34, s. 91.</HistoricalNote></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Rules and regulations</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make such rules and regulations as may be necessary or advisable to give effect to the provisions of this Act.</Text><HistoricalNote>1946, c. 34, s. 4.</HistoricalNote></Section></Body></Statute>